<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-08-12T19:42:51+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wikimedia Design Blog</title><subtitle>Make sharing of knowledge easy and joyful, for everyone.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Improving search on Wikimedia Commons</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/08/12/media-search.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving search on Wikimedia Commons" /><published>2021-08-12T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/08/12/media-search</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/08/12/media-search.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/derrellwilliams&quot;&gt;Matthew Williams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people don’t realize that along with Wikipedia, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Foundation&lt;/a&gt; hosts a number of other projects, ranging from reference projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Wiktionary:Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wiktionary&lt;/a&gt; to software projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki&quot;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt;. These projects belong to everyone and like Wikipedia, are free to use to further our goal of providing the essential infrastructure for free knowledge &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; is one of these projects and is the world’s largest free-to-use library of illustrations, photos, drawings, videos, and music. Wikimedia Commons hosts more than 71 million freely usable media files&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to which anyone can contribute. It also hosts and organizes a majority of the media you encounter on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, one of the tasks of the structured data team, a cross-functional product team at the Wikimedia Foundation, was to focus on how to improve the search experience on Wikimedia Commons to better surface all of the media files contributed by people from around the world. One of the key tenets of this work was making the experience less intimidating, in particular to those not familiar with Wikimedia Commons. Being able to support a wide range of use-cases, from power users like museums digitizing their photography collection to a high school student using Wikimedia Commons for the first time to find free usable media to complete a science project, was critical to building a successful search experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious area the team focused on was ways to improve search accuracy since it doesn’t matter what you do with the presentation if the actual results aren’t mapping to the expectations of the searcher. However, this article, being written by the designer on the team, will be focused on the work that was done to ensure a much better experience that was created to complement these improved search results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the average person hears that I’m the designer on the Growth team for Wikipedia, there’s a common misconception that it’s about growing the number of readers, the more commonly thought of “Wikipedia user”. However, our team was formed almost three years ago with a different challenge and audience as our focus. This article aims to tell the six-part story of how and why we started this team, and all the failures, learnings, and successes we’ve had since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;baseline-research&quot;&gt;Baseline research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Special_Search_on_Commons.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Special Search on Commons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Largely untouched in its 17-year history, a screenshot of search on Wikimedia Commons before we started this project. | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Special_Search_on_Commons.jpg&quot;&gt;Special Search on Commons&lt;/a&gt; | Public Domain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We kicked this project off with a round of research to get a more honest understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of search on Wikimedia Commons. With only a few quotes from the participants of this research, you can see what we were up against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is so much text and details, it was hard to find what I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was frustrating to find all of the advanced search options, I figured it out after a while but didn’t expect to find them where I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t feel like a very nice display of results…difficult to see the details and evaluate the results with such small images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It feels complicated and the images are hard to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s extra work to  navigate back and forth between the file page and search to get everything I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I don’t trust it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can read, there was room for improvement. We needed to make the search experience more familiar and easy to use. Image search on the web is not a novel problem but the uniqueness of search on Wikimedia Commons was detrimental to casual users and those not intimately familiar with the project. With over 3 million daily page views&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on Wikimedia Commons, it’s more than obvious we needed to build a tool that made sense to everyone and aligned closer to their expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also knew that our most passionate contributors to the Wikimedia Commons project needed certain features and tools to help with their work. Would it be possible to make an experience that both catered to those unfamiliar with Wikimedia Commons and those that use it every day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-a-more-functional-and-familiar-interface&quot;&gt;Creating a more functional and familiar interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the search experience on Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Upon clicking of a result, you can see more information in a “quick view panel” | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg&quot;&gt;Search on Wikimedia Commons with Quick View&lt;/a&gt; | By Matthew Williams | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working through a myriad of wireframes, ideas, and approaches with the team, we began to arrive at some key areas we were going to focus on. One of the more visually obvious changes we started with was moving towards a grid layout that more effectively uses the space and highlights the media shown. Even with images around twice as large, we are able to show around three times as many results before needing to scroll. With as many results as we have, this helped users more quickly parse what Wikimedia Commons has to offer. Other interface improvements included surfacing all the different media types available upfront, making filters easier to find and use, and adding more information to a “quick view panel” upon clicking to eliminate the need to leave the page as often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Media_Search_and_Other_File_Types.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of Media Search while searching for other file types&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Examples of the different search experiences per file type | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Media_Search_and_Other_File_Types.jpg&quot;&gt;Media Search and Other File Types.jpg&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also separated the different types of media files into tabs. It became clear throughout the conversations with research participants that combining all file types into one result set was overwhelming, especially when the majority of visitors just wanted to search for images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Media_Search_on_Mobile_Web.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of the search experience of Commons on Mobile Web&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of the new search on Wikimedia Commons on mobile web | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Media_Search_on_Mobile_Web.jpg&quot;&gt;Media Search on Mobile Web&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 30% of all Wikimedia Commons usage&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-3&quot; id=&quot;ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on mobile web, we also wanted to make sure that all of these improvements were considered and easy to use on a mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-input&quot;&gt;Community Input&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear from research and usability studies that we were making progress with those less familiar with Wikimedia Commons, but what about those who use it the most frequently, like the countless contributors and volunteers, galleries, libraries, and museums?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new search experience was designed and built with these communities’ involvement from the ground up, with Wikimedia Commons contributors involved from conception and design to prototyping to the final push for feature completion prior to launch. The team planned a robust feedback cycle for sharing, bringing in information, iterating, and communicating with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community involvement began in May 2020 with sharing the ideas and designs, and by June the community was using a prototype. Over the next nine months, the development team would go through six distinct feedback cycles, with a total of 24 community members participating and leaving detailed ideas, comments, concerns, and questions to improve the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial feedback was positive and helped us refine many aspects of the new experience. For example, one of the many pieces of useful feedback was a request for a filter that was able to search specifically for images that had received an assessment. Assessments are a system that the community has created to recognize important contributions across Wikimedia Commons, with groupings such as featured pictures, valued images, quality images, and picture of the day. This filter in particular was an excellent suggestion that we were able to implement that really sets Wikimedia Commons apart from other image searching tools with its human-powered curation at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making significant progress, we completed a wide array of usability tests to understand if the answers and changes we had applied from the initial baseline research were actually improving the experience. Here are some of the quotes from those interviews:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much clearer and simpler to use. I prefer this version because the images are bigger. There were so many details in the old search that it was hard to see what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is comparatively much simpler and clearer to understand, with less space wasted in this format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It feels easier because it requires less clicking and the options are more visible. It also had more images to see at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is more intuitive, user friendly and easier to navigate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This feels much easier to operate and it is comfortable to use. It was much simpler in style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also conducted a survey in late December 2020/early January 2021, asking users directly if they had a preference for the new search experience or legacy search. We received 40 responses, again showing a preference for the new search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the evidence from that research and analysis, as well as the qualitative and quantitative feedback from the community, we decided to make this new search experience the default search on Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this update, we hope to have made finding and discovering this amazing treasure trove of freely usable media on the internet just a bit easier while honoring all of the hard work and contributions people around the world have made to Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Statistics&quot;&gt;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Statistics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=all-access&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=all-access&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=mobile-web&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=mobile-web&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The new search experience on Wikimedia Commons</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Nurturing newbies: Growing Wikipedia contributors by Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nurturing newbies: Growing Wikipedia contributors by Design" /><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@reetssydney&quot;&gt;Rita Ho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the average person hears that I’m the designer on the Growth team for Wikipedia, there’s a common misconception that it’s about growing the number of readers, the more commonly thought of “Wikipedia user”.  However, our team was formed almost three years ago with a different challenge and audience as our focus. This article aims to tell the six-part story of how and why we started this team, and all the failures, learnings, and  successes we’ve had since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant the seeds for Growth: Research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The set up: Team process &amp;amp; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design experiments 1, 2, and 3: Down, up, and up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now what? Doubling down and scaling up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-identify-the-problem&quot;&gt;1. Identify the problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s commonly known that Wikipedia is a multilingual project, one thing that may be surprising is how much variation there is between articles on the same topic in different languages. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canel%C3%A9&quot;&gt;French canelé article&lt;/a&gt; has a fairly different history on the origins for the small pastries than its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canel%C3%A9&quot;&gt;English version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This is because each article version is written by its own community of editors, not machine translated&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The diversity and breadth of content across around 300 languages is awesome, but it also presents a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How might we grow knowledge across all languages?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Currently the largest Wikipedia language is English, with ~6.3 million articles&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-3&quot; id=&quot;ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Contrast this with the Hindi version (the 4th most spoken first-language, just behind English&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-4&quot; id=&quot;ref-4&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) with ~147K articles&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-5&quot; id=&quot;ref-5&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This highlights the many knowledge gaps that exist on Wikipedia – and how it is a massive barrier to information access for those who don’t know English. To continue on the case of the canelé, (as of writing) there is no article about the deliciously rich heritage of these pastries documented on Hindi Wikipedia at all. Or to give a more ‘serious’ example of the knowledge gap (though one would argue pastries are a culturally significant item), the Hindi edition also lacks biographies for prominent figures like Nobel laureate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ir%C3%A8ne_Joliot-Curie&quot;&gt;Irène Joliot-Curie&lt;/a&gt;, or conservationist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dian_Fossey&quot;&gt;Dian Fossey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/irene-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Iréne Joliot-Curie's English Wikipedia page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; Screenshot of “Irène Joliot-Curie” from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irène_Joliot-Curie&quot;&gt;English Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; (2021) with a pop-up dialog on the bottom left with a message that the article does not yet exist in Hindi Wikipedia. | Accessed 2021-05-18 | text CC-BY-SA-3.0 | ™ Wikipedia logo | Other media in this image may be subject to other terms.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/vision/&quot;&gt;vision&lt;/a&gt; is to ensure that every single human being can freely share in the world’s knowledge, which can only be accomplished if more people contribute to that corpus of knowledge across all languages. Unfortunately Wikipedia has seen the number of contributors (a.k.a. editors) either stagnate or shrink over the years, and struggle to attract and retain new folks. A notable metric is that around 94% of first time editors don’t ever stick around to make a second edit&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-6&quot; id=&quot;ref-6&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Growth team was formed at the Wikimedia Foundation in July 2018 to directly address this problem. There need to be significant increases in the number of contributors  as well as a more diverse contributor pool in order to supply knowledge that is relevant to everyone in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, the Growth team’s objective is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase contributor &lt;strong&gt;activation&lt;/strong&gt; (people who make a first edit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase contributor &lt;strong&gt;retention&lt;/strong&gt; (people who come back another day to make subsequent edits)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also concentrated on working with smaller-to-medium sized Wikipedias to help promote the diversity of the contributors (rather than the larger, established language Wikipedias who tend to be an established homogenous group).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-planting-the-seeds-for-growth-research&quot;&gt;2. Planting the seeds for Growth: Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inception of our work actually began a year earlier with the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/New_Editor_Experiences&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences&lt;/a&gt;” research project in 2017. This was a foundational research project aimed at learning as much as possible about new editors in Korean and Czech Wikipedias – two languages chosen as representative of many smaller Wikipedias. The project was conducted not only in collaboration with a research partner Reboot, but also with Wikipedians in Korea and Czech, with a “Community ambassador” role created for a long-term active member in each language, to encourage their communities’ participation in the project. In all, 64 interviews were conducted in Korea and Czechia to draw out a number of important insights about new editors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/new-editor-research.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page of the new editors experiences research.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left: &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:New_Editor_Experiences_summary_of_findings,_August_2017.pdf&amp;amp;page=12&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences summary of findings, August 2017 - Page 12&lt;/a&gt; | By Reboot and the Wikimedia Foundation | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; || Right: &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences_user_personas,_August_2017.pdf&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences user personas, August 2017 - Page 1&lt;/a&gt; | By Reboot and the Wikimedia Foundation | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of the research was identifying that contributors have very different motivations for editing (represented in the personas). Despite their differences, all these newcomer personas encountered one or more of these key barriers to editing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical barrier (e.g. How do I write in code?)&lt;/strong&gt; – Newcomers have trouble finding and using editing tools.  A lot of our editing tools can seem too overwhelmingly open-ended and complex for them to know where to even start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptual barrier (e.g. What is “notability”?)&lt;/strong&gt; – How do they write the “Wikipedia way”? What does it mean when their subject is not notable enough? What is NPOV?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural (e.g. Why are people so mean?)&lt;/strong&gt; – Newcomers are often unaware of the collaborative effort involved in writing Wikipedia. In turn, they can’t easily become part of the “community” of established and active editors, because they don’t know it exists. And for many, their first interaction is not positive because it’s someone telling them they did something wrong, or reverting their edit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/new-editors-barriers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing three icons - no wikitext, warning sign and a sad message emoji&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration of the three key barriers (Technical, Conceptual, and Cultural) newcomers face when editing Wikipedia. By Rita Ho | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the different newcomer needs, motivations, and challenges being surfaced, the research concluded with a number of recommendations. This was where the Growth team came into the picture, as it was formed to take action on these recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim was to experiment with design interventions to drive increases in activation and retention of newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-the-set-up-team-process-and-principles&quot;&gt;3. The set up: Team process and principles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanilla Ice once sang, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ice_Ice_Baby&quot;&gt;Stop, collaborate and listen&lt;/a&gt;”. Our team works according to similar principles, but in a different order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-collaborate-in-the-open&quot;&gt;1. Collaborate in the open&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modelling on the success of the New Editor Experiences research approach, a core part of our process is to ensure close communication and collaboration with the communities in which we work. The first thing we did when the team was formed was to partner with four “pilot” languages (Korean, Czech, Arabic, and Vietnamese) that we would collaborate with in controlled experiments. In addition to the team’s Community Relations Specialist (a liaison between Wikimedia product teams and volunteer community members), we created a “Community Ambassador” role for each pilot language – a representative who helps us to collaborate with their respective members on a range of tasks such as translation, communicating our progress, and recruiting others to participate in our project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/growth-team-wikipedias-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Logos of the Growth team and pilot wikis&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Top: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Growth_team_logo_-_en.svg&quot;&gt;Growth team logo - en&lt;/a&gt; | By Rita Ho | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;  || Bottom (left to right): &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia/2.0#SVG&quot;&gt;Wikipedia logo 2.0&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-ar.svg&quot;&gt;Arabic&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-cs.svg&quot;&gt;Czech&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-ko.svg&quot;&gt;Korean&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-vi.svg&quot;&gt;Vietnamese&lt;/a&gt; | By Wikimedia Foundation &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; (™ Wikipedia logo)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, not only do we collaborate with our communities, but because it’s Wikipedia – anyone can be a part of the community – so we work in the public. We post in-progress designs and engineering updates that anyone interested can react to and give feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-listen&quot;&gt;2. Listen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We listen to all the feedback coming back on our work, from usability testing on early stage designs through to analysing data from our released experiments in order to decide how to improve. We also listen to our community partners, and try to ensure there is sufficient flexibility and adaptability in designs to work for different groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-stop-if-its-not-working&quot;&gt;3. Stop (if it’s not working)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very important work principle we try to keep in mind is that experiments fail. When we see something is not working, we try to make a clean stop and take learnings from that failure to make the next experiment better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, nested in this last principle is making sure we are measuring results rigorously, and running &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treatment_and_control_groups&quot;&gt;controlled experiments&lt;/a&gt; for everything we try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-design-experiments-1-2-and-3-down-up-and-up&quot;&gt;4. Design experiments 1, 2, and 3: Down, up, and up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate our process and journey, I’d like to talk about three key experiments our team has worked on based on major recommendations from the design research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-help-panel-a-helpful-failure&quot;&gt;#1 Help panel: A helpful failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/growth-help-panel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of the help panel&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshots of the Help panel open over the “Hamlet” article from four Wikipedia languages (left to right: Arabic, Czech, Korean, and Vietnamese). | Text from Wikimedia projects are &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-3.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our first experiments was based on research recommendations for better &lt;strong&gt;in-context help&lt;/strong&gt; (small doses of help relevant to the activity being done at that moment), as well as &lt;strong&gt;human-to-human help&lt;/strong&gt; (providing a real connection to a friendly person in the community). In a nutshell, the feature was a help panel tool available to newcomers when they opened an article for editing, and allowed them to search and/or ask questions to experienced users about how to edit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for this design to work in practice, not only did we consult with all our pilot wikis for buy-in on the idea, via our ambassadors, but we needed these very experienced editors from each language to sign up to answer questions. So community engagement was doubly important for this experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engagement with the help panel was quite high&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-7&quot; id=&quot;ref-7&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; considering its ancillary placement and function, so we considered it a positive sign that newcomers want in-context and human help.  An interesting tidbit was that there were cultural differences in the usage, where Koreans asked very few questions compared to the other pilot wikis. However, per our “Stop if it’s not working” principle, we ultimately didn’t see any change in more people starting to edit or being retained, so we paused further iteration and went to try a different idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-newcomer-homepage-a-welcoming-place&quot;&gt;#2 Newcomer homepage: A welcoming place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Newcomer homepage was the second project built as a result of  the usability testing of our earlier work, where we noticed a lot of test participants expected a dashboard or some homepage to orient themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we created this “newcomer homepage” that gives them that clear place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its first iteration, it contained a few different modules that help someone learn about editing, encourage them to create a user page, and seek help from both the help desk or from a specific experienced editor assigned as their mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was encouraging to see people engaging with this page and returning to it on multiple days to take different actions. One of our most important observations was that the most popular button was for creating a “user page”, which is like a user profile in which newcomers can identify themselves to others.  The engagement with this button gave us a very strong signal that newcomers will start contributing if given a call-to-action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/interaction-percentage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing interaction percentages&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Image is a derivative of &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Homepage_mockup_2019-04-24.png&quot;&gt;Homepage mockup 2019-04-24&lt;/a&gt;, by Alessandro Contini, used under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;, with percentage values added to indicate the different amount of interactions from newcomers on various parts of the homepage, showing the “create user page” call to action as having the highest percent of clicks. This image is licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; [Rita Ho].&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-newcomer-tasks-suggestions-to-get-started&quot;&gt;#3 Newcomer tasks: Suggestions to get started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural next step after seeing newcomers interacting and seeking out editing actions on the newcomer homepage was to give them opportunities to edit actual Wikipedia articles. We did this in the form of newcomer task recommendations, a feature we call “Suggested edits” on the homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on foundational research and cumulative feedback from previous experiments, we knew that many newcomers either arrive with a very challenging edit in mind (e.g., write a new article from scratch) from which failure becomes a demoralising dead-end, or else they don’t have any edits in mind at all, and never find their footing as contributors. The “Suggested edits” module offers tasks ranging from easy tasks (like copyediting or adding links), to harder tasks (like adding citations or expanding articles) that newcomers can filter to based on their specific interests (e.g., copyedit articles about “Food and drink”). This feature is intended to cater to both groups – a clear way to start editing for those who don’t know what they want to do, and for those who do have a difficult edit in mind, it provides a learning pathway to build up their skills first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/suggested-edit-mobile.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of Suggested edits on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Suggested_edits_-_sample_mobile_screens.png&quot;&gt;Suggested edits - sample mobile screens&lt;/a&gt; | By RHo (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch, and as we added more editing guidance and improvements to the homepage design over multiple iterations and variant tests (a subject for another post), we’ve seen steady increases in edits and number of editors using it. In other words, the release of this experimental feature saw us succeed in increasing editor activation and retention. 🙌 🙌&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-now-what--doubling-down-and-scaling-up&quot;&gt;5. Now what?  Doubling down and scaling up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success we saw in the pilot languages meant that we are able to work on the next great problem to solve: how can we scale up and encourage all the other Wikipedias to adopt our features?&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-8&quot; id=&quot;ref-8&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Luckily, one of the benefits of working in this somewhat slow-and-steady approach is that as the team consults with the different language communities, we’ve got a lot of supporting data and built up a lot of trust from collaborating with our pilot communities which has helped encourage many language communities to sign up. To date, we’ve added the features to 35 Wikipedias, which, when accounting for the relative sizes of the languages, amounting to nearly half (42% to be exact) of all newcomers to Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/languages-with-growth-features.png&quot; alt=&quot;List of languages where growth features are enabled&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration showing that the 35 Wikipedia languages which currently have the Growth team’s newcomer features accounts for nearly half of all newcomers (new accounts) on Wikipedia. | By Rita Ho CC BY-SA 4.0, Wikimedia Foundation CC BY-SA 3.0 (™ Wikipedia logo)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the time it has taken from the initial failed experiment with the help panel to the modest success we’ve had so far in increasing new contributors, these were my biggest realisations about what it is to design with and for the open community of communities that is Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of collaborating with communities for adoption &amp;amp; understanding.&lt;/strong&gt; Collaborating with our communities is paramount for trust, acceptance, and improved user experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimenting with an open mind&lt;/strong&gt; (and being ready to fail with a next plan).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There’s no one size fits all for everyone.&lt;/strong&gt; Accepting that actually, there is no perfect design for everyone. Seeing how different cultures and languages react to and use the same design differently has made me realise the importance of allowing a degree of customization, to empower different communities to figure out what’s best for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change takes time and perseverance&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-whats-next&quot;&gt;6. What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve now established a good cadence to our experiment-and-scale-up-on-success approach, and as the Growth team features become available on more Wikipedias, our ultimate goal is that one day these will no longer be experiments but a core part of welcoming editors to the Wikipedia community. So, mission accomplished right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thankfully, my job as a designer is not done here.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that all the design interventions so far have been about trying to get newcomers to succeed by giving them access to help and suggestions to edit using the existing editing interface. At the moment, if someone selects a suggested edit to “copy edit” an article, they don’t receive any specific pointers about what part of the article needs help with fixing spelling or grammar. Our newcomers still need to know which of the many editing tools they should be using, and will often need to ask for more guidance. And that’s what instigated our team’s latest design exploration: &lt;strong&gt;Structured tasks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that instead of guiding people through the current complex, open-ended editing UI, we create new, easier ways to edit. And we will do this by breaking down editing tasks you can do on Wikipedia into a series of single smaller steps or “structured tasks” instead. Something that newcomers can quickly and easily accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first structured task that we have designed is to review suggestions by an algorithm to make words in a Wikipedia article link to other articles, and we are again approaching this by seeing how this new task type is working firstly for our pilot Wikipedias by the start of June 2021. I’m anxiously optimistic about  how this next experiment goes, fodder for  another post, but until then (and until there’s time for another blog post), you can learn more about our work on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot;&gt;team page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;
Cover image by Rizzelli Stefania. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:MUFFE_E_LIEVITI_ISOLATI_NELLE_FARINE_ALIMENTARI.jpg&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-4.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Marshall Miller, Jessica Klein, and Margeigh Novotny for your feedback and editing help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;Digression: As of 2021-05-17, the French version of the Canelé article talks about its creation being connected to wine production in the Bordeaux region: since only egg whites were used in the “fining” wine process, the excess egg yolks were used in canelé-making. This is contrasted with the English article which focuses on the origins of the name, and is much more circumspect about its origins.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;Wikipedia does, however, also offer a pretty great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Content_translation&quot;&gt;Content Translation&lt;/a&gt; tool that helps multilingual people translate articles into different languages they know.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-4&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-4&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_languages_by_number_of_native_speakers&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_languages_by_number_of_native_speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-5&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-5&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindi_Wikipedia&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindi_Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-6&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; Ripstra, A. &amp;amp; Quinn, N. (2018). “New Editor Experiences, Wikimania 2018” [PDF Presentation]. Slides 4-5. Available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimania2018.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences,_Wikimania_2018.pdf&quot;&gt;https://wikimania2018.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences,_Wikimania_2018.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2021-05-18)
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-7&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-7&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; 13-29% of newcomers opened the help panel. Of those, 43-59% took some action.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-8&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-8&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;Some of you may be flummoxed that it is a necessary step at all to encourage the different communities to adopt our features. This is one of the interesting things about designing for Wikipedia! Communities have the option to not adopt the features we create, literally being able to change or turn off features if their particular community has not reached consensus. This is what makes developing trust and collaboration particularly vital, and also helps explain our slower pace of change.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Reflections on a multi-year effort now bearing fruit</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/isolated-food-flours.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/isolated-food-flours.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bringing Wikipedia to the homescreen on iOS</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing Wikipedia to the homescreen on iOS" /><published>2021-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://carolynlimadeo.com/&quot;&gt;Carolyn Li-Madeo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepakmantena.com/&quot;&gt;Deepak Mantena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Apple introduced an update to &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/system-capabilities/widgets&quot;&gt;widgets&lt;/a&gt; with iOS 14, the Wikipedia iOS team was excited to take the opportunity to rethink our own. With the ability to place widgets right on the home screen, the team was curious about how we could highlight Wikipedia content in a way that was visually engaging, glanceable and up-to-date. For our first suite of home screen widgets, we built off of elements from the app’s Explore Feed to design and build three new widgets for iOS 14: On this day, Picture of the day and Top read on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we’ll share some of our widget building process – from design to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of various iOS widgets&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Widget designs we explored throughout our product process&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;design-principles-for-the-wikipedia-ios-widgets&quot;&gt;Design principles for the Wikipedia iOS widgets&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iOS team defined the following design principles at the start of the project, which helped us to decide what features to highlight in our new widgets as well as to prioritize features like dark mode and supporting all three sizes for each of our widgets. These principles also guided the visual and interaction design of the widgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-first&quot;&gt;Content first&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This design principle comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#trustworthy-yet-joyful&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Design Style Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People come to Wikimedia projects for their content. Our solutions should help to facilitate its creation, consumption, and sharing — without getting in the way. Our content (facts, images, quotes, etc.) is our most representative element, and needs to be emphasized in our solutions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came to applying this principle to our widgets, we used this guidance to place a strong focus on the beautiful images and community written content in our widgets. Great encyclopedic content is why many people love Wikipedia and we wanted to ensure that our designs placed Wikipedia content front and center, with other design elements like graphs and headings taking a supporting role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focused&quot;&gt;Focused&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home screens can easily become cluttered or distracting. With so many different apps, widgets and notifications pulling readers in different directions each time that they open their phone, we didn’t want to add to the noise or create unnecessary friction. We aimed to design widgets that were beautiful, glanceable and focused on a single element or content type from Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dynamic&quot;&gt;Dynamic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia projects are constantly changing and evolving. The projects are shaped by volunteer contributors from across the world. Readers also make their mark on Wikipedia, by following their unique interests and learning more about current events. With this in mind we want to highlight and celebrate the liveliness of Wikipedia with designs that reflect the dynamic nature of the Wikimedia projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;customizable&quot;&gt;Customizable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Widgets can come in three sizes (small, medium and large) and two reading themes (light and dark). We want to ensure that our readers can access the information that they are interested in, in a layout and theme that works well for them. Building off of the frameworks provided by Apple, we want to ensure that people can read comfortably (and in their preferred language, when available), regardless of the time of day or night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designing-the-wikipedia-ios-widgets&quot;&gt;Designing the Wikipedia iOS widgets&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came time to begin designing our widgets, we looked to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2020/10103/&quot;&gt;WWDC 2020 talk on designing widgets&lt;/a&gt; and the information available through &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/system-capabilities/widgets&quot;&gt;Apple’s Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. We wanted to ensure that whatever widgets we designed would adhere not only to our defined design principles but also to Apple’s design guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some key takeaways from Apple’s guidelines were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilize a standard margin of 16pts for comfortable reading and design consistency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on highlighting content that will change often to avoid widgets becoming stale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create designs for both light and dark mode, or focus on creating designs that will work in both reading modes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase information with each widget size. Larger widgets should contain more information than their size small counterparts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SF Pro should be used over custom fonts so that widgets look at home with widgets from other apps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember that the associated app’s name will appear under each widget, so it isn’t necessary to include app icons or  app names on the widget itself unless the widget is related to a content aggregator.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shapes inside of a widget should match the corner radius of the widget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be mindful of how many deep links each widget size supports. As small widgets only support a single deep link, while there may be room to include more information, small widgets will only be able to link to a single location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We utilized the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/resources/&quot;&gt;templates provided in the Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; to jumpstart the sketching process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-picture-of-the-day-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the Picture of the day widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-picture-of-the-day-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the picture of the day widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Picture of the day widget features beautiful, hi-res imagery from Wikimedia Commons&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Vulpes_vulpes_Mallnitz_01.jpg?fastcci_from=2194179&amp;amp;c1=2194179&amp;amp;c2=3943817&amp;amp;d1=15&amp;amp;d2=0&amp;amp;s=200&quot;&gt;Vulpes vulpes image&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Uoaei1&quot;&gt;Uoaei1&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first widget we designed was the Picture of the day widget. We wanted to start with something that would be easy to implement but also visually striking. Every day, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; community selects a freely usable image to be the ‘Picture of the day.’ These high-resolution images range from composite images of &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Acropoclipse.jpg&quot;&gt;lunar eclipses&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Glaciar_Margerie,_Parque_Nacional_Bah%C3%ADa_del_Glaciar,_Alaska,_Estados_Unidos,_2017-08-19,_DD_33.jpg&quot;&gt;striking landscapes&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:D%C3%BClmen,_Wildpark_--_2015_--_8894-8.jpg&quot;&gt;around the world&lt;/a&gt; (and much more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing this widget we wanted to make sure that the beautiful images were given as much room as possible, with other necessary information (like copyright and the widget title) coming second. This widget really embodies our design principle of ‘Content first’ by placing an emphasis on imagery over secondary information. When designing this widget, we also had to consider how cropping might affect different aspect ratios and photo subjects. With each increase in widget size, more of the image is shown and on the largest size the first three lines of the image description are also displayed. Tapping on the widget in any size deep links you into a full screen view of the featured image in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this design, we did not make separate light and dark mode designs as the content is full bleed and we typically display description text over a dark background in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-on-this-day-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the On this day widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-on-this-day-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of on this day widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The On this day widget highlights an event that occurred on this day in history
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love helping to ignite new &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki_rabbit_hole&quot;&gt;rabbit holes&lt;/a&gt; for our readers, so we created a widget that would change each day and encourage readers to check out an article they might not have read before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of this widget was based off of the ‘On this day’ card from the app’s Explore feed. Both the widget and the Explore feed card highlight the work of Wikipedia’s volunteer editors, who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Selected_anniversaries&quot;&gt;compile and annotate lists of important events throughout history&lt;/a&gt; for each day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering how to adapt this feature from the app to the three widget sizes, we began first with the largest widget size. The largest widget size allowed us to include multiple tap targets (linking directly to the associated article or to a timeline view of the day’s events) and to include a splash of typography that illustrates the day’s date and date range. Including the timeline element also helped to create a sense of continuity between the widget and the existing feature on the app which utilizes the same timeline design. With the smaller widgets we focused more on the event text (removing the card representing the related article) and utilized a single tap target for both of these sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the feature is already available on the app in &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2017/12/04/ios-app-dark-theme/&quot;&gt;our four reading themes&lt;/a&gt;, it was easy to support both light and dark modes for this widget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-on-this-day-widget-changes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of changes made&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Changes made after receiving feedback from designers at Apple
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing a first draft of our widgets, we received some very helpful feedback from the designers at Apple, who suggested we move the puck on the timeline up in order to better mimic the widget’s corner radius. It was a change of just a few pixels, but really helped to balance the visual design of the widgets and we were super grateful to have their feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-top-read-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the Top read widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-top-read-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the top read widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Top read widget highlights which articles are popular in your language’s Wikipedia
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing what the world is reading on Wikipedia is a constant source of fascination for many readers and editors (ourselves included!). We had previously supported a Top read widget in the older iOS style and were glad to have the time to be able to update this widget and bring it to the home screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first considerations with this widget was how to display articles that might not have an associated image, without needing to use a placeholder image. We wanted to avoid placeholder images as they don’t include relevant, encyclopedic content and can be repetitive if reproduced multiple times in a list. This was most important for the smallest size widget which only has space to link to one article. For the small widget with an available image we went with a full bleed image with a small spark map representing the popularity of the article over the past week. This sparkline was then enlarged and used as the primary imagery for articles that did not have an associated image. The sparklines were also included in the largest widget size, where we had just enough room to fit the top four articles, their associated sparklines and their title descriptions. For the medium sized widget we wanted to ensure that we could show more articles than were available on the small widget, so we focused on presenting two articles without their sparklines vs. one article with more meta information than we could show on the small widget size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This widget was also quite easy to translate into both light and dark designs as we were able to utilize our existing color palettes, which were designed to share the green used in the sparklines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-widgets&quot;&gt;Building the widgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new widgets also gave the engineering team an opportunity to experiment with new platform technologies. The widgets are implemented using &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/swiftui&quot;&gt;SwiftUI&lt;/a&gt; – Apple’s new user interface toolkit that aims to help bridge the gap between design and implementation. Converting the Top read sparkline we currently use in the app to SwiftUI provided valuable practical experience. It was encouraging to see potentially complex interface elements translate elegantly to the new framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineering work began during the early betas of iOS 14. The biggest implementation challenge we faced was using the unfinished development tools. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debugger&quot;&gt;debugger&lt;/a&gt;, a tool used during development to examine the state of running widgets, often failed to work at all. Another challenge we encountered was balancing the expectation of always updated widget data with being considerate of the device’s battery life. This remains something we’re interested in refining – &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;contributions are always welcome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;increased-multilingual-support&quot;&gt;Increased multilingual support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently the widgets utilize each reader’s primary language as set in app settings. We would like to provide a way for multilingual readers to set a language preference on a per-widget basis, which would enable readers to keep an eye on what articles are trending on multiple Wikipedias or see what was happening on this day in history across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-dynamic-on-this-day-widget&quot;&gt;More dynamic On this day widget&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The On this day widget currently updates once a day and highlights a single event each day. In the future we would like to make this widget more dynamic by featuring multiple events each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-widget-ideas&quot;&gt;Future widget ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints we were unable to build all of the widgets that we dreamed up. In the future we would love to update three of our older style widgets: Today’s featured article, In the news and Continue reading. Additionally we had some ideas around a widget that would enable you to jump straight into exploring Wikipedia with deep links into features like randomizer or reading lists. Finally, we had designed a map based widget that built off of our Places feature and would have enabled readers to quickly locate and read Wikipedia articles about landmarks near them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-us-in-developing-and-designing-new-widgets&quot;&gt;Join us in developing and designing new widgets!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS app is open source&lt;/a&gt; and contributions are always welcome! If you are interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T257370&quot;&gt;developing one of our already designed widgets&lt;/a&gt; or if you have an idea for something new, please do reach out! You can follow along with the team’s work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/project/view/782/&quot;&gt;Phabricator&lt;/a&gt; and file design or development tickets there, or feel free to contribute to the project on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Rita Ho, Robin Schoenbaechler, Matt Cleinman and Toni Sevener for editing help. Thank you to Deepak Mantena for writing the ‘Building the widgets’ section.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How we designed and built our iOS 14 widgets</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How we hire UX designers at Wikimedia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How we hire UX designers at Wikimedia" /><published>2021-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;In the interest of providing more clarity over our hiring process, this article will attempt to answer some of the questions that people who want to apply for a UX design job at Wikimedia may have...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lucyblackwell&quot;&gt;Lucy Blackwell&lt;/a&gt; : Senior Design Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-alignment&quot;&gt;Mission Alignment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a mission driven organisation on a quest to support every human being in freely sharing knowledge.  We’re a non-profit operating one of the world’s top five websites, Wikipedia. We believe that those who are passionate about our cause will be the best contributors to our mission. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/mission/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Wikimedia,disseminate%20it%20effectively%20and%20globally.&quot;&gt;our mission&lt;/a&gt; and these are our &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/values/&quot;&gt;values&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first things first, check them out before going any further, and just be honest… is this what you’re into? If so, why?  We want to know! It’s also totally fine if it’s not, but we really only hire people who are as passionate about our mission as us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; The best way to show us your passion for the role is in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cover_letter&quot;&gt;cover letter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-skills&quot;&gt;Design skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to know that you have all the design skills needed to do the job. We have high standards in the team which we want to uphold, so we’re looking for people who are motivated to do their best work with us, people we can support to grow and evolve here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our job descriptions outline the specific skills we’re looking for in each role, but just to briefly summarise, for any of our UX designer roles we seek folks that can envision and create experiences that reduce complexity. English Wikipedia has just celebrated its 20th birthday, and we are a fairly small design team for the size of our main website, so there are many legacy UX issues to be addressed. Designers at Wikimedia need to be able to break down a complicated existing experience and come up with a much simpler, clearer solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a highly user-focused organisation with two key user groups on Wikipedia; the readers, and the editors (who we refer to as our community). Our community is very active and engaged, with many of the editors volunteering huge amounts of their time to write and edit content on Wikipedia. They have lots of great perspectives to add and are often the drivers behind the changes we decide to make on our platform(s). This means that for designers, we look for people who are comfortable, or excited by the opportunity to be very engaged with the community throughout their design process.  We value a transparent work style using open source platforms and public task boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, we are a truly global product.  Wikipedia is available in around 300 languages. We design for everyone!  This means that many of the design decisions we make have to consider carefully the global reach of our platform. In addition, we need to make sure the platform we’re evolving is accessible too, so we do require a basic knowledge of how to apply accessibility standards to your designs, as part of our interview process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-portfolio&quot;&gt;Your portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your portfolio is going to be one of the best ways for you to show us your work before we’ve met.  We review portfolios to decide if we should chat further. No portfolio = no interview. For designers, portfolios are often more important than your CV or resume, this is because this is the place we can see how you think! When we look at portfolios we are trying to understand a few key things which are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the people you are designing for come first in your process?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have the ability to simplify complex problems?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you communicate your ideas and process clearly and simply?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you deliver effective solutions and pay attention to detail?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a hiring manager, I’ve had the privilege of looking through hundreds of portfolios over the years, and in my experience the ones that stand out are always those with 3 or 4 solid projects that clearly frame an interesting problem they had to solve and explain to me how they did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know designers spend hours and hours making their portfolios.  As you focus on the design of your portfolio, don’t forget the UX of your portfolio too. Your core user is going to be a recruiter or a hiring manager. That’s me! So here’s a few of my user needs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to be able to scan your portfolio in less than a minute, and find something that makes me want to look longer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to see your best work first. (I don’t need to see everything you’ve ever done)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to see your thinking process and how you break down problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to know what your specific role was in the projects you’re presenting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I understand that some of your work maybe under NDA, so I need you to tell me about this work in another way, like a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep it simple and just show your best work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-skills&quot;&gt;People skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our job descriptions we state ‘The right person is better than the right set of experiences.’ Of course we need to know you have the design skills, but we’re less concerned with ‘&lt;em&gt;where’&lt;/em&gt; you developed those skills. What we feel is more important is if you’re a great collaborator and can communicate your ideas clearly. This is not an optional skill, we actually see this as a core requirement for working in our team.  This doesn’t mean you have to be an extrovert though, you might have developed your own unique way of collaborating and communicating with others that fits your personality and abilities.  It also doesn’t mean english needs to be your first language, we just need to know that you can communicate your ideas in english to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’re a global organisation, it’s really important to us that our team represents some of the different aspects of the communities we serve.  We’re always looking to bring different perspectives into the team, because fundamentally we know that diverse teams deliver better products. This is why we’re a fully remote team. By hiring in many different places in the world, we have the best chance of attracting a wide-range of perspectives.  We currently have designers across 12 timezones from India to the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; In the interview, come prepared to share specific examples of how you’ve collaborated with people and overcome challenges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;levels&quot;&gt;Levels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UX designers in our team sit at 4 different levels based upon experience going from UX designer to Seniors, Leads up to Principals.  For each role, the job title and job description will show you what level of experience we’re looking for and what our expectations for your skills at that level are. Generally we won’t hire someone if they are over-qualified, or under-qualified for the level of the role we have listed, as this creates inequity in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll normally mention how many years of experience we expect someone to have at the level we’re recruiting for on the job spec, but this is purely a guide. We know that people grow and develop at different speeds and this is fine, so we’re really assessing your experience based upon the skills you demonstrate in your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-tasks&quot;&gt;Design tasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tools that we use to assess what level someone is at is a design task. We’re very aware that this is now a fairly controversial debate in the design community, for lots of good reasons.  We recently took a step back and reassessed the pros and cons of design tasks, but ultimately came back to the decision to continue to ask UX designers and Senior UX Designers to do design tasks in a time-boxed manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is that we have found that our design tasks serve a few key purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They allow us to see how candidates approach a problem within a time constraint.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They give the candidate an opportunity to demonstrate their thinking process to us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They allow candidates to be assessed more fairly against other candidates in the process who may have wildly different backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One thing we have realised, is that people with more time often spend longer on their tasks than the suggested time period. Whilst this clearly shows their passion for the role, it doesn’t feel entirely fair to those with other commitments that simply couldn’t put as much time into their task.  So, we’re now trialling a slightly different approach to the process in our next recruitment round, in the hopes that we can make things a bit fairer and less of a burden on candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve now explicitly time box the task to a maximum of 3 hours.  We’ll ask the candidate to let us know what time and date suits them to do the task, then we will send the task out at that exact time via email.  The candidate is then required to return the task by email within 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-interview-process&quot;&gt;Our interview process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each role, a hiring team is put together, each with specific roles in the hiring process. We have a step-by-step approach to interviewing, where you will have a series of interviews with different people from Wikimedia. Whilst there maybe some overlaps in questions, generally we try to make sure different areas are covered in different interviews. This process allows us to gather a collective view on a candidate. On average it can take approx. 1-2 months to complete all the steps in our process, although we’re currently looking at ways to speed this up. At any stage we may decide not to proceed further with a candidate as we don’t want to waste anyone’s time. Our process is continually evolving, but here’s where it stands today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1: Interview with Recruiter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss your experience and why you’re interested in working at Wikimedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2: Interview with Senior Design Manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss your background and design skills and where you’re looking to go in your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3: Design task&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Task will be sent out at a time of your choosing, upon which you will have 3 hours to complete the task and return it by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 4:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Panel interview with Designers, Product Manager &amp;amp; UX Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Part 1 - Designers:&lt;/em&gt; Present and discuss your design task, followed by UX and design focused discussion about how your design approaches and ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2 - Product Manager &amp;amp; UX Engineer:&lt;/em&gt; Discuss how you collaborate, agile development processes, accessibility guidelines and design systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Interview with the Senior Director of Strategy and Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss product strategy and other related questions specific to your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; The interview process is as much for your benefit at ours.  We try to leave time at the end of every interview for your questions, so come ready to ask all the things you want to know…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well that’s it for now, but we’re always looking to evolve and improve our processes.  We’re keen to be sure our hiring process is a good experience for you, the candidate.  If you’ve got any thoughts that could help us improve this experience, do let us know.  We’re especially interested in how we could make our hiring process even more inclusive.  Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;
Cover image by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/people/37804979@N00&quot;&gt;Tony Hisgett&lt;/a&gt; from Birmingham, UK. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Coloured_Lights_2_(5129805518).jpg&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC-BY-2.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This article attempts to answer some of the questions that people who want to apply for a UX design job at Wikimedia may have.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/colored-lights-hiring-ux-designer.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/colored-lights-hiring-ux-designer.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">People are talking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="People are talking" /><published>2021-03-10T00:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;Embarking on a design refresh of Wikipedia Talk pages — in three acts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://jessklein.is/&quot;&gt;Jess Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue&quot;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, when I started making edits to Wikipedia, it felt illicit; like doing graffiti or writing notes inside a library book. I would open up the article editor and stare at the screen in disbelief that I could change a page by just typing a few words and hitting “Publish changes”. But there I was, making changes to the world’s biggest encyclopedia, a site that sees 250 billion page views a year (on average). It was simultaneously exhilarating and anxiety-provoking. Was I editing the page correctly? Was the content that I was adding valuable? Was someone going to check my edits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not know that Talk pages existed for at least a year into my editing adventures, and when I did learn of them, I misunderstood their purpose. With a name like Talk pages (on English Wikipedia), I thought they were literally pages to discuss whatever article it was connected to (if it was attached in fact to an article page), assuming that the Talk page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;Artemisia Gentileschi&lt;/a&gt; would be a fan forum of sorts for admirers of this 16th-century artist. I have since learned that it works like this: every single page on Wikipedia has a corresponding page associated with it for discussions and these pages are called “Talk pages.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/talk-pages-top-level-navigation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Talk pages on mobile web&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;You can access Talk Pages the same way that you access articles (in the top level page navigation) on Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the purpose of Talk pages (the ones connected to articles), is to discuss with other volunteers ways to improve the article. So the Talk page on Artemisia Gentileschi is not a fan forum for her, but a set of conversations around how to improve the Artemisia Gentileschi article on Wikipedia. The page was actually created so that I could ask questions, ask for help or get reviews! I had found the secret entrance to an underground club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/not-fan-forum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a Talk page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Definitely not a fan forum! This is what the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;Talk page&lt;/a&gt; connected to the article on Artemisia Gentileschi looked like on January 6, 2021 at 11:58am EST. It contains lots of suggestions on how to improve the content of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;the article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the thing about clubs is that you have to know the rules (what to wear, how to talk to people, is it appropriate to dance?) in order to be part of the club. As you might have guessed, I didn’t know the rules — I didn’t even understand the language that I had to use in order to communicate with other people. This page sort of looked like people were writing and responding to questions, but when I went in to ask some questions myself, I was a mess. I couldn’t figure out where to post new topics, where to click to reply, how to sign my name, or, (if I even got this far) how to tell if someone was replying to my questions. Everything was written with what’s called wikitext (but at the time I just thought it was some sort of code), and it didn’t have any of the affordances that I expected from a forum. I couldn’t just click, type and publish. I had to type special characters to thread my conversations! Those were just the technical issues that I had with the page, to say nothing about understanding editing policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/fight-club-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF from the movie Fight Club&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;This club was more like the club in the David Fincher film &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight_Club&quot;&gt;Fight Club&lt;/a&gt;, in that no one discussed the rules. Image src: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.syfy.com/&quot;&gt;Syfy.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the middle of 2019, and in my role as Lead Designer at Wikimedia Foundation, I was given the opportunity to make improvements to the club, aka the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_project&quot;&gt;Talk pages Project&lt;/a&gt;. I knew it was going to be an important project because I could help other volunteer editors connect with each other and improve the quality of content on Wikipedia. But, did every new volunteer have to go on an adventure to discover these “secret” Talk pages? Did every volunteer have the same experience as I did? In this article I’m going to share how I’ve spent the past year approaching the research and user experience design of these powerful spaces within Wikipedia and I’ll wonder out loud about the future design interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-1-listen-to-the-experts&quot;&gt;Act 1. Listen to the experts.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I started to sketch, I did a lot of research to better understand how contributors were using Talk pages. Even though I had my personal experience on Talk pages to inform the work, I wanted to learn a few things: the history of Talk pages, how they are being used by people who are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_project/Glossary.&quot;&gt;Senior contributors&lt;/a&gt;, and how they are being used by more Junior Contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;community-consultation&quot;&gt;Community Consultation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I wasn’t starting from scratch. My colleagues had just completed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_1&quot;&gt;Talk page Community Consultation&lt;/a&gt;, which was basically listening to contributors evaluating their experiences with Talk pages. We heard from community members, who had a range of experience levels. However, at this stage we primarily were informed about the more experienced contributor’s experience (as Senior Contributors were the ones most likely to opt into conversations in the wiki forums). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_2_report&quot;&gt;We learned a few things about Senior Contributor’s experiences&lt;/a&gt;, including that some have important and complex workflows that any new design would need to respect. They identified opportunities for improvement of the look and feel, and interaction design of Talk pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a very small sampling of quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;threading-conversations&quot;&gt;Threading conversations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“但一些编辑喜欢用“：”缩进，一些编辑则使用“*”。后者可以附带唯一ID，前者或会被视为页面内容（Content）的普通章节，可能有点问题.” — 笔尖留痕, Chinese Wikipedia&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some editors like to indent with “:” and some editors use “ * ”. The latter can be accompanied by a unique ID, the former may be considered a normal part of the page content. This may be a bit problematic. — 笔尖留痕, Chinese Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;templates&quot;&gt;Templates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Instead of actually moving the templates, perhaps this could be implemented as a “show/hide” option in the interface. Users who work with wikiprojects etc. could set all pages to “show templates” by default. A special “override” tag could be added to important administrative notices, making them visible to all users. — Dlthewave, English Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-list-the-good-and-the-bad&quot;&gt;A list. The good and the bad.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A list, trying to be brief. I’ll probably come back and update this. First the good:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(1) Everyone loves the idea of the talk page. Let’s keep them. :) (2) Pretty low barrier to participation. (3) Once you get the hang of it, it’s pretty easy. (4) Page history is indispensable. (5) Easy to revise what you’ve written.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The not good:(1) Overall formatting not as intuitive as they’re used to. (2) Too easy to forget signature. (3) Indenting and bulletting interchangeable and messy. Hard to keep track of where things are sometimes. (4) Accessibility issues. (5) Other people’s signatures don’t always make it clear who you’re talking to. Sometimes add to confusion. (6) Archives often hard to find. Harder to use. (7) Too often don’t get a response (only mention because there may be an intervention relating to discoverability of active editors). (8) Banners at the top can be overwhelming as the first thing you see. (9) Edit conflicts. (10) Some pages are overly long. — &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Rhododendrites&quot;&gt;Rhododendrites&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Rhododendrites&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_1&quot;&gt;18:21, 24 February 2019 (UTC)&lt;/a&gt;, English Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes that contributors wanted to be made were clear. Talk pages are too similar to article pages in their appearance and functionality, but not similar enough in their interaction capabilities (including the use of the visual editor tool instead of solely the markup wikitext editing tool that I had first experienced when trying to add a comment several years ago). As you can see from the quotes above, different contributors had different pain points that they wanted to highlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Danny Horn, Director of Product Management at the Wikimedia Foundation explained to me that “a key insight was that the users who are most impacted by feature changes should see a direct benefit of those changes.” This means that instead of expecting users to change their workflows and practices now, in order to benefit a different set of users in the future, we will need to focus on an approach that is informed by the experience of these contributors who have been using Talk Pages for frequently for many years (and in some cases, decades).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;previous-design-interventions&quot;&gt;Previous Design Interventions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people mentioned a previous attempt at rethinking the Talk page design called “Flow.” As Pau Giner, Principal Designer at the Wikimedia Foundation explained “Flow was conceived of as a new product to eventually replace Talk pages. Flow’s scope was around discussions, but Talk pages were used to support many other use cases such as a working space (drafting a paragraph before adding it to the article) or for decision making (voting). Part of the criticism was about the missing support for those.” Here’s an example of what Flow looks like below. In my opinion, it solves many problems that were identified in the consultation. It is easy to browse topics, it’s quick to start a new discussion, it’s obvious how to see responses, etc., so, why wasn’t everyone just using this? I followed up with Danny on this via a Slack conversation on January 6, 2021 asking him if the issue was the tool or maybe some larger issue with the way that the tool was socialized with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a real problem with the tool, and the way that we were thinking about it. We assumed that it was okay to build a tool that couldn’t handle a lot of important senior editor use cases, because it would be easier for junior editors, and that was worth it. If we had gone ahead the way that we were planning to, we would have broken a lot of things without really understanding or respecting how important those broken things were. It was not the case that Flow was a great product direction, and the only problem was selling it to people. We had the wrong philosophy, and that led to bad product decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow wasn’t compatible with the existing Talk pages. The strength of Flow and other interventions such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:LiquidThreads&quot;&gt;LiquidThreads&lt;/a&gt;, was that they were built around the constraint of providing a solid framework for structured discussions. For some, this constraint was freeing as commenting and starting new topics was finally clear to them. For others, it was too restrictive and the loss of source editing eliminated the flexibility core to their contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow, if it had been fully developed, would have also provided new functionalities called “workflows”, such as the ability to count votes automatically, to close a discussion at a predetermined date, to conveniently hold cross-wiki conversations, to move individual discussions with their page histories, and to watch only specific discussions rather than whole pages — all things that experienced editors have requested. That said, it changed all the paradigms around page history and discussions and it limited experienced contributors from using the page the way they had been using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things that I took away from reviewing the work on Flow is 1. the new tool needed to consider the use of the tons of metadata that gets collected on Talk pages. 2.Many wikis actually still have Flow deployed and use it, so whatever we come up with in the future needs to be a better value to those wikis so that they would want to deploy our new set of features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/flow-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of the Flow product&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A previous attempt at refreshing Talk pages was a project called Flow.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;researching-community-gadgets&quot;&gt;Researching Community gadgets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonderful thing about designing for Wikipedia is that if a problem is a big enough issue on Wikipedia, then a community member has probably leveraged the fact that this is an open source project and built what’s called a gadget to attempt to fix it. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Gadgets&quot;&gt;gadget&lt;/a&gt; is a homemade tool that any Wikipedia can enable. The only catch is that it’s not officially supported by the Wikimedia Foundation. This means that even if the tool is a game changer, the community member who created it has to maintain the code and make adjustments based on feedback or bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/community-driven-idea-funnel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of community driven idea funnel&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;This process represents one framework that we use for feature ideation. It would be great in the future to have a more supported version of this currently very fragmented and not always obvious framework (a girl can dream).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been working in the open source design community for over two decades, I kind of take for granted the uniqueness of this kind of innovation framework. I discussed this with Wikimedia Senior Design Manager Lucy Blackwell who said that “Wikipedia is unique in that it is truly community-driven, meaning the community are ‘active creators’ of the platform itself, their vested interest is their passion for Wikipedia and the many hours they have put in personally to developing it. In stark contrast, one finds in most other organizations that when gathering feedback from the people who use the platform, they end up being ‘passive participants’ in the feedback loop, often paid or rewarded to provide an opinion, for which the organization will decide whether to uphold or disregard.” It gives me great pride to work in an environment that operationalizes its values, whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The way that I view gadgets is that:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever the quality is of that gadget, the problem was big enough that someone felt compelled to fix it (so there’s a usability issue with what’s currently deployed to all users that I should probably look into).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If lots of other Wikipedia contributors have installed the gadget, then it probably has some good ideas that were accepted by the larger community, so I should learn from them, and, if appropriate, uplevel the ideas by productizing them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two gadgets that were brought to my attention by community members that impressed the Editing Team were the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey/reply-link&quot;&gt;Reply Link&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Jack_who_built_the_house/Convenient_Discussions&quot;&gt;Convenient Discussions&lt;/a&gt; (authored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey&quot;&gt;Enterprisey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Jack_who_built_the_house&quot;&gt;Jack who built the house&lt;/a&gt; respectively). Both addressed key issues such as replying and threading and handled them with elegant and intuitive interaction design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/reply-link-gadget-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Relpy Link Gadget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Here is a gif of the Editing Team Product Manager, Peter Pelberg and I testing out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey/reply-link&quot;&gt;reply link gadget&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-2-newcomers-and-emerging-communities&quot;&gt;Act 2: Newcomers and Emerging Communities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2019-2020)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading the reports from both phases of the consultation, I realized that the voice of Junior Contributors was missing from the conversation (despite several attempts from communities to reach out to this audience). Hearing directly from them would provide a complete picture of the potential opportunities for the design. In fact, one of the major reasons that this project was being undertaken in the first place was to make it easier for new contributors to communicate on wiki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;usability-testing-with-junior-contributors&quot;&gt;Usability Testing with Junior Contributors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying where to start to do this research was pretty challenging because the contributors to the Talk page consultation weren’t 100% brand new to the site. They probably had some level of experience on Wikipedia and other Wikimedia wikis, whether that was editing content or some other kind of interaction. I decided to try out a widely used testing service. What I like about services such as usertesting.com is that they often attract multilingual testers and, because of their popularity, I could pre-screen and filter the testers to meet profile requirements that matched the experience goals of Junior Contributors. I pulled together a very basic persona (based off of what I could intuit from the Talk page Consultation as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/New_Editor_Experiences&quot;&gt;other research&lt;/a&gt; on new editors) and wrote a few simple protocols for testing common workflows, such as replying to or starting a new conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior Contributors did, in fact, deal with many of the issues that I was dealing with. Specifically, testing showed that it was hard to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reply to a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;follow a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thread discussions within a conversation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here are a few choice quotes from the usability testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There was too much information going on in the top section. It was painful looking at all the options that I could click and also read through what is at the top.” Ct2-d4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I was not easily able to find it, although it was right in front of me.” ct3-d1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everything was painful, I got lost a couple of times, the layout is very difficult to digest with lots of text and too much colours that don’t mean much unless you are familiar with the site” ct3-d2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If I got to this point, I’d give up. Regardless of what I was doing because it’s overwhelming.” ct3-d2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, people who I tested the tool with repeatedly described how outdated the tools looked, felt, and worked. That’s probably because the tools haven’t significantly changed in 15 years, so it’s time to upgrade and provide contributors with the modern web affordances that they have come to rely on. One usability tester even said “I was really thinking I was going to see something like a Reddit page or some kind of chat page where there are some boxes and you just put in what you want to add.” Ct2-d5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/thread-colon.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Relpy Link Gadget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;In order to thread a conversation on Talk pages, a user needs to add a colon and then write their response.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emerging-communities-have-started-to-leave-wikipedia&quot;&gt;Emerging Communities have started to leave Wikipedia!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to individual Junior Contributors, another key stakeholder that the Talk page Consultation didn’t go into depth exploring was emerging communities. These are wikis who have moved these kinds of conversations mostly off wiki and into other widely used platforms, such as WhatsApp or Facebook. Sherry Snyder, Community Specialist at the Wikimedia Foundation explained “Different communities have different approaches, and some of them find it easier to communicate off wiki, using third-party services.” So, after talking with colleagues on our Product Team, our goal with this project is not to tell these communities what to do, but to offer an appetizing alternative should they return to on-wiki communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-3-synthesizing-feedback-and-designing-a-strategy&quot;&gt;Act 3: Synthesizing Feedback and designing a strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(present day)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of these data points, we needed to develop a strategy for how to work with the online communities to design these new series of interventions. I took a step back from all of the pockets of feedback I received and &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendesignkit.org/methods/journey-maps/&quot;&gt;created&lt;/a&gt; a journey map for a few common workflows. The journey map was asking the questions: What’s the current experience for a Junior Contributor talking to a Senior Contributors? And, in turn, what does that experience look and feel like for Senior Contributors? I asked the questions intentionally this way because, unlike previous attempts at solving the problems of the page, I wanted to represent a shared experience. As Peter Pelberg, product manager for the project described, “A core promise people need to depend on talk pages to fulfill is connecting them with others. In this way, talk pages represent a unique place in the software where Junior and Senior Contributors meet. As such, we needed to consider their individual experiences within the context of the productive interactions this work is intended to promote.” Talk pages are places for conversations (in addition to also being places where people draft and evaluate Wikipedia content and much more), so I wanted to represent that there are opportunities for reinvigorating that asynchronous collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/journey-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of journey map of different personas&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A journey map shows what the current experience feels like and identifies opportunities for improvements.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Discussion_Page_Reply_Journey_Map.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Link to a larger (more legible) image&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we understood the problem space and had a few solutions that we could start to experiment with, but we needed to figure out how and when we were going to do it. In terms of how, our team developed three principles that would guide all of our decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make it easy to do the right thing&lt;/strong&gt;: it shouldn’t be a challenge for someone to follow a social convention, such as signing their posts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevate existing functionality&lt;/strong&gt;: wherever possible, build upon the functionality that existing contributors have come to know and use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fix what doesn’t function&lt;/strong&gt;: don’t elevate functionality for the sake of elevating. Make sure that it works, and if it doesn’t, fix it. Once that’s done, make sure that it’s super easy to discover and use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that philosophy in mind, our strategy is to fix the core interaction touch points that everyone struggles with, to make it easier for contributors of all skill levels to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discover new discussion tools to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acquaint yourself with the editing environment: technically understand the UI, conceptually understand that this is a public post, have an expectation as to how and where it will be posted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type and format your post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find your post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A key part of this strategy is to continue to learn from the work that the communities are doing on gadgets and to develop an understanding of how people are using and adapting Talk pages regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-to-start&quot;&gt;Where to start?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question. That’s a tall list to work from, where should we even begin? Even though we know that there are issues with discovery and context, we decided to start after that point in the conversation timeline. We are going to start off by making it easier for contributors to use the tools and then follow that up by making it easier for folks to discover them. The advantage of this approach is that it’s more iterative than designing something wholesale and deploying it. We can make small incremental tweaks and test those tweaks before building on them further. When I was researching approaches, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.uie.com/death_of_relaunch/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Jared Spool which describes many times when companies went big with a design change and it just failed. Because of this area’s history of failed attempts, we wanted to avoid that and so we are moving slowly, asking lots of questions and testing with the online communities early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first post in a series dedicated to the design of Talk pages on Wikimedia wikis. Please continue to read and share ideas, opinions or questions. You can learn more about the project on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_project&quot;&gt;Project Page&lt;/a&gt;. In my next post I will dive into some of the first features that we are working on and share what it’s been like for contributors testing out the prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to: Ed Sanders, David Lynch, Danny Horn, Sherry Snyder, Benoît Evellin, Prateek Saxena, Carolyn Li-Madeo, Peter Pelberg, Pau Giner and Lucy Blackwell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unless otherwise credited, all images in this post are licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Embarking on a design refresh of Wikipedia Talk pages — in three acts</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/people-talking-header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/people-talking-header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In search of the perfect search for Wikipedia</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In search of the perfect search for Wikipedia" /><published>2021-02-19T00:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T00:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;The Android app team improved one of their core features—searching for articles on Wikipedia. Along the way of making discovery more intelligent, personalized and efficient, we experienced a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schönbächler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent project, the Android app team decided to improve one of their core experiences: searching for articles on Wikipedia. Community feedback and previous usability tests revealed, that the app’s search functionality was perceived as inconsistent. Our goal was to make the discovery process for readers more intelligent, personalized and efficient to present the right result at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/272698/global-market-share-held-by-mobile-operating-systems-since-2009/&quot;&gt;market share of 72%&lt;/a&gt;, Android is by far the most used Mobile operating system worldwide. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android app team&lt;/a&gt; builds features for more than five million active readers per month. And it‘s not a secret, that the majority of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextbillionusers.google&quot;&gt;next billion users&lt;/a&gt; are likely joining the internet on an Android device. What does that mean for the Wikipedia Android app? Uncle Ben from Spiderman said it best: “With great power comes great responsibility“.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to make an educated decision about one of our app’s core features, we had to take a step back and understand how people are using the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-readers-navigate-to-articles&quot;&gt;How do readers navigate to articles?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team collected usage data and insights from readers who had explicitly opted in to sharing their anonymized usage data. We wanted to understand how readers currently access Wikipedia articles in the Android app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/pageviews-by-source.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie chart of page views by source&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered that the pageviews were almost equally distributed into thirds. At &lt;strong&gt;33.7%&lt;/strong&gt; the largest portion of readers, visit articles via links from other Wikipedia articles. This data supports the reader behavior known internally as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki_rabbit_hole&quot;&gt;Wiki rabbit hole&lt;/a&gt;, where reader[s] travel by navigating from topic to topic while browsing Wikipedia. &lt;strong&gt;30.7%&lt;/strong&gt; of readers enter into an article via external links, these readers likely perform a search request via their default browser and are taken to the Wikipedia article in the app. Finally, &lt;strong&gt;28%&lt;/strong&gt; of all article visits (1.5 million readers a month) utilize the internal search bar for their queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-the-data-tell-us&quot;&gt;What did the data tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew now that &lt;strong&gt;28% of all page views derive from the internal app search&lt;/strong&gt;. However, we wanted more insight on how the different internal entry points for search are used. To accomplish this, we had to dig deeper into the data. Together with our analytics team we explored how readers commonly used the internal search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we examined how the search experience worked and looked like. There were two main entry points to perform a search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-first-entry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First entry point:&lt;/strong&gt;Search input field at the top in the Explore feed, the app’s home screen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-second-entry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second entry point:&lt;/strong&gt; Search button in the form of a magnifying glass icon at the top of each article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data revealed that approximately 60% of all readers access the search via the first entry point, a search input field in the Explore feed. Around 35% of readers were searching via the search button at the top of article (second entry point). Since the majority of our user base uses Wikipedia to read articles, we expected that most readers rely on the search button at the top of an article – so this was a surprising insight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-usage-distribution.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie chart of page views by source&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we asked ourselves if the search button in the articles is not obvious enough, as our hypothesis was that people were navigating back to the home screen to make use of the first entry point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-the-readers-tell-us&quot;&gt;What did the readers tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain further insights about how search is used, our engineering team created three variants for a usability test. Each variant had a different design and position for the main Wikipedia search in the article. Our goals were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find out about pros and cons of each variant, with a specific focus on discoverability and speed of access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How discoverable is the search functionality in each variant?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can the specific variants be improved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant A:&lt;/strong&gt; Full size search input field at the top of the article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant B:&lt;/strong&gt; Search icon at the top of the article, which is the current user experience.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant C:&lt;/strong&gt; Search icon at the bottom of the article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant A&lt;/strong&gt; was inspired by the analytics insight that two-thirds of all readers search via input field in the home screen. This version put the search input field at the top of the article, as it is on the home screen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant B&lt;/strong&gt; was the existing search experience in the app. To save vertical space, the image ratio and treatment was also slightly different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant C&lt;/strong&gt; featured a search button in the bottom toolbar. The goal of this variant was to provide a more ergonomic search experience that should reduce “thumb travel” when reaching it on a smartphone. Find in page was moved to the overflow menu at the top right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went for an unmoderated, task-based test on &lt;a href=&quot;http://usertesting.com/&quot;&gt;usertesting.com&lt;/a&gt;. Participants were given a set of tasks to complete in a 15-20 minute time frame and perform the test remotely. Check out more details about the test &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T266883&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your guess on which of the variants performed best in the usability tests?&lt;/strong&gt; I bet if Luke Wroblewski, aka Mr &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LukeW/status/454637989503590400?s=20&quot;&gt;“Obvious Always Wins”&lt;/a&gt; had guessed, he’d have guessed right. &lt;strong&gt;Yes, it was Variant A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, participants had no issues finding articles after installing the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar to what we saw in analytics data, all participants directly used the search input on top of the Explore feed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our hypothesis, that participants were remembering their initial action once they were prompted to search for another article from the article page, turned out to be true. All participants naturally used the search input in the article.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From observing participants, we assume that readers are familiar with the look, feel and functionality of a search input from web browsers, such as the default web browser on Android: Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to these reasons, we decided to move forward with the large search input field at the top of the article. The change guarantees great discoverability for searching Wikipedia and as a bonus, the find in article feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-make-search-more-intelligent&quot;&gt;How did we make search more intelligent?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way of optimizing the discovery process for articles, we realized that there was room for improvement in how we handled search queries with no results. One of the amazing things about Wikipedia is that it exists in more than 300 languages. Notably, a third of our readers access articles in multiple languages and effortlessly switch between different language versions of Wikipedia. When using Wikipedia on web, these are completely separate websites: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;en.wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;de.wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt;, for example. One of the strengths of the Android app is that we can make these boundaries disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example below, you’ll notice that, even though multiple languages have been set in the app, the German word “Schabrackenschakal” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black-backed_jackal&quot;&gt;a type of jackal&lt;/a&gt;) outputs zero results in the old version of the app when English Wikipedia is selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-second-language.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Searching articles that exist in a second language currently output 0 results.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, &lt;strong&gt;there is a German Wikipedia article&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schabrackenschakal&quot;&gt;Schabrackenschakal&lt;/a&gt;. The result of the search query could be improved, as a person who’s using the app in multiple languages may not be aware of the language they’re searching in. We designed a solution that indicates results from other language versions of Wikipedia. This sounds like a straightforward solution, but is brand new to Wikipedia. For the first time, readers are able to search Wikipedia in multiple languages at once. Let’s check out how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-no-of-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Instead of 0 results, a compact list of results for other languages is presented. In this example, the result in German is highlighted as a link.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-other-language.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;After tapping the list item, readers are taken to the search of another Wikipedia language version.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-other-language-article.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;And finally, tapping the top search results then takes readers to this friendly guy!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why we don’t show results from other languages in the same list rather than having this extra tap. We intentionally designed it this way to educate readers about how to search the different language versions of Wikipedia. Wikipedias in different languages can have  different content and articles might not exist across languages. The extra tap raises awareness. Plus, we didn’t want to make the slightest sacrifice in regards to search performance, and searching multiple Wikipedia languages would mean significant search speed reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-personalize-search&quot;&gt;How did we personalize search?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its core, the app is a browser designed to explore the contents of Wikipedia in the best possible way. Saved articles, tabs and history are a reflection of a reader’s interest. We wanted to embrace this fact and create and a more personal discovery experience for readers. The new personalized search is another highlight and a brand new experience in the world of Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate how useful this is, here’s an example: During summer 2020, there was a brief moment in Switzerland where cinemas were open. As one of a few Hollywood blockbusters this year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenet_(film)&quot;&gt;Tenet&lt;/a&gt; made its way to the big cinema halls. A good friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/azumbrunnen_&quot;&gt;Adrian Zumbrunnen&lt;/a&gt;, and I have been big fans of the film’s director, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan&lt;/a&gt; for years and closely follow his career. Adrian and I were in agreement that the movie was average for Nolan movie standards, but I remember looking him up on Wikipedia that night. We were interested in rewatching Nolan’s older movies and landed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan filmography Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the end of the year when I was looking for Nolan infos in the Wikipedia Android app again. This was the result of that search query:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-previous-experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The previous experience:&lt;/strong&gt; a search for “nolan” results in results that are not relevant to my interest.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re now surfacing relevant search results based on the user’s history. Articles from open tabs, reading lists or your browsing history are shown first. The right result is presented at the right time. Here’s the new search results list in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-new-personalized-experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The new experience:&lt;/strong&gt; a search for “nolan” takes articles from your open tabs, reading list and search history into account.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-new-personalized-experience-article.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Personalized search results allow readers to more efficiently find the right results. Let’s dig into Christopher Nolan’s art!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to prioritizing articles that readers have interacted with in the past, we added a source indication in the form of the icons next to the article thumbnails. To ensure that readers aren’t in their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filter_bubble&quot;&gt;filter bubble&lt;/a&gt;, we show a maximum of three personalized results at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for the perfect search never ends. Design is an iterative process and we’re going to continue monitoring community feedback and data in the upcoming months. All the features above are now available in the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android app on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;. The app is ad-free and free of charge, forever. With the Wikipedia Android app, you can search and explore 40 million+ articles in 300+ languages, no matter where you are. Our team is working on other exciting features like this, stay tuned! Let us know what you think about the updates, what you’d like to see in the app and even more importantly, which Christopher Nolan &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;film&lt;/a&gt; is your favorite one and why via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WikimediaDesign&quot;&gt;@WikimediaDesign&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Pau Giner, Carolyn Li-Madeo, Volker Eckl, Jess Klein, Matt Cleinman, Shay Nowick, Cooltey Feng, Sharvani Haran, Johan Jönsson, Rita Ho, Dmitry Brant, Jazmin Tanner, Anthony Borba &amp;amp; Prateek Saxena for their contributions to this article or the features.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;related-links&quot;&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Apps on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Polar_Bear_-_Alaska.jpg&quot;&gt;File:Polar Bear - Alaska.jpg - Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/272698/global-market-share-held-by-mobile-operating-systems-since-2009/&quot;&gt;Mobile OS market share 2019 - Statista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://foundation.wikimedia.org/wiki/Privacy_policy&quot;&gt;Privacy policy - Wikimedia Foundation Governance Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan filmography - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/wikimediadesign/In-search-of-the-perfect-search-for-Wikipedia-ca2a939963694c13a18e784b4abd7abf&quot;&gt;Black-backed jackal - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schabrackenschakal&quot;&gt;Schabrackenschakal - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LukeW/status/454637989503590400&quot;&gt;Luke Wroblewski on Twitter: ”Obvious always wins.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schönbächler&lt;/a&gt; is a Senior Designer at the Wikimedia Foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Android app team improved one of their core features—searching for articles on Wikipedia. Along the way of making discovery more intelligent, personalized and efficient, we experienced a surprise.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/polar-search-cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/polar-search-cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Translation on Wikipedia — Inclusion begins with discovery and ideation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/01/25/translation-on-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Translation on Wikipedia — Inclusion begins with discovery and ideation" /><published>2021-01-25T00:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-25T00:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/01/25/translation-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2021/01/25/translation-on-wikipedia.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;Using remote international research to ensure diverse user groups are represented at the earliest stages of product development&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Eli Asikin-Garmager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-bit-of-context-for-starters&quot;&gt;A bit of context for starters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone with an internet connection can now access around 40 million articles across more than 300 languages on Wikipedia. However, depending on which language(s) you read, the amount of knowledge you can access may differ. For example, if you read English, you have access to over 6 million articles; over 1 million articles are also available in about 20 other languages. In contrast, Wikipedias in some languages have far fewer articles — for example, someone speaking only Lao, a language spoken in Southeast Asia by more than 30 million native speakers, can access fewer than 4k articles. Language, in part, affects your access to free knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/depends-on-which-language-you-read.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of languages on Wikipedia&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Access to knowledge currently depends in part on which language(s) you can read&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content on any language version of Wikipedia is carefully curated by volunteer editors, who continually collaborate to ensure that information is well-sourced and accurate by identifying and analyzing references, and adding citations. This allows a reader to verify facts on their own if they wish. Ensuring that editors can contribute knowledge to Wikipedia regardless of what language(s) they read/write is critical to, “imagining a world in which every single human being can freely share in the sum of &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; knowledge,” the Wikimedia Foundation’s vision (emphasis added). Language barriers stifle not only &lt;em&gt;access&lt;/em&gt; to knowledge, but people’s ability to &lt;em&gt;contribute&lt;/em&gt; knowledge. As such, everyone suffers from missed opportunities for participation - some miss out on the opportunity to access and contribute knowledge, and the entire global community misses an opportunity to learn and grow from that wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the goals of the Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Language_engineering&quot;&gt;Language Engineering Team&lt;/a&gt; is to help facilitate the growth of Wikipedias with smaller article collections, especially with the help of computer/machine-aided translation tools. Such tools help content and knowledge flow more freely between different language versions of Wikipedia (‘wikis’). One such tool - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Content_translation&quot;&gt;Content Translation&lt;/a&gt; - has been used to help create more than 800k articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how do we design and build language tools and features while ensuring we meet the diverse language and cultural needs of communities worldwide? Let’s take a look at three strategies guiding a recent international research project carried out by Design Strategy in coordination with the Language Engineering Team. The recently completed &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Multilingual_Editor_Experiences_in_Small_Wikis&quot;&gt;Multilingual Editor Experiences in Small Wikis Project&lt;/a&gt; aimed to better understand how we can support multilingual editors in small wikis who are leveraging translation to contribute across knowledge and content gaps. The project was carried out with editors from seven different language versions of Wikipedia in India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-ensure-inclusion-begins-at-discovery-and-ideation&quot;&gt;1. Ensure inclusion begins at discovery and ideation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To reach the goal of helping smaller wikis grow by making it easier to create multilingual content through translation, we knew we needed to involve these editors in our design and research process right from the start. As such, we planned and carried out a generative research project that helped us identify current barriers and challenges to the use of translation and creation of new content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this study we focused on better understanding the existing workflows of both veteran and potential editors and translators. Through a series of workflow observations and interviews, we learned about these editors’ experience journeys, motivations for editing, and barriers to editing and translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the goal of reducing barriers to research participation, we planned sessions around participants’ schedules, helped them show up to sessions with whatever device they regularly had access to (whether a phone or laptop), and facilitated sessions in a total of eight languages, based on the participant’s preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this project, we learned that the challenges and needs of small wiki editors differ to some degree from the experiences of editors on larger wikis. For example, many small wikis use non-Latin scripts that are not always well-supported by their systems by default, which can present challenges when contributing to Wikipedia. The challenge was particularly widespread when observing new editors. As described by a current Gujarati Wikipedia editor, “The first challenge is typing. Not for me because I have been typing in Gujarati since 2016, but when I try to teach many people to edit Wikipedia, the first challenge is typing.” (This was subsequently confirmed through direct observation of new editors.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of a difference we observed related to motivation. While small wiki editors’ motivations are multi-dimensional (as is true of all editors) and range from purely altruistic to those grounded in self-improvement, small wiki editors may be particularly motivated by considerations of access for others. For example, many India-based editors were motivated by the ability to help bring knowledge access to people who do not read English fluently, especially in rural areas. Small wiki editors were also aware that fewer articles are available in their wikis, so their direct impact in terms of providing a ‘boost’ to the content available in their language was especially motivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/journey-map-marathi-wikipedia.png&quot; alt=&quot;Journey map of Marathi Wikipedia editor&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Excerpt from a sample &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Multilingual_Editor_Experiences_in_Small_Wikis#/media/File:Experienced_Translator_Journey_Map.png&quot;&gt;journey map of an experienced Marathi Wikipedia editor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the research project deliverables, we created personas and experience journey maps that will guide product development. In upcoming months, we will use them during annual planning sessions to ensure that we’re focused on solving the right set of problems. By including more diverse voices and audiences at the earliest stages of product development, we help ensure those diverse experiences guide all subsequent efforts. This allows us to make decisions grounded in the real, lived experiences of users; not guesses or approximations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-strategize-for-necessary-pragmatic-choices-and-plan-for-iteration&quot;&gt;2. Strategize for necessary pragmatic choices and plan for iteration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the challenges at the onset of this project was determining which small wikis we would focus on. Acknowledging that we couldn’t immediately tackle research in all the small wiki communities, we needed to make some strategic choices and create a plan for what iteration would look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By partnering with our Analytics Team, we gathered data for a number of metrics that we used to arrive at an initial set of small wikis for the project. We examined patterns related to the number of articles for various wikis, the number of users and active editors, as well as percentage of mobile views. We also considered the number of speakers for the language and factors such as what machine translation options are currently available for the language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, through this process we clearly identified what we meant by “small”, and arrived at a set of potential candidates. Then, from this set of candidates, we choose a subset to focus on for the project. For practical purposes the project would need to be time-boxed, so we chose a subset of small wikis with significant potential for growth - potential measured by considering active editing behavior and overall size of the language community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/overview-small-wikis.png&quot; alt=&quot;Table showing overview of small wikis&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; Overview of the small wikis selected for this project.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in an ideal world we might have simply selected to do research on all small wikis, given practical considerations and real-world constraints, by following a deliberate strategizing process rooted in data available through analytics we felt more confident about our selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through this process we also set ourselves up to be able to make subsequent decisions as further research opportunities open up. For example, which small wikis make the most sense for subsequent research projects. And, while we arrived at the option of focusing research on a single country covering several languages, we know there may be some country- and/or cultural-factors that do not fully generalize to a broader set of small wikis. Such limitations simply help highlight more work we know we have to do. Continuous iteration to support the truly global collective of editors working to break down language barriers to knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-embrace-remote-options-and-some-practical-tips&quot;&gt;3. Embrace remote options (…and some practical tips)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it hasn’t yet been mentioned, the project highlighted in this post was successfully completed during 2020, a year to be defined in part (or whole?) by a global pandemic that brought travel and many in-person activities to a screaming halt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, while quickly embracing remote methods became an immediate necessity for moderated research sessions during the pandemic, even before the pandemic, the Wikimedia Foundation’s Design Strategy Team had embraced remote methods as a way of achieving a variety of goals. In some cases remote research brings significant cost savings advantages or enables a small design research team to accomplish more in a shorter time frame. But, in other cases the primary motivation may be more related to how it can benefit the diversity of who can show up and participate — especially in light of the fact that product teams have research needs that need to be met in accordance with sometimes tight schedules and timelines that they’re operating on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on our experience with this project, here are five tips for moderated international research sessions being conducted remotely:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule a quick ‘logistics call’ with each participant&lt;/strong&gt;. Before each research session, schedule a short call with each participant. This serves two  purposes. First, it allows you to do a quick test run of the technology you’ll be using for the session and sort out any wrinkles. Secondly, it allows you to begin building rapport with the participant. While it necessitates an investment of some additional time, we found this investment well worth it. We experienced fewer technical hiccups during the actual sessions, and participants felt more comfortable performing tasks and providing honest feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have a backup contact plan&lt;/strong&gt;. Assuming participants agree, have their cell number on hand in case the video call goes down. If you’re not in the same country as the participant, we found using a popular option like WhatsApp can sometimes be advantageous. When we experienced internet connection drops, if participants had a small amount of mobile data available, we were still able to communicate — either to resolve the connection issues or reschedule and not leave anyone hanging.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide live support for language moderators&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re using a moderator to accommodate language preferences of your participants, even if the session will later be transcribed and translated, ensure that a research lead is available for the duration of all sessions. The researcher may be better suited to handle unexpected issues and provide guidance for moderators who may not be as close to the project and research questions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embrace the sound of silence&lt;/strong&gt;. This isn’t specific to remote research facilitation, but becomes particularly important when you’re conducting sessions via video calls. Pausing and allowing a bit of silence ensures that participants are being provided a sufficient invitation and opportunity to speak. It’s also a useful strategy to provide a bit more silence than usual since you often experience short lags with video calls.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule consistently inconvenient times when working across time zones&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re working across timezones, be kind to yourself. Of course you’ll need to schedule times that are convenient for participants, but if this means very early days or late nights for you, be kind and avoid the exhausting ‘late night + early next morning’ combination. For example, maybe one week you plan on having early mornings (but then resting at a decent hour), and the following week going with late nights but sleeping in a bit longer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you find some of these practical tips useful. Please check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Multilingual_Editor_Experiences_in_Small_Wikis&quot;&gt;Multilingual Editor Experiences in Small Wikis project page&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:EAsikingarmager_(WMF)&quot;&gt;Eli Asikin-Garmager&lt;/a&gt; is a lead design researcher at the Wikimedia Foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Using remote international research to ensure diverse user groups are represented at the earliest stages of product development</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/translation-on-wikipedia.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/translation-on-wikipedia.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Design Strategy Website Launch</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Strategy Website Launch" /><published>2020-12-08T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-08T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;Making design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Design Strategy Team&lt;/strong&gt; is pleased to announce the launch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/&quot;&gt;a new site&lt;/a&gt; which makes years of design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community. While most of this work is specific to the user experience of content creators and readers of Wikipedia on our various platforms, some of these studies are more generally applicable - for example, work related to &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/online-social-behavior.html&quot;&gt;online social behavior&lt;/a&gt; and use and training of &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/machine-augmentation.html&quot;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt; applications may be of more general interest. If you find this to be the case &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:desresadmin@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;we’d love to hear from you&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/team.html&quot;&gt;Design Strategy&lt;/a&gt; supports product development at the Foundation by providing the qualitative and quantitative research that enables Product teams to make informed and inspired decisions. From explanations of what people do and want, to evaluations of what they experience, to experiments with new and emerging technologies, the research team answers the most urgent and impactful questions that stand in the way of achieving our vision of &lt;strong&gt;a world in which every single human being can freely share in the sum of all knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Making design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/wiki-pins.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/wiki-pins.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transparency by Design</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transparency by Design" /><published>2020-11-16T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;How making page issues more visible on Wikipedia mobile helps foster trust and participation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Alex Hollender&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today when reading a Wikipedia article on your phone you might see a notice at the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-transparency-by-design.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia notices on mobile&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be more familiar with how they look on a computer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-arizona-state-university.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia notices on desktop&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call these notices &lt;em&gt;page issues&lt;/em&gt;, and 2018 we made them more visible on the mobile website. This blog post is about page issues: what they are, how they increase transparency, and our design process around increasing their visibility on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are page issues?&lt;/strong&gt; — Page issues let you know that there are unresolved issues with the article you’re reading. These issues range from the article not having sufficient citations, to the article not being neutral in its viewpoints, to the article having spelling and grammar mistakes. They usually do a good job of summarizing the issue, and then invite you to help fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-four-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of four different notices&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Page issues are manually added to articles by Wikipedia editors, and on English Wikipedia there are around 340 different kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Page issues are inherently revealing. They are perhaps uncommonly honest. And they seem so unmistakably Wikipedian; I can’t quite imagine Facebook or Airbnb putting up such a notice — &lt;em&gt;this isn’t quite right, help us fix it&lt;/em&gt; — on one of their pages. So before proceeding to some of the specifics about how we increased their visibility on mobile I want to think aloud about some general questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re trying to establish a website as a trustworthy source of information, why would you tell your audience that a certain page is sub-par, or lacking in some way? Could this bit of transparency actually help build trust with them? Maybe it shows them that you’re more interested in finding the knowledge together than you are as being perceived as already having the knowledge on your own. At the same time imagine you’re trying to facilitate collaboration between a huge number of volunteer encyclopedia editors. Might it be helpful if they could leave little notes and clues for each other on articles, helping direct attention and effort? Is there some bigger purpose page issues serve, beyond just giving people a heads up? Or in other words, are page issues symbolic of some larger truth or value within the Wikipedia community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust through transparency&lt;/strong&gt; — In 2007 David Weinberger gave a talk about his book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2695&quot;&gt;Everything is Miscellaneous&lt;/a&gt;” at Google. Forty-five minutes in he comments on page issues on Wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FWHeta_YZ0oE%3Fstart%3D2695%26feature%3Doembed%26start%3D2695&amp;amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DWHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FWHeta_YZ0oE%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;amp;schema=youtube&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; title=&quot;Everything is Miscellaneous&quot; class=&quot;ev hy ew hz w&quot; scrolling=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2695&quot;&gt;Everything is Miscellaneous&lt;/a&gt;” David Weinberger, 2007&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Wikipedia is very happy to have these notices stuck in…they encourage you to put up these notices saying this article isn’t good enough, don’t fully believe this article. And because of that we know that Wikipedia is on our side. [Wikipedia] becomes more credible because they’re willing to admit their lack of credibility, their lack of authority. It’s not trying to convince us that it’s the world’s greatest authority, it’s trying to help us know.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His observation rang true to me. To reiterate and expand: because Wikipedia is more interested in having correct information than it is in being perceived as authoritative, it is able to be transparent about issues and shortcomings. Wikipedia is happy to show its hand, happy to let you know when something might be wrong, because it empowers you as a reader to be alert and discerning. This transparency also reminds readers that every Wikipedia page is a work in progress, and hopefully encourages them to get involved (which is where collaboration comes in).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participation through (intimate?) transparency&lt;/strong&gt; — Imagine that you walked into a coffee shop, sat down at a table, and on the table there was a note saying: &lt;em&gt;Hello, we’re not entirely sure if this table works well here. How does it feel to you? Do you have enough space/privacy from the next table over? Do you think it’s annoying when people slide by to get to the bathroom? Please feel free to let us know your thoughts, or move the table elsewhere. This experiment will end next week.&lt;/em&gt; What would you think or do? How would that information and invitation change your relationship to that coffee shop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking of this note as a display of transparency. The coffee shop is being transparent about what it knows (or doesn’t know), and how it makes decisions. But the note is different from publishing an annual report, or some other kind of formal transparency statement. Instead it’s intimate, direct, and timely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve seen during my time as a Wikipedia community member, this kind of transparency, often in the form of handwritten signs (so to speak), guiding people’s attention towards what’s going on, what needs additional work, is a fundamental aspect of how and why people choose to participate. This transparency seems to inspire a spirit of independent participation. Which is to say that you’re empowered to fix things on your own, while also being supported by others if you need help. So I wonder if page issues function in this way; showing newcomers where help is needed and inviting them to jump in? They also seem to help experienced editors stay organized and direct energy appropriately. And in their humble, handwritten way maybe they reinforce the spirit of intimacy that is so necessary for a community-run project. Again these are questions, hopes, guesses; not a proven understanding of what’s happening. Now onto the more concrete stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing the visibility of page issues on mobile&lt;/strong&gt; — Wikipedia community participation isn’t limited to writing and editing Wikipedia articles. The community is also involved with the planning, design, and development of Wikipedia as a website/piece of software. Just as anyone can edit, anyone can also voice their opinion about the functionality or look of the website and propose improvements, which is how page issues on mobile came to be prioritized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September, 2016 Wikipedian McGeddon posted on Village Pump (a Wikipedia discussion board):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-mobile-page-issues.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(left) McGeddon’s post, (right) how page issues looked on mobile in 2016&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“If an article is up for [deletion] and flagged as a possible hoax with insufficient medical sourcing, any reader visiting that article on a computer is greeted by three large red and orange boxes at the top of the page, one with a cautionary stop sign… If a reader instead visits the same hoax medical article on their phone… they just get two tiny grey words “Page issues” under the article title…”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while the fix wasn’t made until 2018, all in all it was a great demonstration of Wikipedia at its best — a community member voiced their question/opinion, a discussion began, and eventually an improvement to the site was made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design challenge&lt;/strong&gt; — A page issue is like the note on the coffee table. They come in all shapes and sizes. They are not particularly standardized. Look at some of them, how much personality they have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Collage of different types of notices&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal seemed relatively straightforward: show these page issues to people reading Wikipedia on their phones to make them aware of any known issues with the article they were reading. However if you try the straightforward thing, and just show them on the mobile website, you get this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-language-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Notices in different languages&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t just automatically get smaller and look good on the mobile website. And to make matters worse, articles that have one issue often have others, so you get these boxes stacked on top of each other which pushes the article text way down the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how should they look on the mobile website? What’s the right balance between making them noticeable and them overwhelming the article? Keep in mind there aren’t just the 340 different page issues on English Wikipedia to test out, there are hundreds of others across various Wikipedia projects (e.g. French, Arabic, Thai, etc.). Some contain one image, some contain two or three. Many contain links to pages that also aren’t formatted to look good on a phone. We understood that we needed to come up with a systematic way of creating smaller, “mobile-friendly”, versions. To begin we identified that mostly all of them have: an icon/image, a text description, and a color. So it wasn’t too difficult to imagine the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-mobile-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Notices on mobile&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the type of visual consistency we were hoping to achieve. Since page issues aren’t standardized from a code/template perspective the technical challenge to isolate the relevant pieces (image, description, color/severity) was significant, though I won’t be getting into that here. A few other questions naturally occurred as well (partly curiosity, partly things that we thought might inform our design process):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are all the different page issues that exist?&lt;/em&gt; There was no straightforward way to get this information. &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.wikimedia.org/~jdrewniak/page_issues_inventory/en.index.html&quot;&gt;This gallery&lt;/a&gt; shows page issues for some of the largest Wikipedias (thanks to Jan, an engineer on our team, who did this audit programmatically).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there any structure or categorization to their level of importance?&lt;/em&gt; Thankfully yes, most page issues have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&quot;&gt;type&lt;/a&gt; parameter, which is a consistent way of programmatically knowing how severe a given issue is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How common are the different types of page issues? Are there a small few that show up a disproportionately large percentage of the time?&lt;/em&gt; There was no straightforward way to get this information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While we loved the personality of the custom icons/images many of them weren’t able to effectively communicate at a small size. We also hoped that using a simple visual system consistently across all page issues would make it easier for readers to quickly understand their importance. So we adopted the scale from English, using simplified versions of the icons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-types.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design criteria were also relatively simple: 1) people should see them (without them being distracting), 2) people should see the severe ones most easily, 3) the notices shouldn’t clash with other notices that appear at the top of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-prominence.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketches showing different prominence of notices&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Initial sketches&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-other-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Other notices and elements that appear at the top of some articles&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also questioned whether the placement on desktop — at the top of the article — was appropriate for mobile. We considered whether it might make sense to put important notices above the article, and less important ones perhaps below the first section. But we opted for simplicity here, and decided they should all just go in the same place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-severity.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Position of notice according to severity&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point we felt like our solution was good enough to start testing. The main thing we wanted to learn from our test was: do people notice the page issues, and interact with them, more than before? This was the goal for the project and was admittedly a pretty low bar (considering that previously they were very understated). We also wondered about the secondary effects of exposure to page issues. Would exposing page issues on mobile affect trust and/or participation in Wikipedia, even for people reading from their phones? Here is what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the main goal we succeeded: the new page issues were noticed and interacted with significantly more than the old ones. And furthermore, more severe issues are noticed and interacted with significantly more than less severe ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the secondary goals the outcome was less clear: we saw no immediate increase in editing as a result of the updated treatment, and we didn’t end up measuring trust.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Reading/Web/Projects/Mobile_Page_Issues/AB_tests?useskinversion=2&quot;&gt;full report here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And so we labor on, continually trying to bring transparency to every corner of our experience. The more people know about the information they are reading the better equipped they are to be discerning. We believe that transparency has value in and of itself, and this project was about furthering that value. We didn’t see an immediate increase in editing, but we also know that editing from a mobile is more difficult to begin with, and we are still continuing to learn about the different mentalities different people have when reading Wikipedia on their mobile device versus on a computer. In other words, we’re far from finished yet. But now people reading on their phones will see the notices, and over time more of them may be inspired to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  Alex Hollender is a lead designer at the Wikimedia Foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How making page issues more visible on Wikipedia mobile helps foster trust and participation</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Organizing a remote offsite for a global team</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Organizing a remote offsite for a global team" /><published>2020-10-15T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Lucy Blackwell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started working at the Wikimedia Foundation as a Senior Design Manager in March of this year, just after the lockdown began in London, UK where I’m based. Whilst this design team has always been a fully remote team, they annually get together in person for a few days somewhere in the world for a team offsite, but this year, all travel was cancelled! This blog post will share a bit about how I set up a remote offsite for the team and what I learnt in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-defining-the-goals&quot;&gt;1. Defining the goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a difficult time to organise an event with the coronavirus adding a new layer of stress to peoples lives. I realised we were going to have think carefully about what we wanted to achieve with this offsite, and what capacity people were likely to have to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gathering-information&quot;&gt;Gathering information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began like any designer, researching and reading everything I could find about how others had run remote off sites previously, and then started discussions on the topic with the other members of our design leadership group. Our director, Margeigh Novotny, suggested the theme of ‘cooperation’ and how we work together, which we all felt was very appropriate. We also agreed that it should have a light-hearted and fun tone, as a lot of the year so far had been quite difficult for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also keen to understand what the team wanted to get out of the offsite, so I created a survey to gather their opinions including questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the single most important thing you personally want to achieve by attending the team offsite?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What inspires you most about how our team works together?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you think could be improved in how our team works together?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communicating-goals&quot;&gt;Communicating goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After collating all the responses, some pretty clear topics emerged – team bonding, learning from each other, small group collaboration and fun. There were a few other topics from one or two individuals which we decided not to do this time. I presented the survey results back to the team in our team meeting (about a month before the actual offsite) and explained the decisions we’d made for what to include and what to leave out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By defining our goals early on, this helped set the expectations for the team, and created a blueprint for me to build the agenda and activities upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-planning-logistics-and-tools&quot;&gt;2. Planning, logistics and tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design and research team is truly global, with a total of 17 designers and researchers located all over the world from Bangalore to San Francisco.  We span a 12 hour time difference, so when it’s 8am in San Francisco, its 8pm in Bangalore. This requires some careful planning to make things run smoothly if we all want to connect at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scheduling&quot;&gt;Scheduling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a group we use google calendar to schedule our meetings which displays events in the right time zone for each individual, and allows users to define their working hours so we can identify the overlaps which is very important for remote teams. However, sometimes folks haven’t got around to putting in holidays they’re planning in the future, so I decided to use a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://doodle.com/en/&quot;&gt;doodle poll&lt;/a&gt; to determine what dates everyone was free and lock down the week for the offsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;screen-time&quot;&gt;Screen time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the dates agreed upon, I needed to work out which activities would require all 17 team members together on a screen, versus which ones would be more effective in smaller groups, pairs, or even alone. I learnt some great tips from Jasmin Tanner in &lt;a href=&quot;https://jazmintanner.com/blog/2020/5/15/a-wikimedia-foundation-product-team-had-productive-virtual-strategy-sessions-and-meaningful-team-bonding-in-a-remote-environment-across-various-time-zones&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; where she talked about limiting the amount of time on screen with others to just 4 hours a day, broken into sessions of 2 hours maximum at a time.  I realized that I needed to be more aware of the cognitive load during screen time to be sure people didn’t disengage. This is quite different to the physical off sites I’ve run previously, where I often included a walk or a physical activity to break up the sessions throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we decided we would connect as a whole team for one 2 hour session every day, we chose the only reasonable time slot we could find, which was 8am - 10am in SF, which made it 8pm - 10pm in India.   In addition to these all team sessions, I then arranged some smaller break out sessions between individuals and people located in similar time zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-schedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Schedule for the offsite activities day by day&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I started to gather ideas, I realised there were a number of activities that needed to happen before the group sessions, so I was going to need somewhere to provide instructions for what everyone needed to do, by when, and with whom.  I decided to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.notion.io/&quot;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt;, which is a lovely user-friendly in-browser tool for creating and sharing content that the team had been starting to experiment with. I prepared instructions for each day in Notion and then shared each page with the team the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-notion.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of prep page in Notion&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team are already very active &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slack.com/&quot;&gt;slack&lt;/a&gt; users so I created a special channel in Slack for all our offsite banter and chatting.  For some of the activities I also created some collaborative boards in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.miro.com/&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; which is an online whiteboard used primarily for visual collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborators&quot;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always useful to seek help from within the team when running an event as it brings a fresh perspective to the planning, lightens the load on the organizer and also engages some of the team in the process.  For this offsite, our research manager, Ana Chang and I brainstormed all the plans together, then she took over the activities for the last day with a couple of other designers, Carolyn Li-Madeo and Jess Klein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon hearing that the theme of the offsite was ‘cooperation’, Bethany Gerdemann in the research team offered to share her facilitation skills, as it turned out she is a qualified Coop developer and has lots of experience helping groups establish workplace democracy.  We discussed the best way to weave her contribution into the event. In the end she made a great presentation and video for us all to watch about cooperation, which was very well received by the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people didn’t have much time with busy day jobs in their product teams and I think for many it felt challenging enough just to clear their calendar for 3 days to attend the event.  But a couple of the designers offered to organize an icebreaker, which is a short 10 minute warm up session which normally happens at the start of a meeting. These were really effective and didn’t take too much prep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the organizer, I was responsible for the bulk of the prep work, but I felt part of my role was to bring as many people into the process as I could, so it would really feel like a team effort, after all the offsite was for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;swag&quot;&gt;Swag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like at every great event, everyone enjoys a little swag, and fabulously our team director, Margeigh Novotny, had already made some really awesome pins for everybody and ordered a small hardback book titled ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/why-we-cooperate&quot;&gt;Why We Cooperate&lt;/a&gt;’  by Michael Tomasello, so we got these sent off to everyone in advance. It’s a bit like sending out the VIP passes before the festival, it creates a little excitement and anticipation for the event and makes people feel special!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-swag.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikimedia swag: 'The last best place on the internet' pins&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-team-building-activities&quot;&gt;2. Team building activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed to think of activities that could be done anywhere in the world, keeping in mind that some people were in lockdown and unable to leave their homes. We started by breaking the overarching themes into sub-themes for each day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals - learn about our teammates and their personality traits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Groups - explore ways to work together in small groups and learn facilitation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 3:&lt;/strong&gt; Diversity - develop an appreciation for the diverse backgrounds in the team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did all sorts of different activities including a series of games around our personality profiles and making a set of guidelines for collaboration following a small group activity. Here’s a bit more detail about just a few of the activities that went pretty well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ice-breakers&quot;&gt;Ice Breakers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice breakers are short warm up activities to get everyone in the spirit of interacting together. Carolyn Li-Madeo ran a super fun activity which some may know as ‘A big wind blows’.  It went as follows…. we were all on the call with our cameras on, Carolyn asked us all to turn our cameras off, whilst she kept hers on.  She then said ‘Who had avocado for lunch?’ and anyone who did have avocado for lunch had to turn their camera back on. The last person to turn their camera on, who had had avocado is now ‘it’ and the process starts again….  So again each round started with everyone turning their camera off except the person whose turn it was…. they then asked a new question like… ‘Do you wear glasses?’  and the game continued… People really loved this activity as it allowed us to see how similar and different we all are, it was very interactive without any effort, and many people said they could have kept playing it for ages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diy-user-manuals&quot;&gt;DIY User Manuals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read that lots of teams have had success getting to know each other better by writing their own personal user manuals and sharing them with each other. In case you’re not familiar with the term, basically a user manual explains things like how you like to communicate best, if you’re a morning person, how you manage challenges etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I searched through different options, it occurred to me that many of the examples I’d found felt a bit heavy and serious and we had agreed to keep things light, so in a highly unscientific manner, I decided to create my own list of 10 questions. I pulled from all sorts of different sources like a game from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theschooloflife.com/shop/100-questions-work-edition/&quot;&gt;School of Life&lt;/a&gt; where they ask the question ‘Which of your talents is the world in danger of overlooking?’, and a question from my favourite radio BBC show &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qnmr&quot;&gt;Desert Island Discs&lt;/a&gt;,  which asks ‘If you were going to be cast away to a mythical desert island and could only take one thing with you, what would you take and why?’  I even remembered an application form I’d filled out the year before in order to attend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedolectures.com/&quot;&gt;Do Lectures&lt;/a&gt; in Wales, where they’d asked me ‘If you had a life motto, what would it be?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared the list of 10 questions with the team and asked everyone to fill them in on their own. Then I paired each person up with another person in the team who they said they’d spent less time with, and  encouraged them to spend an hour sharing their user manuals with each other and diving deeper into their answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our collaborative all team session each person had to describe the person they’d chatted with, to the whole group. There were some amazing facts and stories revealed which allowed us all to gather some new perspectives on our team mates, such as the fact that one person said the living thing they feel most similar to is ‘slime mold’ - that same person also said that their ‘secret talent that the world might overlook’ was that they were an awesome parallel parker!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photo-walks&quot;&gt;Photo Walks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last day some of the other folks in the team came up with the idea of asking everyone to take a walk around their neighbourhood to take photos. They wanted to encourage people to pause and really look at their physical environment objectively as a designer. The team were asked to take photos of; things that inspired them, things that they thought were good or poor design, and examples of inclusive or exclusive design. (If folks couldn’t leave their homes due to a lockdown, we suggested they found inspiration inside their home instead, or even using photos they’d taken before, or found relevant images online.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then asked everyone to upload their photos to a shared collaborative Miro board, adding their initials and any notes they wanted to add about the images. Later that day, in our full team group session we took turns sharing some of the stories behind the images we’d taken with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of our miro board from our photo walks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fully remote team we usually only see each other on Google meet and have no idea about the context our colleagues live in that inspire and inform their lives. This exercise really helped build an appreciation of the diverse environments and perspectives within our group, from Indian streets to European towns, to the American countryside, each image full of cultural nuance with its own unique story to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-reflection-and-learnings&quot;&gt;4. Reflection and learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the offsite was a great success, we had a good time and got to know each other better and achieved many of the goals we’d set out to do. But there’s always more to learn, so here’s a few of my reflections after the event…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-keeping&quot;&gt;Time keeping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively running a series of sessions requires quite a bit of preparation, not least a clear minute-by-minute plan of how long everything should take, especially when many folks in the team are working unusual hours already in order to attend the session. One of the key roles of the facilitator is to keep everything on track time-wise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first day, I had planned a series of activities and games based upon the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.16personalities.com/&quot;&gt;personality type profiles&lt;/a&gt; we’d identified for ourselves before that session. However, each activity had taken longer than I’d expected, so this meant the whole session ran over by about 20 minutes.  About a third of the group had to leave promptly at the agreed end time and it meant a few folks didn’t get to share back their user manuals with the team.  The beauty of being online was that we could easily record the remaining part of the session, so those who had to leave could watch it later, but it meant they had more to do to catchup and be ready for the next day.  The following day I did manage to keep the group session to time, but learning how to nail this every time is something I will be focusing on in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-anti-climax&quot;&gt;The anti-climax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of our offsite I felt exhausted and a bit deflated, I found this to be a rather strange reaction, given that I thought things had generally gone fairly well. But it occurred to me as I cycled home that night on my own, that it was kind of sad not to be able to go and have a drink or a cup of tea with some folks from the team that evening, or even over lunch the next day. I wanted to hear their banter about the event, to know what they thought!  This is also contrary to my previous experiences, as in my last role I’d never been overly keen on the after work get togethers and usually would have to skip them anyway due to childcare responsibilities, but suddenly not having this option made me feel a bit empty. So how might we celebrate and wrap projects better in a remote world, without spending the evening on a screen again?  I think I will be exploring this question on the next remote offsite, but do let me know if you have any ideas…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-survey&quot;&gt;Feedback survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of there being no wrap party to speak of, I did ask the team to fill in a short survey after the offsite to reflect upon what they’d learnt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more positive results was that the team unanimously gave top marks for ‘having fun’. Before I began planning the event, I had not been totally sure if this was possible online, besides you can’t really tell people to ‘Have fun!’, you can only create an environment for it to happen and hope it does. It turns out the fact it was online really made no difference to this. I also think agreeing this as an objective early on helped us collectively create an experience that we all enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the loveliest piece of feedback that came from multiple people in the survey, was that they really enjoyed the one-on-one sessions they’d had in the offsite with people in the team that they don’t normally work with. This is of course the easiest thing to organise of everything. It is so often the simplest things in life that take us the farthest. Perhaps the simple act of finding time to get to know our teammates, and making this a pattern in our busy routines, might be the thing that really helps us bond as a team overtime.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Whilst this design team has always been a fully remote team, they annually get together in person for a few days somewhere in the world for a team offsite, but this year, all travel was cancelled!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-design-web.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-design-web.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>