<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-11-29T15:43:25+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wikimedia Design Blog</title><subtitle>Make sharing of knowledge easy and joyful, for everyone.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Solving gendered-harassment: a feminist framework for creating safety on Wikipedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/11/02/gendered-harassment-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Solving gendered-harassment: a feminist framework for creating safety on Wikipedia" /><published>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/11/02/gendered-harassment-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/11/02/gendered-harassment-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://aishwaryavardhana.medium.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Aishwarya Vardhana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My product team, Trust and Safety Tools, has been tasked with building a system for people to safely report harassment on Wikipedia.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:code-of-conduct&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:code-of-conduct&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As a woman my instinct was to first ask, how does harassment affect women on the platform? What about other people who are targeted based on their gender identity? Knowing that the internet is rampant with sexist, homophobic, and transphobic rhetoric, what could our team do to make a small difference in this complex space?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;understanding-the-problem&quot;&gt;Understanding the problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a designer, and I follow a design process, therefore my first question is to ask, how well do we understand the problem of gender-based harassment? Who experiences it and in what form is the harassment? What do targets of gendered-harassment do about it? What do these “users” (to use product-speak) need? What are their goals and motivations? If we were to create personas for them, what would they be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to answer these questions we, of course, need to do user research. However, in order for this research to be properly contextualized, it needs to be parsed through a feminist lens. Here we push up against the limitations of the individual designer. To design for complex, sociocultural scenarios, I believe a designer needs to be fluent in sociology and the disciplines it spawns, such as the study of race, gender, class, and religion. You see, when analyzed in a vacuum, gendered-harassment is easily misunderstood as “bad actors misbehaving”. However, if one understands the mechanics of patriarchy, one is able to see how gendered-harassment is the byproduct of a misogynistic culture. I, as the designer, don’t need to be an expert in sociology, but I need to know who to talk to, to appropriately understand the problem space. As I proceed with this project, I will be doing exactly that!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A disproportionate number of editors who experience harassment on Wikipedia are women and/or identify as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LGBT&quot;&gt;LGBTQIA+&lt;/a&gt;. They are vulnerable to harassment in the form of name calling, discrimination, stalking, trolling/flaming, and threats of violence.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:harassment-survey&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:harassment-survey&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to understand and accept that we have a cultural problem on our hands, and cultural problems are not easy to fix. They require intervention and prevention, such as inclusion training, protections for the vulnerable, accountability for those who inflict harm, and strong, egalitarian values embodied by leadership. So, before my team begins this work I would just like to say, no singular product can solve gendered-harassment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, solving gendered-harassment can and should be prioritized, and not an afterthought which is why I’m writing this blog post and would like to drive this work forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-this-matters&quot;&gt;Why this matters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving gendered-harassment is not only a moral imperative, it is central to the mission of the Wikimedia Foundation. When editors are harassed they stop contributing, and we will never reach our vision of free knowledge without equitable participation from folks of all genders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote Professor Jessica Wade’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PUpOqdB6RDU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;TEDxWomen London 2018&lt;/a&gt; talk, a Wikimedian herself and voice for diversity in science, “…the majority of history has been written by men, about men, for other men … and the majority of content on Wikipedia is written by white men in America.” Professor Wade, and many other community members, are working to recruit more women to edit Wikipedia, but we must also ask, why aren’t more women organically evangelizing or joining Wikipedia? Once they join, what is their experience like? Do they stay? Do they encourage more women to join? Why or why not? Is the editing community an inviting, welcoming, and friendly space for women?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, it is not enough to acquire women who edit, we must retain them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-communitys-efforts&quot;&gt;The community’s efforts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years various Wikipedia community members have asked for improvements to reporting systems, specifically to protect women and LGBTQIA+ editors. &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Paisleypeach&quot;&gt;Daniellagreen&lt;/a&gt; proposed a way to &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:IdeaLab/End_Sexism_and_Intolerance_on_Wikipedia&quot;&gt;end sexism and intolerance on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. Wikimedian-in-residence &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Bluerasberry&quot;&gt;blueraspberry&lt;/a&gt; sketched the basics of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:IdeaLab/Centralised_harassment_reporting_and_referral_service&quot;&gt;centralized harassment reporting and referral service&lt;/a&gt;. User &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:IdeaLab/Require_Apologies&quot;&gt;beauxlieux&lt;/a&gt; centered ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:IdeaLab/Require_Apologies&quot;&gt;apologies&lt;/a&gt;’ in their suggestion for how to make Wikipedia a kinder and more civil place. Editors &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:QEDK&quot;&gt;QEDK&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Djembayz&quot;&gt;Djembayz&lt;/a&gt; teamed up to propose a whole suite of reporting tools and best practices specifically for addressing gender concerns such as “have moderators who are trained to understand the reality of women’s safety needs’’. One of my favorites is by Wikimedian and sociologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Radfordj&quot;&gt;radfordj&lt;/a&gt; who derived inspiration from the U.S. Women’s Rights movement in the 60s and 70s, and proposed a consciousness raising-style &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Grants:IdeaLab/A_Consciousness_Raising_Repository&quot;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; to document and elevate the stories of traditionally marginalized groups, in the hope that this data can be used to understand and mitigate marginalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Online gender-based harassment is not a new phenomena or a simple problem to fix. A few infamous examples include &lt;a href=&quot;https://feministfrequency.com/2012/06/10/harassment-and-misogyny-via-wikipedia/&quot;&gt;Harassment via Wikipedia Vandalism – Feminist Frequency&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slideshare.net/syeo/women-and-wikipedia-panel-discussion&quot;&gt;Women and Wikipedia: Perspectives on the gender gap, harassment, and the Gamergate controversy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zdnet.com/article/quoras-misogyny-problem-a-cautionary-tale/&quot;&gt;Quora’s misogyny problem: A cautionary tale | ZDNET&lt;/a&gt;, and a woman-volunteer bringing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title%3DUser_talk%253AJimbo_Wales%26oldid%3D680807651%23Tweet&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=docs&amp;amp;ust=1666821146180537&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3MayTFyHy_vof9f-6e9Xyw&quot;&gt;a harassment issue straight to Jimmy Wales&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;demonstrating-the-use-of-a-feminist-lens&quot;&gt;Demonstrating the use of a feminist lens&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to demonstrate how to critically examine the existing ecosystem on Wikipedia through a feminist lens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English Wikipedia has five foundational principles. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:five-pillars&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:five-pillars&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; One of these principles is about &lt;em&gt;conduct&lt;/em&gt; and the two values that underpin &lt;em&gt;conduct&lt;/em&gt; are “civility” and “assume good faith”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of analysis let us assume a new, woman-identifying editor is harassed by a veteran male editor and searches for resources on Wikipedia. Below are the first four instructions she’s given. I have highlighted parts of the instructions which I find counterproductive to our shared goal of supporting targets of harassment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When dealing with incivility:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;First of all, consider whether &lt;strong&gt;you and the other editor may simply have misunderstood&lt;/strong&gt; each other. &lt;strong&gt;Clarify, and ask for clarification.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Consider the possibility that &lt;strong&gt;something&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;you said or did&lt;/strong&gt; wrongly provoked a defensive, irritated or fed-up response. &lt;strong&gt;Be prepared to apologize for anything which you could/should have done better. (If an awful lot of people seem to be getting frustrated with you, the problem may be with you.)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Even if you’re offended, &lt;strong&gt;be as calm and reasonable as possible in your response.&lt;/strong&gt; Until there is clear evidence to the contrary, &lt;strong&gt;assume that the offense was unintended.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In a case of ongoing incivility, first decide if anything needs to be done. &lt;strong&gt;Confronting someone over a minor incident – particularly if it turns out that you misinterpreted what they meant – may produce more stress and drama than the incident itself. Consider your own behavior, and, if you find you have been uncivil, apologize to them instead.&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Civility&quot;&gt;civility documentation&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps 1-3 undermine the target’s emotions and her judgment. One could go so far as to make the argument that these instructions gaslight the target, by first asking her what &lt;em&gt;she&lt;/em&gt; did wrong. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gaslighting&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gaslighting&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second core value is to “assume good faith”. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:assume-good-faith&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:assume-good-faith&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Asking victims of harassment to assume good faith, when trust has been broken, places an unfair burden on them. This can lead to inequitable distributions of emotional labor and a higher rate of burnout. Other advice we give is to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Harassment&quot;&gt;“first and foremost act calmly (even if difficult)”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:No_personal_attacks&quot;&gt;“simply ignore it”&lt;/a&gt;, and to stay &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Staying_cool_when_the_editing_gets_hot&quot;&gt;cool when the editing gets hot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that our current policies are intended to be helpful. Wikipedia is written and run by volunteers with limited time, and these policies attempt to save volunteers time and emotional labor by asking people to resolve conflicts themselves. However, policies that don’t serve victims of gendered harassment ultimately create &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; work for the responder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-the-inclusive-product-development-playbook&quot;&gt;Using the inclusive product development playbook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing policies is out of scope for my team, Trust and Safety Tools. We are focused on designing a minimal viable product (MVP) for how someone will report harassment and what the responder will see on the other end. I am advocating that we prioritize solving for gendered-harassment, and reporters who are women or LGBTQIA+. With the rollout of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Product/Inclusive_Product_Development#Background&quot;&gt;inclusive product development playbook&lt;/a&gt;, we have the tools and support to approach an old, systemic issue in a new way. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:inclusive-product-dev&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:inclusive-product-dev&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team is in the first phase of product development, also known as the STRATEGIZE phase. I’ve read through the playbook and grouped together a set of tasks pertaining to our audience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Establish a baseline of current users and use cases, and opportunities for equity based on your context. Include existing research (internal and external) of the problem space you want to address.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Be intentional and clear about who you will empower and engage with (have a clear why), and what that engagement will look like (target audience). If your answer is everyone, consider thinking about who you will engage with first for learning and then scale.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Establish “Who are we leaving out?” and be clear if you will include those that are being left out in this iteration or in the future based on your baseline understanding of “established” audiences and “growth” audiences.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;When establishing objectives and key results, be specific about who you are serving, what assumptions you are making and how you will validate or challenge those assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Clearly define what barriers and/or knowledge gaps you are aiming to address as well as what new opportunities you are planning to create for your target audience and why your team is uniquely positioned to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our challenge is to understand the pain points of women and LGBTQIA+ folks because a Wikipedia that is safer for the most vulnerable, is safer for all. Within our target audience, we should focus on those who are the least well-connected and influential within the community i.e. the newcomers. We will need to conduct user interviews to better understand who we are building for and speak with responders who have helped resolve or witnessed gendered-harassment. Given how complex and expansive this project is, it will be necessary to who we are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; designing for as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Establish what partners (internal and external) need to be brought into each phase and give them advance notice of the goal you intend to accomplish if not sooner. Advanced notice should occur as soon as you are aware you will need the team’s support, ideally at least a quarter in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some potential partners include mission aligned organizations such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://geekfeminism.fandom.com/wiki/Geek_Feminism_Wiki&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Geek Feminism Wiki&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wearebgc.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Black Girls Code&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://pollicy.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Pollicy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://feministinternet.org/en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Feminist Internet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://adainitiative.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Ada Initiative&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.karisma.org.co/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Fundación Karisma&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cybercivilrights.org/about/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Cyber Civil Rights Inititiave&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://genderit.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;GenderIT&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apc.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;APC&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://thebachchaoproject.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;The Bachchao Project&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://civiclaboratory.nl/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CLEAR&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://iheartmob.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;HeartMob&lt;/a&gt;. For internal partnerships a few potential partners include the Global DEI team, the Trust and Safety legal department, and the inclusive product development working group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anti-harassment-work-is-inclusion-work&quot;&gt;Anti-harassment work is inclusion work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to identify the root cause of harassment to individual personalities e.g. “so and so is just a bully”. Harassment can indeed be random and isolated, but it is frequently about power. When women or LGBTQIA+ folks are targeted because of their gender-identity, it can be with the intention of systematically driving them away. This form of harassment is not interpersonal, it is ideological. If we didn’t view harassment in this way, a feminist way, we would be missing a very important insight about the problem space. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:feminist-principles-violence&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:feminist-principles-violence&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; According to Valerie Aurora, ED of Ada Initiative, anti-harassment work is part of a successful diversity initiative. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:diversity-initiatives&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:diversity-initiatives&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wish to retain and cultivate gender diversity on Wikipedia, we must design and build a reporting system that addresses the nuances of nonmale needs. This blog post is an analysis, a call to action, and just the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-in-touch&quot;&gt;Get in touch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:avardhana@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;avardhana@wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt; if you’d like to discuss this work further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Selene Yang, Bethany Schowengerdt, Lucy Blackwell, and Carolyn Li-Madeo for their thoughtful edits.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:code-of-conduct&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Universal_Code_of_Conduct/Revised_enforcement_guidelines#3.2_Recommendations_for_a_reporting_tool&quot;&gt;Universal Code of Conduct/Revised enforcement guidelines - Meta&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:code-of-conduct&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:harassment-survey&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Harassment_Survey_2015_-_Results_Report.pdf&quot;&gt;File:Harassment Survey 2015 - Results Report.pdf - Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:harassment-survey&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:five-pillars&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Five_pillars&quot;&gt;Wikipedia:Five pillars&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:five-pillars&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gaslighting&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gaslighting&quot;&gt;Gaslighting - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gaslighting&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:assume-good-faith&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Assume_good_faith#Dealing_with_bad_faith&quot;&gt;Wikipedia:Assume good faith&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:assume-good-faith&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:inclusive-product-dev&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Product/Inclusive_Product_Development#Background&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Product/Inclusive Product Development - MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:inclusive-product-dev&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:feminist-principles-violence&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://feministinternet.org/en/principle/violence&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Violence | Feminist Principles of the Internet&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:feminist-principles-violence&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:diversity-initiatives&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:Successful_diversity_initiatives_in_open_tech_and_culture.pdf&amp;amp;page=13&quot;&gt;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:Successful_diversity_initiatives_in_open_tech_and_culture.pdf&amp;amp;page=13&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:diversity-initiatives&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Trust and Safety Tools team is designing a harassment reporting system for Wikipedia. I propose that we prioritize the needs of women, non-binary, trans, and queer users who experience gendered-harassment on the platform so that we retain gender diversity among our editors and make progress towards our mission of knowledge equity.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/gendered-harassment/image1.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/gendered-harassment/image1.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Entering the Wikimedia universe: starting with a design internship</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/07/12/entering-wikimedia-universe.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Entering the Wikimedia universe: starting with a design internship" /><published>2022-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/07/12/entering-wikimedia-universe</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/07/12/entering-wikimedia-universe.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/olgatichonova&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Olga Tichonova&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Universe image adapted from Alexander Meleg, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;, via Wikimedia Commons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to find a job during the peak of the pandemic as a junior UX designer was a grueling process, but after months of applying, I was given the opportunity to start a 9-month internship at the Wikimedia Foundation. There are a limited number of junior design positions out there that allow new designers to gain the experience required to propel their careers forward. This blog post is intended to share insights from my experience, specifically in these areas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The application process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design at the Wikimedia Foundation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the Growth project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the Editing project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of the iOS work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s next?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-application-process&quot;&gt;The application process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was applying to purpose-driven organizations because my personal values most closely align with workplaces that aim to have a positive social impact. I was interested in working at the Wikimedia Foundation because I have been a supporter of their mission and have learned about their impact through commons, peer-to-peer, and Transition Design literature. Hence, I decided to apply for a UX Design role there, and to my surprise, I was invited to interview for the position a couple of weeks later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-interview-process&quot;&gt;The interview process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interview flew by and the hiring manager shared that there were many strong candidates that applied for this role. Generally, the Foundation has only one designer per product team so they hire designers with more experience. She mentioned that there might be an internship program later on but currently there was none. I did not get the UX Designer role that I applied for, but weeks later they reached out and offered me an internship role. Due to the pandemic, they needed someone to help out on the Design team. Since this position didn’t exist in the past, the management didn’t have a clear vision of how I would spend my time, but they offered me to work on a couple of teams and participate in the Foundation’s organizational meetings and events. I accepted the role right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;internship-overview&quot;&gt;Internship overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the nine months, I rotated through three different teams, which included &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth#Objective&quot;&gt;Growth&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Editing_team&quot;&gt;Editing&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt;, where I took over small projects parallel to the team’s main work. Spending time with more than one team allowed me to observe different team processes and work on a variety of deliverables. I was also able to attend all of the design team meetings, product pre-release demos and take part in Wikimedia-wide events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Foundation is a fully remote, nonprofit organization that has a very welcoming, engaging, and collaborative environment. The design team is distributed across a number of projects and time zones, but the whole team meets on a weekly basis, which allows the designers to share their work, discuss relevant topics and get valuable feedback from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-on-the-growth-team&quot;&gt;Work on the Growth team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first 4 months of the internship I spent on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth#Objective&quot;&gt;Growth team&lt;/a&gt; working on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth/Mentor_dashboard?languageinheader=1&amp;amp;useskinversion=2&quot;&gt;mentorship dashboard&lt;/a&gt;. The team generally focuses on developing software that can help engage new contributors, especially those in mid-size Wikipedia projects. Engagement over the years has decreased because new contributors need to learn technical and cultural skills to start contributing to Wikipedia, and it is not always straightforward to acquire these skills. The team has previously built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth/Personalized_first_day/Newcomer_homepage&quot;&gt;newcomer homepage&lt;/a&gt;, which is a primary feature in the team’s core objective to improve newcomer retention. The newcomer homepage has a range of modules, one of which is the mentor module where the newcomer can reach out to an experienced editor with questions or concerns. Currently, the mentors don’t know anything about their mentees until the mentee reaches out to them. I was assigned to improve the mentor experience, which included understanding the mentor’s needs and frustrations and designing a dashboard that would allow them to be more proactive in their mentorship role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;support&quot;&gt;Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Throughout the project I had support and guidance from the designer on the Growth team, who met with me on a weekly basis and gave me feedback on my process and designs. These meetings kept me on track and helped me plan out my weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Additionally, I met with the project manager on a biweekly basis where we discussed timelines and other milestones like presenting research to the team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Later in the process, I had weekly meetings with the engineer who worked on the project with me and was a great support throughout my time on the team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discovery-phase&quot;&gt;Discovery phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began with exploring the problem space by studying mentorship, existing Wikipedia projects, and external mentoring platforms. The research helped me get accustomed to the Wikipedia-scape, but I still knew little about mentorship on the platform. Therefore, I decided to conduct interviews with mentors on wikis to which the Growth features have been deployed and talk with mentors on Russian, Ukrainian, Arabic, Vietnamese, Czech, Hungarian and French wikis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research goals for the interviews were to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the general profile of a mentor&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the mentor’s motivations and attitudes regarding mentoring&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand processes &amp;amp; behaviors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-interviews&quot;&gt;The interviews&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After transcribing and consolidating the interviews I learned that there was a continual thread that linked the mentors: their willingness and patience to teach and help newcomers. Almost every mentor I interviewed had a good experience with a mentor figure when they first started editing Wikipedia and many of the mentors were motivated by this. Most importantly I got to understand what these mentors would like to have in their dashboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An overview of their mentee list and mentee contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Template answers for the most frequently asked newcomer questions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better mentor-mentee related notifications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Better support and training for mentors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For mentees and mentors to be matched by interest or demographic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defining-and-visual-design-phase&quot;&gt;Defining and Visual Design Phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on that information I proceeded to design modules that would showcase information that would help mentors communicate with their mentees, motivate them and help them be better in their roles. It was important to consider the existing workflows of experienced editors and ensure that the dashboard was not a hindrance to them. I designed the following six modules for the first version of the dashboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mentees overview - a module where mentors can view information about the newcomers that were assigned to them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Settings - dashboard settings where the mentor has an overview of their current status and the welcome message the newcomers see&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unanswered questions - a space where mentors have access to questions they haven’t yet answered from their mentees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replies to FAQs - the mentors own saved answers that they can reuse when answering mentees’ questions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your impact - this would show the number of contributions their mentees have made, thanks they have received and total questions the mentor has answered.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resources - is a module that holds the most useful links to resources a new mentor might need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image2.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Proposed modules&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All 9 of the proposed modules for the mentor dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reviewing-the-designs&quot;&gt;Reviewing the designs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The designs were reviewed by the Growth team and discussed at the design team’s weekly design review. The feedback that followed was incorporated into the mockups. Receiving feedback from the other designers was an excellent way to improve my work and it was one of the main ways that I was able to continuously learn. Additionally, the presentations by other designers were a great source of learning and inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;development-phase&quot;&gt;Development Phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked closely with an engineer to build out the top 3 modules for the first version of the dashboard, which was then tested with the community. The modules included the mentee overview, settings and resources. Once the modules were almost ready I ran a moderated remote usability test with the goal of identifying opportunities for usability improvements related to placement, priority, navigation, and orientation. I also wanted to test whether the V1 of the dashboard had met the mentor’s expectations and see what a V2 version should prioritize. The key findings included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everyone quickly located the dashboard and the participants found the ‘mentee overview’ to be important. However, they didn’t find the module as functional as others. They wanted further ability to interact with the table.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;According to the mentors, the second version of the dashboard should include further modules such as, ‘unanswered questions’, ‘replies to FAQs’ and the ‘impact module’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lessons-learned&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biggest learnings and takeaways from the Growth team project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experience working on a constantly evolving, iterative project.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Took part in team discussions about their ongoing projects and processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned about ways the product teams deploy projects and disseminate information amongst other teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned how to work with the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily skills and processes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got in the habit of documenting all of my work to ensure that the information can be easily shared among other teams and the Wikimedia community.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ran moderated usability testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned about design systems and got more comfortable using the component library.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-on-the-editing-team&quot;&gt;Work on the Editing team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second part of the internship, I spent time with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Editing_team&quot;&gt;Editing team&lt;/a&gt; which works on editing tools across projects and improves the editor’s ability to contribute to Wikimedia projects. My project revolved around researching and exploring a tool that would help new contributors become more successful at publishing edits that adhere to Wikipedia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Policies_and_guidelines&quot;&gt;policies and guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. Currently, many new contributors’ first edits get &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:Reverting#:~:text=On%20Wikipedia%2C%20reverting%20means%20undoing,but%20leaving%20other%20contributions%20intact.&quot;&gt;reverted&lt;/a&gt; at Wikipedia because newcomers are not aware of existing policies and guidelines. Having their edits reverted demotivates the newcomers from making further edits and lowers newcomer retention. Hence, the tool could:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make contributors aware when their edits defy existing policies or guidelines before they publish their edits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help to educate newcomers about policies and guidelines&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Diminish the frequency of the newcomer’s first edits being reverted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;support-1&quot;&gt;Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly to the Growth team, I met with the Editing teams designer on a weekly basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In this team I had a set of deliverables that were determined by the project manager and designer with whom I met multiple times to discuss and present these deliverables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;discovery-phase-1&quot;&gt;Discovery phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first phase of the project included putting together a research report that would identify the known and unknown areas of the problem space. The research included information such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The newcomer editing experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ways experienced contributors interact with newcomers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The history of policies and guidelines at Wikipedia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the initial research, I learned about the evolution of the policy space at Wikipedia. Writing articles for Wikipedia was an iterative, inclusive and collaborative process where editors could co-create content. As the size of Wikipedia grew, one of its strongest criticisms was that it was an unreliable resource. Over time, community members have made quality control one of the wikis primary focuses. In light of making the information more reliable, the number of policies and guidelines has increased over the years. There are now more policies and guidelines than ever before, they have become complex and are cited much more frequently by editors as a means to support their activity on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team spoke about choosing one policy and using it as a way to help guide the project, it would serve as the policy to showcase the potential editing tool. After consideration, I decided to focus on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Verifiability&quot;&gt;verifiability&lt;/a&gt;, as it is one of the most important policies for newcomers to be aware of. Since Wikipedia is an online encyclopedia, its content must stem from reliable sources, and therefore defying the verifiability policy while editing will ensure that the editors’ contributions will be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Reverting&quot;&gt;reverted&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Deletion_policy&quot;&gt;deleted&lt;/a&gt;.
During the next phase of the project, I did a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/YpABXIwc1OfvOW0sCycQka/Editing-policy-project%3A-Comparative-analysis?node-id=0%3A1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;comparative analysis&lt;/a&gt; of Wikipedia projects as well as external platforms and apps whose objectives were to help teach contributors a specific skill set. I looked mainly at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Grammar correction apps/writing apps&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Education apps and extensions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Existing Wikipedia projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gamification methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This aided in narrowing the ways the editing tool could be displayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defining-phase-and-the-visual-design-phase&quot;&gt;Defining phase and the visual design phase&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a difficult phase of the project. With so much valuable information and perhaps more questions than when I had started, I took the first stab at designing the editing tool. The editing tool is a feature that contributors would be able to use to see areas in the text that defied the verifiability policy. For instance, the tool would suggest placing citations in certain areas and it would highlight titles that need to be linked. Additionally, the tool would allow users to quickly access resources about verifiability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image5.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Recommendations in side panel&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/HDIb51f195EZKZTpDLR5kM/Editing-Project%3A-Policy-Check-Mockups%3A-V1?node-id=0%3A1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Policy Check&lt;/a&gt; with all recommendations and content located in a side panel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image3.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Inline recommendations&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another version of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/HDIb51f195EZKZTpDLR5kM/Editing-Project%3A-Policy-Check-Mockups%3A-V1?node-id=0%3A1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Policy Check&lt;/a&gt; where recommendations appear inline with the text&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;presenting-at-wikimania&quot;&gt;Presenting at Wikimania&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the editing team, I was able to present the editing tool project at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimania.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikimania&quot;&gt;Wikimania 2021&lt;/a&gt;. I presented with other volunteers in a talk called ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QUhhdgF_1RI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Editing the Wiki Way: software and future of editing&lt;/a&gt;’. I was able to meet numerous committed community members that are passionate about various projects and discuss the future of editing with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lessons-learned-1&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biggest learnings and takeaways from the Editing teams project:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gained experience working on a research-heavy project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Took part in team discussions about their ongoing projects and understood the processes and how these are similar/different to the Growths team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned a lot about policies and guidelines on Wikipedia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;daily-skills-and-processes&quot;&gt;Daily skills and processes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Put together a research report&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gained practice presenting my process and artifacts to a multitude of people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Became more comfortable using Miro diagrams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;work-on-the-ios-team&quot;&gt;Work on the iOS team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final and shortest stretch of the internship was with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot;&gt;iOS team&lt;/a&gt;. They are part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Apps project&lt;/a&gt; together with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android&quot;&gt;Android team&lt;/a&gt;. The apps teams are historically considered to be more experimental, in part because they have lower user traffic than the desktop and mobile versions of Wikipedia and are used more by readers rather than power editors, who generally engage differently with existing features. It was very interesting to learn a completely new set of processes and to get accustomed to using the apps style guide and a slightly different product altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;support-2&quot;&gt;Support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the iOS team I also met with the designer on a weekly basis and had meetings with the project manager every 2-3 weeks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tasks&quot;&gt;Tasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team was working on a notification center during my time there and I was tasked to complete a set of audits, do research, and do smaller design tasks that would be helpful in the future. I really appreciated that the team prioritizes designing and developing for a variety of accessibility needs. This is made possible by &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/swift/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Swift&lt;/a&gt;, Apple’s native programming language, which allows one to easily create products that give support to those who might be, for example, visually impaired. Through the variety of deliverables, I was able to engage with different parts of the app and learn more about another pocket of the wiki-verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image1.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Warning explorations mobile banner&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first tasks I worked on - the iOS mobile banner warning explorations. We ultimately chose the middle option where the warning has a background color and is inline with the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lessons-learned-2&quot;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biggest learnings and takeaways from the time spent on the iOS team&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Designing for iPad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned more about Apple’s accessibility support&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned about iOS UI and deployment processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daily skills and processes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Learned about the iOS team’s design &amp;amp; engineering processes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Became comfortable doing design audits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got to know Apple’s Human Interface Guidelines in greater detail&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could not have wished for a better internship experience! The 9 months were incredibly diverse, challenging, and fun. I was supported throughout by amazing designers, project managers, engineers, and numerous different team members from the Growth, Editing, and iOS teams, who worked with me to improve my skill set as a designer and helped me find my footing in the wiki-verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my internship, I have been offered the opportunity to join the iOS team full-time. The design team is interested in creating more formal internship opportunities for junior designers. This year they have welcomed two new interns to the Design team, and hopefully there will be more internship positions available in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thank you to Lucy Blackwell, Rita Ho, Jess Klein and Carolyn Li-Madeo for this opportunity, as well as your support and feedback!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The projects, the processes, and the main learnings from a 9-month design internship at the Wikimedia Foundation.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image4.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/entering-wikimedia-universe/image4.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Hey, check out this egg-laying wool-milk-pig: said no one ever</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/06/14/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hey, check out this egg-laying wool-milk-pig: said no one ever" /><published>2022-06-14T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-06-14T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/06/14/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/06/14/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Robin Schoenbaechler&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/itsjaztanner&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Jazmin Tanner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, the Wikimedia Foundation Android team has focused on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android/Communication&quot;&gt;improving the communications experience&lt;/a&gt; in the Wikipedia Android app. Asynchronous collaboration is a core component of the Wikipedia editing experience, and the lower the entry barrier to editing, the more diverse the content will be for our 14 projects across 300 languages. This diversity of content and collaborators is core to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Movement_Strategy&quot;&gt;movement strategy&lt;/a&gt;, which focuses on knowledge equity and knowledge as a service. The movement strategy brings us closer to ensuring our projects represent the sum of all knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As the organization focuses on knowledge equity, the Product and Technology departments have worked on a&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/freely-sharing-the-sum-of-all-knowledge/the-journey-to-make-wikipedias-technology-more-equitable-152321df1366&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;framework for inclusive product development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. To ensure the framework was reflective of the varying scope and team composition of our development teams, seven Wikimedia Foundation teams signed up to test the playbook and provide feedback. The feedback would serve as an input for V2 of the playbook in our framework. With our team’s goal of reducing the barrier to communication and collaboration in the Wikipedia Android app and being very &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2022/01/21/accessibility-support-in-the-wikipedia-android-app/&quot;&gt;intentional about accessibility&lt;/a&gt;, we were a logical test team for the playbook. We also recognized there would be a lot to balance as we worked towards this goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the original request to improve communications in the apps came from experienced members of our community that largely wrote in English, we wanted to be very intentional about partnering with members of the community who haven’t been historically centered in our projects. Depending on the development team and platform the partner communities could look different. In our context, the identified partner community members consisted of women and non-binary editors on Japanese Wikipedia, French and Arabic editors in Mali, Egypt, Morocco, and DR Congo, Hindi and Indonesian Wikipedia editors, English Wikipedia editors in Nigeria and visually impaired English Wikipedia editors in India. You can read more about our process in selecting these partner communities &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android/2021Roadmap?tableofcontents=0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-egg-laying-wool-milk-pig-for-android&quot;&gt;The egg-laying wool-milk-pig for Android&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/1-eierlegende-wollmichsau.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Eierlegende Wollmilchsau&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wollmilchsau.webp&quot;&gt;The “Eierlegende Wollmilchsau”&lt;/a&gt;
 | By Georg Mittenecker
 | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 2.5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--audio&quot;&gt;
	&lt;audio src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/die-eierlegende-wollmilchsau.m4a&quot; alt=&quot;Word pronunciation&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;/audio&gt;

	
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Listen the pronunciation&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In German, there’s a popular idiom of the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eierlegende_Wollmilchsau&quot;&gt;Eierlegende Wollmilchsau&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/strong&gt; It roughly translates to an egg-laying wool-milk-pig. The phrase describes an imaginary animal that combines unique characteristics of some of the most renowned animal species: chicken (lay eggs), sheep (provide wool), cow (give milk), and pig (meat).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idiom encapsulates what we are trying to achieve; a seemingly unachievable and perfect outcome of a product for diverse user needs: all the benefits, no drawbacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article shares the steps we took to develop a design approach that reflects the ideal the egg-laying wool-milk-pig represents. When you finish reading, we hope you come away with the following lessons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The importance of &lt;strong&gt;designing with people&lt;/strong&gt; instead of for them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Understanding when to focus and when to see the big picture&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;User Segmentation: Meeting audiences where they are&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Leveraging Data: Data doesn’t show where to go; it shows where you are&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Focus Mode: Adding capabilities without distraction&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Customization as a means to include:&lt;/strong&gt; Optimizing the article experience based on different user goals&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-shape-our-tools-thereafter-our-tools-shape-us&quot;&gt;“We shape our tools, thereafter our tools shape us”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quote by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marshall_McLuhan&quot;&gt;Marshall McLuhan&lt;/a&gt; feels very true for Wikipedia. Here’s why: When we &lt;a href=&quot;https://uxdesign.cc/in-search-of-the-perfect-search-for-wikipedia-136f86ac6168&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;improved searching for articles&lt;/a&gt;, we realized that people use Wikipedia in unique ways. Use cases and opinions for those who regularly use the Wikipedia app vary substantially. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android/Communication/UsertestingJuly2021?tableofcontents=0#Results&quot;&gt;difference of perspectives&lt;/a&gt; even rang true when learning from our target audiences what their communication preferences were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Editors&lt;/strong&gt; see a need for more editing capabilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The only missing feature is providing notifications like on the website”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readers&lt;/strong&gt; love to read articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why would I need Wikipedia notifications? I don’t even have a login!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wikipedians&lt;/strong&gt; long for missing key features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Please make it possible to access talk pages and edit histories.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;And others&lt;/strong&gt; simply prefer the Wikipedia web experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Functionally very similar to the web browser experience, if not less intuitive.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a tiny sample of the sometimes contradictory feedback we receive from people using our app primarily or in conjunction with other platforms. However, these examples exemplify that qualitative feedback points us in multiple directions, especially when we weigh the maturity of a wiki. So, when user feedback pulls us in multiple directions, how do we decide where to go?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could be easy to rely on the intuition of the team. However, as we learned from the Inclusive Product Development framework, even with a globally dispersed, fully remote team that aims to live up to the organizational &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/01/10/surfacing-and-embracing-diversity-within-your-team.html&quot;&gt;goal of embracing diversity&lt;/a&gt;, we must be wary of introducing our biases into the product and strive to be inclusive of these different audience goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-doesnt-show-where-to-go-it-shows-where-you-are&quot;&gt;Data doesn’t show where to go, it shows where you are&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we delve deeper into our quantitative data, there’s evidence of commonalities amongst different cultures, use cases, and needs. Our data scientist, Shay Nowick, was able to provide the insight that &lt;a href=&quot;https://analytics.wikimedia.org/published/reports/wikipedia-android-app/metrics/2021-03.html&quot;&gt;62%&lt;/a&gt; of those that opt-in to share anonymized data visit the article view most frequently in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/2-article-view.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Article View&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article view is the most visited screen in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This insight seemed logical considering the Wikipedia Android app was initially created as a “readers-first” tool. It always had editing capabilities, but the editing experience was historically limited, had a high participation barrier and resulted in a low edit count compared to other platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-areas-to-create-the-egg-laying-wool-milk-pig&quot;&gt;Focus areas to create the egg-laying wool-milk-pig&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;balancing-reading-and-editing&quot;&gt;Balancing reading and editing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2021/11/30/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/&quot;&gt;“readers first” strategy&lt;/a&gt; shifted from full-article editing to explore the concept of micro contributions with the introduction of a feature called suggested edits. Micro contributions aim to lower the barrier to contributing by introducing an alternative to longform writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/3-suggested-edits.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Suggested Edits&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suggested edits present opportunities for small but vital contributions to Wikipedia. We are aiming to raise edit awareness and make contributing more accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we identified it as gentle onboarding for new editors, and creating new forms of content. As this capability was rolled out, the visibility and editing calls to action (CTA) were intentionally made prominent on the home page toolbar and in the frequently visited article view, shifting the UI away from the “readers first” experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this change could ultimately distract someone who just had the goal of reading as you can see in the example below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/4-edit-calls.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Edit calls&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiple edit calls to action distract from reading the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data shows that the edit asks were somewhat effective in encouraging readers to add missing article information. The &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;+ ADD ARTICLE DESCRIPTION&lt;/code&gt; button alone is the source of almost a fourth of all edits (~23%) made in the Wikipedia Android app. Adding the CTAs was a deliberate strategic move to encourage editing, and it seemed to be effective. Despite the distracting nature, hiding them for all people at all times was not an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But to the point someone raised about not always wanting to see editing features when they’re in the mood to read, how could we accommodate them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to not wanting to distract with too many editing call to actions, a community member left the following feedback on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Google Play&lt;/a&gt; store which made us question the article’s bottom toolbar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Why have you taken away the ability to go full screen? Why do we have to see the bottom toolbar all the time?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I want the option to hide the bottom bar as I scroll down. Thank you.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/5-toolbar.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Toolbar&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article’s bottom toolbar stays visible when reading and scrolling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usability tests from three years ago gave us the insight that some users preferred seeing the bottom toolbar at all times or struggled to find features when the toolbar disappeared.. For example one user shared:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’m deleting the app because it doesn’t support find in page”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article most certainly did support Find in page, we call it “Find in article” and it was located in the bottom toolbar that formerly disappeared on scroll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-distraction-free&quot;&gt;Reading distraction-free&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insights mentioned above, paired with our desire to introduce more prominent editing features, like a prominent icon for talk pages to make it more discoverable, made our interest in honoring some explicit requests from the community to add a reading focus mode that much more urgent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We chose to put the reading focus mode toggle into “Theme” because it’s related to existing preferences like font size or family. When reading focus mode is enabled, CTAs disappear, and the article becomes full screen on scroll, meaning the top and bottom toolbars disappear; limiting distractions while reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a concern within the team that users would have trouble remembering how to access editing features again once reading focus mode was enabled. To ensure we could overcome this obstacle we conducted usability testing with our partner communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of using a clickable design prototype, our developers created a working prototype that our participants could download:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--video&quot;&gt;
	&lt;video src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/6-prototype.webm&quot; alt=&quot;Prototype&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;/video&gt;

	
	&lt;figcaption&gt;Not only were people able to successfully disable the feature if they wanted to edit, they provided other positive insights as well.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s better, the full-screen mode makes it easier to read, there’s nothing that bothers me!” &lt;em&gt;– Usability test participant, Arabic Wikipedia reader&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This reading focus mode is really helpful, excludes all unwanted options, it makes the page more comfortable to read” &lt;em&gt;– Usability test participant, Hindi Wikipedia reader&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s a good feature as the majority of us are here to read articles. It’s a good function to have to limit distractions.” &lt;em&gt;– Usability test participant, Japanese Wikipedia reader&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These insights gave us the confidence to release the feature to production and enhance discoverability. Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/Usability-testing-Android-Feb-2022-Analysis-c1b536068b78486e80da99c4e0461829&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;detailed analysis&lt;/a&gt; to dig deeper into our findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading focus mode was also a success from a quantitative perspective.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;After its release, 80% of all people discovering and interacting with the feature kept it as their default preference.&lt;/strong&gt; We did consider making this feature a default experience, but wanted to ensure users knew they could edit, and for that reason we will continue to have reading focus mode disabled by default.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;customizing-the-experience&quot;&gt;Customizing the experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading focus mode was not the only feature where we aimed to strike the right balance between the needs of readers and editors.&lt;/strong&gt; As we added more features to the app, our overflow menu grew, and we noticed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/Analysis-experienced-users-c78408250c5241da9cf1df9efb036cc6&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;users asking for features&lt;/a&gt; that existed but were hidden in the overflow menu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Doesn’t allow you to read the page’s Edit history or Talk page. So practically only useful for reading, not editing.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It has good features like a menu option to switch between languages”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No option to add to Watchlist, I don’t like the interface or look.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s missing categories.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Please add the capability to share an article’s URL.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the maturity of the wiki, the audience, and user goals, the preferences for what links were available varied, which made it apparent that the next phase of our work before releasing new communication features needed to take a closer look at shortcut usage in the bottom toolbar and the top menu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/7-research-data.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Research Data&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our data informed us that the bottom toolbar and top menu usage ranking were as follows: 1. Contents (61.22%) 2. Language (17.57%) 3. Save (8.95%) 4. Find in article (5.76%) 5. Theme (3.03%) 6. Share (2.19%) 7. Explore (0.47%) 8. New tab (0.33%) 9. Categories (0.16%) 10. Edit history (0.16%) 11. Talk page (0.12%) 12. Watch (0.04%). Note that newer features, and features hidden in the overflow menu were clicked less often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designing for people’s preferences while keeping the experience focused challenged us, but is becoming more of an industry standard with the launch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/blog/announcing-material-you&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Material You&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; Relatedly, one of our approaches to toolbar customization was inspired by Google Chrome. We explored the idea of adding all items to the top menu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/8-actions-destinations.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Actions and Destinations&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Access to the actions and destinations in Chrome on Android.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We asked ourselves if putting all options into one place is considered good or bad information architecture and found the answer in existing research. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/hamburger-menus/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Hiding interface elements reduces their usage&lt;/a&gt; as they are less discoverable.&lt;/strong&gt; We did not want actions related to the article to be less used, as our audience finds them helpful, so we continued with having shortcuts in the bottom toolbar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-the-egg-laying-wool-milk-pig-came-to-life&quot;&gt;How the-egg-laying wool-milk-pig came to life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prototyping-the-first-version&quot;&gt;Prototyping the first version&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We landed on letting people customize their shortcuts in the bottom toolbar, and developed several prototypes to test which approach best achieved our goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned that people had difficulties discovering the “Customize toolbar” feature within the “Theme” shortcut, trouble discovering where items that were moved out of the toolbar and into the overflow menu were placed and issues dragging and dropping items, a gesture we incorrectly assumed would be intuitive. This implored us to have a closer look and ensure our drag and drop movements met Web Accessibility Guidelines(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.boia.org/blog/how-drag-and-drop-movements-affect-web-accessibility&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;WCAG&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--video&quot;&gt;
	&lt;video src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/10-customizable-toolbar.webm&quot; alt=&quot;Customizable Toolbar&quot; controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
	&lt;/video&gt;

	
	&lt;figcaption&gt;The original design for the customizable toolbar had usability shortcomings. Participants ignored the blue tooltip for discovery and couldn&apos;t drag and drop.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address the discoverability issues we added onboarding tooltips, even with this addition, users were struggling to find the feature and effectively scrolled past it making it disappear. You can read our &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T298978&quot;&gt;analysis&lt;/a&gt; for full details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;testing-discarding-and-iterating&quot;&gt;Testing, discarding, and iterating&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We now faced a real example from the inclusive product development playbook of having to choose equity over speed.&lt;/strong&gt; After sharing the results with our communities and collaborating with other Wikimedia Foundation teams like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Design&quot;&gt;design team&lt;/a&gt;, we created two iterations of the original design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/11-variants.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Variants&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Variant A featured a ‘More’ menu item in the bottom toolbar alongside four shortcuts that could be customized. Variant B used the top menu as the entry point to customization, leaving the bottom toolbar largely unchanged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal was to determine which of the two versions participants preferred, why they preferred it, if there were differences amongst language preferences and if the participant would use the feature. Both variants featured:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;A persistent tooltip that only disappears when pressing the newly added ‘GOT IT’ button.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In partnership with UX copywriter Jacqui Clydesdale, we created default helper tooltips to explain the drag and drop function.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Simplified language (e.g., ‘shortcuts’ instead of ‘links’), to ensure terminology was accessible .&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing one more round of usability tests, we gathered feedback on the two variants from ten Arabic, Hindi, Japanese, Indonesian, and French-speaking participants. The results were almost evenly split, so we could not take a majority wins approach. It was evident that both variants were drastic improvements when it came to discoverability and usability. With no clear winner between the two variants we took into consideration Google material design guidance, and considered which change would be less jarring for our existing audiences. This led us to move forward with variant B. The reactions to the updates in &lt;strong&gt;variant B were&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s awesome, it was easy to understand and find.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The design is very good, I haven’t seen this anywhere else.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’d use the feature 2-3 times and think it’d improve the experience.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“It’s a very good feature for people who use Wikipedia daily.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There’s one more shortcut in the bottom toolbar, a lot of people have a habit of clicking the top menu to look for things.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we chose our path forward between the two variants, there were still issues that were exposed in usability testing that we found important to address before a full roll out could occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;designing-cross-cultural&quot;&gt;Designing cross-cultural&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As we mentioned above, we aimed to partner with very specific audiences. When conducting usability testing it was important to test with our partner community in their native languages.&lt;/strong&gt; Building real installable app versions in Android’s file format &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apk_(file_format)&quot;&gt;apk&lt;/a&gt; made the difference. &lt;strong&gt;Due to testing working app versions, we identified various localization issues, and prioritized solving them before release&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the Wikimedia Foundation it is customary to use an open-source translation service in partnership with our community called &lt;a href=&quot;https://translatewiki.net/&quot;&gt;translatewiki.net&lt;/a&gt;. The project, made available by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Translatewiki.net&quot;&gt;Niklas Laxström&lt;/a&gt;, is sensitive to the unique vocabulary used on Wikipedia and is able to consider nuances that machine translation doesn’t always capture. However, because it is community sourced, we do have to take our time in waiting for the translations to come through, or even reaching out for support before launching usability testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, a third of our readers access Wikipedia in multiple languages. As usability test participants were bilingual too, we noticed that people’s device and app language differed. This is not necessarily bad, as it leads to observing even more diverse forms of use. However, for our purposes we deliberately wanted to test in Arabic, Hindi, Indonesian, Japanese, and French, so we asked people to set their device language at the beginning of the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This step was very important because it exposed bugs and unexpected behaviors for right-to-left (RTL) environments earlier than waiting for users to alert us via the app store. Namely, when conducting usability testing, we observed glaring bugs with the direction of typography, icons, and images in RTL that needed to be corrected prior to release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the support of our Product and Technology leadership to build for equity over speed, conducting design research in regions and languages beyond the English-speaking community will continue to be our team’s default. As will it continue to be our team’s default to prioritize fixing potential localization challenges and improving accessibility across cultures, languages, abilities, interests and backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While an egg-laying wool-milk pig does not exist in nature, we have the unique opportunity to design the closest ideal in a digital product. And, by fulfilling one user group’s needs, tremendous advantages will inevitably present itself in serving the needs of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We are committed to equitably&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/05/21/improve-ux-for-everyone.html&quot;&gt;design with everyone&lt;/a&gt; and modify the proverbial table to include as many as possible — and we think you should too&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;figure--image&quot;&gt;
	&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/12-diversity-white-bg.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Diversity White BG&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; /&gt;

	
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the features mentioned in this article are now available in the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android app on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;. Our team is working on many more exciting features to offer all the advantages and satisfy (most of) our user’s sophisticated and sometimes even contradictory needs in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WikimediaMobile&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;@WikipediaMobile&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter for the latest news related to Wikipedia apps. If you don’t want to miss the latest design changes to Wikipedia, follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WikimediaDesign&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;@WikimediaDesign&lt;/a&gt;. Please let us know what you think about the updates in the comments below, on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps&quot;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:android@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;email&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Matt Cleinman, Shay Nowick, Matthew Williams, Carolyn Li-Madeo, Johan Jönsson, Lucy Blackwell, Sam Patton, Rita Ho, and Jess Klein for their contributions to this article.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How designing for customization leads to inclusion on Wikipedia.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/0-diversity-black-bg.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/egg-laying-wool-milk-pig/0-diversity-black-bg.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing variant experiments is as simple as A/B. See?</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/04/04/designing-variant-experiments.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing variant experiments is as simple as A/B. See?" /><published>2022-04-04T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-04T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/04/04/designing-variant-experiments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/04/04/designing-variant-experiments.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@reetssydney&quot;&gt;Rita Ho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As hinted at in the name, the purpose of the Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Growth team&lt;/a&gt; is to grow the number of new people who come and make a first edit on Wikipedia, and to keep more of them around (a.k.a. “editor retention”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an element of teaching and persuasion involved, since we need to convey to the majority of people extremely familiar with using Wikipedia one way (reading and consuming information) that in fact they should consider using it quite differently (participating in writing and changing the information), and then guiding them how to use it in this brand new way. It’s like telling someone who has eaten eggs their whole life that actually, the egg shells can be eaten as a calcium supplement too, if properly prepared (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Egg_as_food#cite_note-31&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;it’s true&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our approach to this mission has been to work briskly, and try out our ideas of how to provide opportunities to edit as a series of experiments. Instead of releasing a new feature or tool for everyone and iterating on the results, we test them out on smaller groups (typically limited to people on a few smaller Wikipedia languages and rarely on the bigger languages like English), then compare how the experimental feature performs against the control (the existing experience). We then iterate on the designs based on a mixture of usability feedback, community feedback, and finally from interpreting the resulting data from people using the feature (or in some cases not using it!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one of the key features on which our team has worked, we decided to run an A/B test. Whilst it is relatively common for the Fundraising department to multivariate test small UI variations (e.g., different button placement, copy differences) on donation banners, it has been less commonly used by the Product Design team to experiment with different user experiences in reading and editing on Wikipedia itself. A major reason we don’t typically run such A/B tests is that there is a high bar for respecting the privacy of people who use Wikipedia, especially those who are anonymous&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. However, since the Growth features are offered to those who have already created an account, this was a case where A/B testing was a good fit for our purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ab-testing&quot;&gt;A/B testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-inciting-incident-a-new-experiment&quot;&gt;The inciting incident: A new experiment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew from past research that many people who create a Wikipedia account often do so with the intention of editing, but then aren’t able to easily find articles to which they can contribute. This led us to design a feature that appears for newcomers after they join Wikipedia, which encourages them to do some small “suggested edits” (like copyediting or adding links) on articles across a variety of topics they might be interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/suggested-edits.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page of the new editors experiences research.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Suggested_edits_-_sample_mobile_screens.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Suggested edits - sample mobile screens&lt;/a&gt; | By RHo (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our hypothesis underpinning this feature was that if we give people specific, and achievable small editing tasks to do, they will be more likely to try a first edit, and more of these people will do enough to build their expertise and interest to become long term contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diagram below illustrates the user flow initially designed for the feature. Newcomers would first be provided with a prompt to “opt-in” to seeing these suggestions, and if they choose to proceed, they are then provided with some short onboarding screens to learn what it’s about and how to customise suggestions to their interests before seeing the actual suggested articles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/user-flow.png&quot; alt=&quot;Var A - Suggested edits v1.1 variant A flow diagram&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Diagram showing the intended user flow design. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Var_A_-_Suggested_edits_v1.1_variant_A_flow_diagram.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Var A - Suggested edits v1.1 variant A flow diagram &lt;/a&gt; | By RHo (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;experimenting-within-the-controlled-experiment-enter-variant-b&quot;&gt;Experimenting within the controlled experiment: Enter Variant B&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started developing the design for this feature, with the design described above as the new feature that would be implemented in a controlled experiment – comparing editing retention with a control group of new accounts which would not receive these suggested edits at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the course of development, Marshall, our Product Manager had a hypothesis that if we showed people the suggestions sooner (without onboarding), that they would do more edits. I agreed this was a valid point, and wondered how we could balance this consideration with my reasons for the importance of user education in letting people understand why doing one was valuable and relevant to them (going back to my earlier analogy of explaining how one can eat egg shells).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how we decided to run our first simple variant test - a nested test within the controlled experiment. We would split the experiment group so that half the participants received variant A which had the “full” designed flow with opt-in and user education; whilst the other half received variant B where they would see the suggestions immediately in their newcomer homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/variant-test.png&quot; alt=&quot;Var A - Suggested edits v1.1 variant A flow diagram&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Var_A_vs_B_-_Suggested_edits_v1.1_A-B_variant_test_flow_diagram.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Var A - Suggested edits v1.1 variant A flow diagram &lt;/a&gt; | By RHo (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-results-are-in-and-the-winner-is&quot;&gt;The results are in and the winner is…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with the data analyst and PM, the key metrics were examined and interpreted to figure out what was significant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
	&lt;figure class=&quot;half-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/interaction.png&quot; alt=&quot; Growth team Var A vs. B result slide 4 2020-04-03&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Growth_team_Var_A_vs._B_result_slide_4_2020-04-03.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Growth team Var A vs. B result slide 4 2020-04-03&lt;/a&gt; | By Nettrom (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/figure&gt;
	&lt;figure class=&quot;half-width&quot;&gt;
		&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/success.png&quot; alt=&quot;Variant A vs. B for edit success 2020-06-08&quot; /&gt;
		&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Variant_A_vs._B_for_edit_success_2020-06-08.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Variant A vs. B for edit success 2020-06-08&lt;/a&gt; | By Nettrom (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
	&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, the results vindicated the user-education hypothesis! The results varied depending on the wiki and platform, but generally showed that whilst more people did indeed interact with the suggested edits module when it was shown to them immediately in variant B on desktop; in the end, more of those in variant A who had to opt-in to the feature and saw the onboarding made successful edits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-informed-iteration&quot;&gt;Data-informed iteration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what did this mean for design improvements moving forward?
As we saw it, the three key takeaways from the test were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Featuring suggested edits prominently&lt;/strong&gt; was key to getting people to try the tool; but at the same time…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Onboarding is crucial&lt;/strong&gt; to driving more people to successfully completing an edit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile and Desktop&lt;/strong&gt; performed differently so as not to be strictly comparable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was based on these findings that the next two new variants C/D were created&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, which applied the best aspects we interpreted from the results of the first test, roughly translated into the designs in the following ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Variants C and D centred much more on the suggested edits feature in the homepage, removing a smaller ‘start’ module and making it more prominent in size and the focus of onboarding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Onboarding is available in both variants C &amp;amp; D, though it is optional (and more easily dismissable) in variant C.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On mobile, variants C and D explore different ways to give more direct access to the suggested edits feature immediately from the homepage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/variants-cd.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page of the new editors experiences research.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/F31790797&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Variant C and D flow&lt;/a&gt; | By Rita Ho | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-decisions-affirmed-by-data&quot;&gt;Design decisions affirmed by data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it was great to see our interpretation of data and design decisions payoff! In the form of both C &amp;amp; D variants in the next iteration leading to both more usage and successful edits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page of the new editors experiences research.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Chart showing the interaction, task clicks, and saved edits from the suggested edits feature on the homepage, with increases highlighted when the design was changed from to variants C and D.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learnings-and-tips&quot;&gt;Learnings and tips&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the gratification of seeing variant tests make a difference in people’s experience of a design, it’s been a great learning experience to apply this method of design optimisation often seen as hard to utilise effectively with other more qualitative approaches.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-3&quot; id=&quot;ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, these are the key aspects of running A/B tests:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set a clear, testable hypothesis.&lt;/strong&gt; Formulating the rationale for why different designs bring about better outcomes will help in devising an experiment that accurately measures the impact of those design changes. Besides that, it’s also good practice for critical thinking that is helpful for design decision making when there is no time/need to run experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Determine if the effort is worth the investment.&lt;/strong&gt; Once the hypothesis is set, ask whether it is worth the considerable time and investment request to run an experiment to get the answer, or whether other tactics (such as user testing) can be used instead to help move the design forward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Be bold with the variant differences.&lt;/strong&gt; If the test ends up being about different button colours, it’s probably a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/multivariate-testing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;multivariate test&lt;/a&gt; that is needed. On the other hand, it’s also not advisable to have too many variables (such as testing complete redesigns) since this would make it hard to pinpoint what changes made the difference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask the right questions of the data:&lt;/strong&gt; For our team, we care about how many people finish an edit (saving it), not if they started it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborate closely with data-savvy colleagues.&lt;/strong&gt; It was vital to work closely with the data analyst and product manager to check the hypothesis and test was sound, to ensure the correct (and sufficient) data was being measured, and then properly analysed. Having an data analyst expert is also very important in removing &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confirmation_bias&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;confirmation bias&lt;/a&gt;, akin to having a design researcher conduct usability testing. They are the key person in determining the experiment feasibility and timeframe from an audience size perspective to get statistically significant results. For folks without an awesome analyst at hand, there are free tools available (like this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.experimentcalculator.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;) that provide sample sizes and time needed to run robust experiments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Involve your engineering team early too.&lt;/strong&gt; Another important partnership is obviously the engineering team who are responsible for both implementing the different features and instrumentation to measure the experiment. Involving them as early as possible as to the parts of the experience that may vary will help them to build them a flexible framework for A/B testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bonus-learning-before-i-go&quot;&gt;Bonus learning before I go&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final learning is not about the A/B test method itself, but about people we design for that came from these variant tests: there’s nothing wrong with providing guidance. I don’t really like the term “user education” or “onboarding” because it is a little condescending (the implication is that the onus is on people to learn how to get on board with this awesome product). User onboarding is actually an opportunity for us as designers to provide persuasive and clear communication, explaining to our newcomer editors what the value is for them to make contributions to Wikipedia in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! You can read more details about the Growth team’s variant testing on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth/Personalized_first_day/Variant_testing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;project page&lt;/a&gt;, or about all of our initiatives for bringing new editors to Wikipedia on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;team page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Marshall Miller, Morten Warncke-Wang, and Matthew Williams for your feedback, editing help, and additional insights into A/B testing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;Details about “Privacy Conscious A/B testing for anonymous readers” can be read &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Privacy-conscious_AB_testing_at_Wikimedia_Foundation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;Phabricator task with more details of the implementation &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T246533&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt; https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T246533 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/putting-ab-testing-in-its-place/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;https://www.nngroup.com/articles/putting-ab-testing-in-its-place/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How we used variant testing in designs for new editors on Wikipedia.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/designing-experiments/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing Wikifunctions, brick by brick.</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/03/14/wikifunctions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing Wikifunctions, brick by brick." /><published>2022-03-14T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-03-14T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/03/14/wikifunctions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/03/14/wikifunctions.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aishwaryavardhana.com&quot;&gt;Aishwarya Vardhana&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-wikifunctions&quot;&gt;What is Wikifunctions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikifunctions will be a collaboratively edited multilingual library of functions. It will be the first platform The Wikimedia Foundation launches since &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikidata&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikidata&lt;/a&gt; in 2012, and part of a bigger vision towards an Abstract Wikipedia, which you can read about at &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Abstract_Wikipedia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Abstract Wikipedia on meta-wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-function-and-its-parts&quot;&gt;A function and its parts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not a programmer you might not be familiar with what a function needs to be usable, or to use technical-speak “to run”. A function takes an input (e.g. the population of a city) and provides an output (e.g. the acres of watershed needed to supply residents with water). It can do this calculation over and over again for different cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A function has three parts. The function definition (part 1), the implementation (part 2), and a test (part 3) to validate. These three components – the definition, implementation, and tests – are what a function needs to perform and be usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A definition defines the functions behavior. What type of inputs does it accept? How many? What will it output? An implementation is the set of instructions that transforms an input into an output. A test is what validates the implementation and ensures it performs correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/function-model.png&quot; alt=&quot;Function model&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-functions-do&quot;&gt;What can functions do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For starters, you might use a function to wake up in the morning. Let’s say you want to sleep 8 hours tonight, you could ask a function, &lt;em&gt;“If I go to sleep at 10 P.M. what time should I wake up to get 8 hours of sleep?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples-of-general-questions-that-could-be-answered-by-functions&quot;&gt;Examples of general questions that could be answered by functions:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the distance from my house in northern Sao Paulo, Brazil to the nearest beach?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If I took out a $240,000 loan and my loan term is 30-year fixed with a 4% interest rate, what is my monthly mortgage?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If the omicron variant has a transmission rate of 25% among vaccinated people, how quickly could it spread in a city with 2,059 people per square kilometer, 95% of whom are vaccinated?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When in the next ten years will my birthday fall on a Saturday if I was born March 28, 1954?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;examples-of-wikimedia-related-questions-that-could-be-answered-by-functions&quot;&gt;Examples of Wikimedia-related questions that could be answered by functions:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given the dates of birth and death of a person, how old did the person get?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given a population and an area, what is the population density?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given an image on Commons, crop it and run it through a filter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Given two images on Commons, which one is more red?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Based on Wikidata, how are Queen Elizabeth II and Barack Obama related to each other?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functions are ubiquitous in modern life, from the apps we use daily (e.g. maps and search) to the analyses made by scientists, doctors, journalists, and financial advisors, functions enable our activities by efficiently and precisely making meaning through calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functions will provide the code that translates language-independent articles from Abstract Wikipedia into natural language Wikipedia articles. This will theoretically allow more people to share more knowledge in more languages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This blog post is about how to create, view, and edit functions in Wikifunctions, and the design process behind making this happen.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-audience&quot;&gt;Our audience&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to other Wikimedia projects, our hope and aim is for Wikifunctions to be inviting, accessible to, and available to all people across the world. This is why we are designing a &lt;strong&gt;multilingual platform that is mobile friendly&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several roles for people within the Wikifunctions ecosystem. There are “answer seekers”, or people who simply want to learn about functions and use them. A level deeper are those who edit or materially contribute to Wikifunctions in some capacity. They could be function patrollers, programmers who write implementations, translators, admins who approve of proposed implementations and tests, or test writers who QA implementations. These folks will maintain functions and documentation. Among these editors there will be technical and nontechnical folks. Leading up to launch and post-launch, &lt;strong&gt;our team aims to increase the agency of the nontechnical folks and “junior” techies&lt;/strong&gt; by creating pathways for them to contribute meaningfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of creating these pathways is simplifying a complicated process. Functions are not simple. They are complex in that they require computational thinking and well-written documentation. When designing the creation experience, our objective was to design an editor interface that looks and feels friendly to nontechnical people and radically simplifies a complex process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-approach&quot;&gt;Our approach&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We explored different mental models for Wikifunctions such as collaborative coding, a structured Q&amp;amp;A forum, a homework helper, infrastructure for Abstract Wikipedia, and a ‘generic library of functions’. &lt;strong&gt;We settled on the structured Q&amp;amp;A model, where we conceive of functions as tools which can answer structured questions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/our-approach.png&quot; alt=&quot;Our approach&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WMF’s mission is to unlock knowledge and help all people share in it, freely. The Abstract Wikipedia team believes that functions can play a key role in unlocking knowledge, and sees Wikifunctions as a crucial player in moving all of us towards this mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a source of power to know how to write and use functions. It gives the person the power of knowledge creation. Our objective when designing the function creation experience was to make it as friendly, intuitive, and simple as possible so that more people can have access to this power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-design-principles&quot;&gt;Our design principles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conceptual simplicity: Given the complex nature of this project, our team aims to radically simplify the concepts involved so that we might be inclusive of all people, especially those who are less familiar with functions, code, natural language processing, or lexicographic knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intuitive interface: We want to build a system with a shallow onramp, one that anyone can figure out and engage with in meaningful ways. We wish for there to be little gap between a newcomer’s existing knowledge (i.e. current knowledge) and the knowledge they need to operate the product (i.e. target knowledge). Our interface will provide community members with an uninterrupted experience, where they are well-supported to complete tasks with relative ease and confidence.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multilingual: In a world where all people can share in the sum of all knowledge, it is critical that Wikimedia products are designed as multilingual interfaces and experiences. From the beginning, the Abstract Wikipedia team will prioritize designing for and testing in the native languages of our community-members. Our objective is to move at the speed of trust with all populations, but especially with small Wikis and underrepresented groups.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Balance: We wish to acknowledge that many of our community members will be veterans of Wikipedia, Wikidata, or any of the movement’s other projects. Many of them will be highly-skilled at navigating technical interfaces and desire customizability similar to Wikipedia or other open source projects. The challenge before us is prioritizing the needs of non-programmers and those with little-to-no coding experience while keeping in mind the expectations of veterans. This will require flexibility and openness in our designs, and filtering design decisions through multiple lenses in order to ensure that we are not locked into any one particular user experience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-have-implemented-these-principles-by-doing-the-following&quot;&gt;We have implemented these principles by doing the following:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Intentionally minimizing the use of technical jargon and providing a glossary of terms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Providing tooltips and informative microcopy on every interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focused attention on information hierarchy so as not to overwhelm users with information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User testing with nontechnical people and iterating to meet their needs and expectations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User testing with technical people to ensure we are not causing irritation or creating unnecessary roadblocks to their progress
-Multilingual design and usability testing (testing is in the planning process)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-use-wikifunctions&quot;&gt;How to use Wikifunctions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-a-function&quot;&gt;Creating a function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say we wanted to create a function that determined if two words rhymed. The “two words” are two inputs of type &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/String_(computer_science)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;string&lt;/a&gt;, and the output is a single “yes or no”, which is a type &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boolean_data_type&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Boolean&lt;/a&gt;. To create a function that could do this, we would need to tell the system, “Hey this function &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;accepts two inputs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, both have to be &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;strings&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, and the function’s output will be a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Boolean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This process is known as “defining” the function, and it is the first step in creating a function.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team believes that the UI and UX for defining a function must be as inclusive as possible because, technically, anyone can do it. It requires no coding or composition writing. Defining a function can be thought of as a request: &lt;em&gt;“Hey I want a function that does X”&lt;/em&gt; translates to &lt;em&gt;“the function accepts this input, returns this output”&lt;/em&gt;. We also provide a way to add documentation so that the user can further explain what they’re looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-challenge-1-the-function-editor&quot;&gt;Design challenge 1: The function editor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We initially planned to design a “function editor” that provided an end-to-end experience, meaning users could define, implement, and test in one environment. Since we were designing for &lt;strong&gt;technical and nontechnical people&lt;/strong&gt;, we hypothesized that unifying the experience would:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplify the concept of what a function needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide a contextual experience which would be helpful for nontechnical users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep related tasks together&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow more senior editors to move in and out of the process as they pleased&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not slow down the technical audience from using the editor as they wanted, while providing guardrails for nontechnical users&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early drafts and variations of an end-to-end function editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/early-draft01.png&quot; alt=&quot;Early draft 1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/early-draft02.png&quot; alt=&quot;Early draft 2&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/early-draft03.png&quot; alt=&quot;Early draft 3&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UX was inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/tags/miro&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/figma&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Figma&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wd-query-builder.toolforge.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Wikidata query builder&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://dribbble.com/tags/typeform&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Typeform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pivoting –&lt;/strong&gt; we tested these mockups with technical non-Wikimedians and Wikimedians, and the results were overwhelmingly positive. However, as our developers were building this design, &lt;strong&gt;we realized that the underlying design of the system was incompatible with this approach.&lt;/strong&gt; Function definitions, implementations, and tests are all separate objects in Wikifunctions, and each object can refer to other objects within it, such as data types (e.g. strings, Booleans, or other functions). &lt;strong&gt;Due to the complexity allowed for each object, we decided it’s best to keep each creation experience separate.&lt;/strong&gt; Objects also have their own pages, so any object you create automatically publishes as a Page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today the function editor is a place only for defining the function, in other words part one of creating a function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/creating-function.png&quot; alt=&quot;Creating a function&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/creating-function-steps.png&quot; alt=&quot;Steps in creating a function&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function editor as it currently exists today&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/function-editor.png&quot; alt=&quot;function editor&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;design-challenge-2-a-function-page&quot;&gt;Design challenge 2: A function page&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you publish a function that you’ve defined, it is saved and published as a function page. &lt;strong&gt;This is the page where all parts of a function live.&lt;/strong&gt; We framed this page as an entry point for the community to learn about, use, and/or edit a function. The goal of this page is to help people progressively edit a function or simply engage with one. The challenge of this page, and a Wikifunctions motif, is that the page must appeal to both non-technical and technical people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-short-term-goals-were-to&quot;&gt;Our short term goals were to&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help all users &lt;strong&gt;UNDERSTAND&lt;/strong&gt; the function so that they can edit or use it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENCOURAGE&lt;/strong&gt; users with coding backgrounds to make technical contributions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ENCOURAGE&lt;/strong&gt; users who are not coders to make non-technical contributions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability test a Figma prototype of the product solution with people who have a strong coding background&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-hopes-and-dreams-were-to&quot;&gt;Our hopes and dreams were to&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage everyone that views a function to try using it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support coders who want to make technical contributions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage users who don’t code to make non-technical contributions because functions need names, aliases, translations of the name/input labels, and documentation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;we-aimed-to-avoid&quot;&gt;We aimed to avoid&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Confusing, discouraging, overwhelming, or intimidating non-coders&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unintentionally signaling to non-coders that this isn’t a space for them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Irritating coders by slowing them down or hiding important actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The function page as it currently exists today. A user lands on a function page’s ‘About’ tab and can toggle between ‘About’ and ‘Details’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/function-page.png&quot; alt=&quot;function page&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user can learn more about the technical details of the function on the ‘Details’ tab, such as how many available implementations and verified testers it has, and what the definition is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/function-details.png&quot; alt=&quot;function details&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-involved-with-wikifunctions&quot;&gt;How to get involved with Wikifunctions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Subscribe to our &lt;a href=&quot;https://lists.wikimedia.org/postorius/lists/abstract-wikipedia.lists.wikimedia.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mailing list&lt;/a&gt; to get weekly updates from our product lead Denny Vrandecic. &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Abstract_Wikipedia/Updates&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Read past newsletters on Meta-wiki&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Join our &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.me/Wikifunctions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;Telegram community&lt;/a&gt; or our &lt;a href=&quot;https://kiwiirc.com/nextclient/irc.libera.chat/#wikipedia-abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;IRC channel&lt;/a&gt; (mirrored) for in-depth conversations on Wikifunctions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow us on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Wikifunctions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; for team and product updates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email me (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:avardhana@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;avardhana@wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;) if you’re interested in product testing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thank you to Nicolas Ayoub, Amin Al Hazwani, Sudhanshu Gautam, Genoveva Galarza Heredero, David Martin, Nick Wilson, and Denny Vrandečić for their contributions!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Wikifunctions will be a collaboratively edited multilingual library of functions.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/header.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikifunctions/header.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Talk is Cheap; it shouldn’t also be hard.</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/02/08/talk-is-cheap.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talk is Cheap; it shouldn’t also be hard." /><published>2022-02-08T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-08T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/02/08/talk-is-cheap</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/02/08/talk-is-cheap.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://jessklein.is/&quot;&gt;Jess Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;prologue&quot;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the discussion page about Nellie Bly’s article, communication isn’t the easiest in normal circumstances. You have to hunt for, and then decipher, little clues scattered around the page to initiate a conversation, and then navigate a confusing interface with seemingly-arcane glyphs to orient yourself in the conversation, all while trying to write what you actually came to discuss. A few months back, I wanted to add a photo of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Nellie_Bly_-_The_Girl_Puzzle.jpg?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Girl Puzzle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, a monument which is located on Roosevelt Island, New York that memorializes Nellie Bly. I think that this image will show how revered she still is for her journalistic work and, since there are very few images of her, it is a nice representation of her likeness. I walk to the monument on the north edge of this island situated within the center of Manhattan, take a photo and prepare to post it on &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; so that it can be linked and posted on the Wikipedia article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where I got stuck. Am I allowed to post this? Are there copyright issues? I visited the discussion page on the English Wikipedia and tried to start a new topic. It’s not easy, but ultimately I realized that I needed to click the “add new section” tab in the interface and ask about inserting the image into the article. After some conversation I wrote &lt;em&gt;“I can take a photo, but would that make it alright to post it or do I need to get approval from the artist?”&lt;/em&gt; I didn’t know the rules around image rights. I magically got responses from other contributors, but I didn’t even notice that they wrote back to me until a month later when I checked the page. Eventually, I’m guided to a number of different policy pages, and from these I figured out that the best way to get the image up is to get an appropriately licensed photo from the monument’s owners, and then go back to the article to post the image and its associated information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, figuring out the best way to get and include an image on the article was painful, but figuring that out while trying to navigate the obscure conventions for using the discussion interface, now that was excruciating. On-wiki communication has gotten a lot better for me personally over time because I have at my disposal colleagues and long-term contributors who I actually know and can help me to learn. That’s great, but for others it has not gone so well; potential contributors just give up. They just stop trying. By their thousands. The Editing Team set out to make moments like this less painful, so that as a contributor, you can just focus on the point that you are trying to get across and improve the encyclopedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-easier-to-use-tools&quot;&gt;Making easier-to-use tools&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;first installment&lt;/a&gt; in this series, I shared how we in the Editing Team conducted research and collaborated with community members to identify a design strategy for the project. The heart of our strategy involves us diving deeply into the asynchronous collaboration experience. To do this, our approach is to first make it easier for contributors to use the tools and then, when we have confirmed that the tools are useful, follow that up by making it easier for folks to discover them in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We undertook a virtual “listening tour”, where we heard from contributors with a variety of experience levels on Talk Pages share what their interactions there were like. From this, we identified four initial opportunities to improve the Talk Page experience that I will walk you through today. Our hypothesis was that addressing these problems would mean that contributors have a more positive and productive experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-1-theres-no-clear-way-to-engage&quot;&gt;Problem 1: There’s no clear way to engage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you look at this discussion page here, you can see that it’s very challenging to identify what to even click to reply to these discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/edit-link.png&quot; alt=&quot;The way to reply to comments currently is to click an “edit” link.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The way to reply to comments currently is to click an “edit” link.
	&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to click the “edit” button to reply. Not obvious. What you’d expect here is a clear call to action, something that says “reply” on it that you can press and initiate the workflow for writing back to someone in a conversation. So that’s what we did. We made a minimal, non-invasive change, which was to add inline links with a more obvious word: “Reply”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/reply-link.png&quot; alt=&quot;Using words that readers expect to see in discussion spaces such as “reply”  as calls to action can be helpful.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Using words that readers expect to see in discussion spaces such as “reply”  as calls to action can be helpful.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though this one change seems simple, it was hugely technically challenging to implement within the constraints that the Wikipedia software gives us. Previous approaches had been hamstrung, either by making trivial systems that don’t work for all the hundreds of language communities that are already part of the Wikimedia movement, or by trying to replace discussion pages and all the functionalities that our communities have built into them over the decades that Wikimedia has been going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Principal Engineer Ed Sanders puts it, “Existing wikitext talk pages are completely unstructured. That means that all the information is thrown together in what we’ve been calling a wikitext soup. And while humans may be able to parse it out by looking at the structure of the conversation, it’s not easy for the software to do this.” For us to extract useful information from the page we needed to build a new tool which we called the Comment Parser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Comment Parser works by breaking up that flat page into structured data. There are lots of edge cases to consider here: hundreds of timestamp formats, multi-line comments with mixed indentation, strange username links. By rolling this out slowly to different communities we’ve been able to identify more edge cases and improve the accuracy of the parser. It helps us to know where comments start and end so we can add the individual reply links to conversations. It also allows us to insert your reply in the correct place with the correct amount of indentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who had used the Structured Discussions system, a key difference is this implementation approach is that, according to Ed, “all the information is &lt;strong&gt;extracted from the page, and not the tool,&lt;/strong&gt; so we can apply this insight to edits made with the full page editor.” The Editing Team’s Product Manager noted that “a key requirement when we spoke to the community was compatibility with existing workflows, so being agnostic about which editor was used means we can do things like show notifications regardless of what editing interface people are using to trigger them.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-2-the-interface-for-writing-is-confusing&quot;&gt;Problem 2: The interface for writing is confusing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the reply button, you now have a nice entry point into the workflow. That said, actually writing a reply was still confusing for a handful of reasons, including the fact that there’s manual threading, the ability to edit other people’s comments by accident, edit-centric language, and you needed to know the wikitext conventions for signing and dating your posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/sign-name.png&quot; alt=&quot;To sign your name and add a date you need to write four tildas “~~~~”&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;To sign your name and add a date you need to write four tildas “~~~~”&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same problems also applied to starting new topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/new-topics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Having to add basic contact information via wikitext isn’t intuitive to most contributors.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Having to add basic contact information via wikitext isn’t intuitive to most contributors.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We addressed this by making it possible to reply and sign your name automatically. This alone would have made a huge difference, because it’s frankly a real pain to have to write “ ~~~~ “ after every single post. We built upon this moment to reduce the complexity of mentioning another Wikipedian, formatting your response, and identifying your comment in the discussion. Again, we made this change inline and more contextual, so that it just felt like an organic conversation experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For adding new topics we made a similar, more obvious workflow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/new-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;Point, click, type and add:the new design for adding new topics. &quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Point, click, type and add:the new design for adding new topics.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-3-missing-notifications&quot;&gt;Problem 3: Missing Notifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a contributor, you were now in the situation where you could start and reply to topics, but in terms of getting notified if someone replied to you, well you got nothing, unless that person knew to use one of the many user-generated templates to @-mention you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact it was even worse than nothing – you would sometimes get a small amount of notifications based on a  set of rules so confusing that you’d have no idea if the other person is getting notified. So, we fixed this with a series of iterations on notifications. We created topic subscriptions, so you can choose if and how you want to be informed about activity within the conversation that you are in. If you’ve used the Structured Discussions tool, you’ll be familiar with these, but you will now get notifications for normal talk page edits, even if the other contributor isn’t using our tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we validated the effectiveness of that feature, we heard from contributors that there are just some conversations that they want to be automatically added to, so that’s what we’ve been working on recently. We have the technology in place and are still checking with test users to ensure that the tools aren’t over-communicating to contributors in such a way that it feels noisy and unwelcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/subscribe-link.png&quot; alt=&quot;Subscribing you to a particular topic will give you timely updates about discussions that you deem important.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Subscribing you to a particular topic will give you timely updates about discussions that you deem important.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/updates.png&quot; alt=&quot;Updates will be integrated directly into your notifications inbox on wiki, and if email (depending on your preferences).&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Updates will be integrated directly into your notifications inbox on wiki, and if email (depending on your preferences).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problem-4-talk-pages-look-like-articles&quot;&gt;Problem 4: Talk pages look like articles.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In English there’s a metaphorical idiom of “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elephant_in_the_room?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the elephant in the room&lt;/a&gt;,” which means that there’s something very important that needs to be discussed but it’s probably going to be a little awkward to talk about it. For talk pages, that elephant is the fact that article pages look very similar to talk pages, and it confuses people who are new to the concept of a talk page. Headings are the same, the table of contents is the same, and there’s no other indication that this is a place where people can have conversations. This is where we are now. We are beginning to explore ways to make it more obvious what this page is all about by emphasizing elements on the page so that you can easily see what conversations are active, who is talking in them, and how you can get involved in them. This will be addressed in a future release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve heard a lot of positive feedback about these improvements. Here are some nice quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…I like the fact that it’s very stripped down and doesn’t feel data intense… The colors are pleasing to the eye. Simple to navigate interface. Overall, it works the way I’d expect it to.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Usability Test Participant&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I think this is the best new feature since years and finally an approach to simplify discussion pages without breaking the workflow of experienced users. So thank you very much for your effort.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– &lt;strong&gt;User:Hgzh,&lt;/strong&gt; German Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feedback is crucial to the success of these tools. Peter explained that “As a fundamentally social and community-driven project, conversation is a core part of Wikipedia. It is a core practice that shapes Wikipedia’s policies, culture and ultimately, the knowledge that is and is NOT represented within it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want testers and skeptics to try these tools out so that I can refine and if necessary rethink the design proposal. What’s particularly great about having a beta release channel is that it offers an opportunity to get things wrong and then quickly throw up a new proposal for review. Try out the tools yourself by going into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Beta_Features?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beta&lt;/a&gt; or global preferences and turning on Discussions Tools. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_project?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Let us know what you think&lt;/a&gt;, it’s a discussion, afterall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the help of the Roosevelt Island Operating Corporation, I was successfully able to add the image of The Girl Puzzle to &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Nellie_Bly_-_The_Girl_Puzzle.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nellie_Bly?useskin=vector-2022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to: Ed Sanders, Sherry Snyder, Peter Pelberg, James Forrester, Bethany Gerdemann, David Lynch, David Chan, Bartosz Dziewoński, Val Puffet-Michel and Esther Akinloose&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Unless otherwise credited, all images in this post are licensed under CC-BY-SA-4.0.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Improving the user experience of Wikipedia discussion pages.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/talk-is-cheap/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Surfacing and embracing diversity within your team</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/01/10/surfacing-and-embracing-diversity-within-your-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Surfacing and embracing diversity within your team" /><published>2022-01-10T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-10T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/01/10/surfacing-and-embracing-diversity-within-your-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2022/01/10/surfacing-and-embracing-diversity-within-your-team.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://lucyblackwell.medium.com/&quot;&gt;Lucy Blackwell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diverse teams generally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/diversity-and-inclusion/diversity-wins-how-inclusion-matters&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener&quot;&gt;perform better than others&lt;/a&gt;, but what do we mean by diversity and how do we know what diversity exists within our own teams?  Most people consider diversity to be things like gender, sexual orientation, racial or ethnic identity, religion, languages spoken, age, educational background, etc. and ultimately everyone has multiple facets to their identity that make them who they are, but some of these facets are not always visible in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month my colleague and I organised and facilitated our annual three-day virtual offsite, for our global team of 25 designers and researchers. Across the team we span multiple timezones and continents and are a very global team geographically, but we are also an entirely English-language speaking team, grounded in many of the cultural norms of American society, where the Wikimedia Foundations headquarters are based. So we decided to focus the offsite on an overarching theme of ‘communication,’ with a particular focus on understanding a little more about each person’s cultural background and the role communication played in this for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-idea&quot;&gt;The idea&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We surveyed the team to find out what languages everyone spoke, and what each person’s native language was. We discovered that almost half the team had NOT learnt English as their first language. It occurred to me then that if we could actually hear every person in the team, speak about themselves in their native language, we may experience something quite different about each other. What if we hired translators to translate team members speaking in their first language?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to be sure that people were encouraged to open up as much or as little as they felt comfortable doing in this context. We were aware that for some people speaking about themselves in a large group can feel quite intimidating, and different people have different levels of personal information they want to share in a work environment. So I thought that perhaps adding a level of abstraction to the conversation might ease this tension. We decided to ask folks to describe themselves through a set of ‘artifacts’ or ‘objects’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the session we asked each person to spend some time identifying and thinking about some objects in their lives that had significance for them. What did they mean to them personally, and what did they say about who they were? They prepared for the activity by following these guidelines;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify a set of three ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/artifact&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;artifacts&lt;/a&gt;’ (or objects) that show…&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;ol type=&quot;a&quot;&gt;
     &lt;li&gt;Something that represents different aspects of your &lt;strong&gt;personality&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
     &lt;li&gt;Something that represents the &lt;strong&gt;culture(s)&lt;/strong&gt; you most closely associate with.&lt;/li&gt;
     &lt;li&gt;Something that represents the &lt;strong&gt;method of communication&lt;/strong&gt; that makes you feel most alive.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take photos or download images of your artifacts and add them to a shared slide deck.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare to talk for 2 minutes about your artifacts and why you chose them, in your native language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;activity&quot;&gt;Activity&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hired seven translators to join the online event and translate the talks, sentence-by-sentence, from Hindi, Cantonese, German, French, Italian, Russian and Spanish back into English for the team. As the activity flowed I could see the faces of the team lit up with intrigue and curiosity as they discovered a whole new side to their teammates. As one person later said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hearing my colleagues speak in their native language was like meeting new people.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were highly creative in how they interpreted the activity and chose fascinating objects to describe themselves. For example, one person showed a picture of a digital watch to describe their personality whilst another showed a tent hung between two trees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/surfacing-embracing-diversity/watch-tent.png&quot; alt=&quot;Digital watch to describe their personality whilst another showed a tent hung between two trees.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people chose very similar objects to describe their culture, often when they in fact came from quite different backgrounds. For example, a couple of people chose stones and objects from nature, whilst two showed pictures of their bikes, and two others shared bottles of olive oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/surfacing-embracing-diversity/nature-objects.png&quot; alt=&quot;Stones and objects from nature, whilst two showed pictures of their bikes, and two others shared bottles of olive oil.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people chose music as the method of communication that makes them feel most alive.  Perhaps we should have a team playlist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learnings&quot;&gt;Learnings&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of translating the talks wasn’t easy, given the fact that many of the people in the team actually spoke better English than some of the professional translators we had hired. This meant that when a few of the translations appeared not to be entirely accurate, some of the people doing their talks, felt the need to briefly re-explain what had been said in English.  As one of the participants said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Listening to translators on the first day, especially when it was evident there was missed or incorrect interpretation. It really highlighted the invisible communication issues we face as designers and researchers working on a multilingual product with people from around the world, and the importance of reviewing text, written, speech, and visual communications as there is so much room for (mis)interpretation.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole process was very interesting to observe and felt like as much part of the experience as the talking was. As the challenges of speaking and translating different languages became evident throughout the exercise, one participant observed,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Hearing fellow team members presenting in their native languages was a lovely moment that made me appreciate what a global team we have and also full of admiration of how so many people communicate so eloquently in English when it’s their second language.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was something about this experience that allowed us all to connect on a different level. One person said to me that no-one had ever asked them to speak their native language at work before. By seeing the different facets of each other and starting to form new types of connections, we began to see how our different views and perspectives actually bring us together and make us stronger as a team. And in turn, this will lay the foundations for being able to work on more complex problems together and ultimately build even better products. As one of my colleagues so beautifully put it;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“All the moments of hearing my multi-cultural team speaking in different languages was such a beautiful sound and an aural reminder of our diversity.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve shared this story today in the hopes that it may inspire others to run a similar activity in their own teams. If you do, please share your experience, we would love to hear about it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">An activity to speak your native language.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/surfacing-embracing-diversity/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/surfacing-embracing-diversity/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Wiki Communications and Mentorship Ecosystems</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Wiki Communications and Mentorship Ecosystems" /><published>2021-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:dchen@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;Daisy Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Growth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Editing_team&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Editing&lt;/a&gt; teams were respectively making plans and progress on Newcomer features and Talk Pages in recent quarters, the teams were curious about where and how wiki users are communicating with one another, and how mentorship manifests within the communication ecosystem. As a first step in this process, &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Product Design Strategy&lt;/a&gt; completed an initial round of research with a participant cohort of primarily affiliate group members, Foundation staff, and other long-time volunteers to illuminate the communications/mentorship ecosystem and identify areas of potential future study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-we-wanted-to-learn&quot;&gt;What we wanted to learn&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Growth and Editing teams wanted to keep the research and discovery process open-ended, they both had some goals in mind for their respective teams’ work. The Growth team hoped the research outcomes would inform the mentorship and collaboration opportunities being tested in the Newcomer program initiatives. The Editing team wanted to understand use cases, benefits and impacts of various communication channels being utilized and how that might feed their work on Talk Pages and New Discussion Tool. Both teams felt this research would impact ongoing work and future plans around communication features/support and mentorship/collaboration opportunities, and we jointly created a couple grounding sets of research questions to that end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;communications&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the various communication tools used by different communities to have these discussions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What types of work are done on these channels?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do community members communicate besides on wiki (ie., besides Talk pages, Village Pump, etc) across different language wikis?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the motivations for using on and/vs off wiki channels? What are the benefits and tradeoffs of each?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are these tools used instead/as well, and what are their efficacies as effective/positive communication tools?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mentorship&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is mentorship defined? What does it look like on the ground?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What factors influence mentorship motivation? How can users be encouraged to mentor others, and see their impacts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How has/does communicating with other contributors affect newcomers’ understanding of Wikipedia as a community of people working together and their connection to it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the efficacy of the off wiki channels specifically in attracting and fostering new contributors?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can productivity tools that promote collaborative editing/communication/tracking, potentially integrated on wiki, also affect mentorship effectiveness?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-research-participants-and-process&quot;&gt;Our research participants and process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To contain the scope of this initial round of research (with a second round envisioned to expand our research into other segments), we decided to keep our first participant cohort to those who have had more experience working in the various wiki communities. These folks worked in a wide range of wiki-related roles both in various organizational and volunteer capacities; the goal was to hear about their communications and mentorship experiences at length. Interviews were conducted in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few target languages/regions came into focus after reviewing geographic areas of interest the Growth and Editing teams pinpointed and where ongoing recruitment of potential participants seemed to be proving most fruitful. Ultimately, the participants were determined after evaluating languages, regions and genders represented, and diversity of roles within the wiki movement, among other factors. The languages/regions in particular were determined when we were able to establish a ‘critical mass’ of sorts, where we spoke with enough participants in each to start observing patterns in their responses and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concluded the project with 18 participant interviews across 4 primary geographic regions. Each of the interviews were semi-structured, with a prepared discussion guide to provide a basic framework for the exploration while allowing for the participants to freely express both directly and tangentially relevant experiences and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;post__table&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Primary Location&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Country(/ies)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Language(s)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;# participants&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;South America&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brazil, Portugal*&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Portuguese&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Southeast Asia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Indonesia, Philippines, UK*&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Bahasa indonesian, Nias, Bikol, Tagalog, Pangasinan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;South Asia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;India&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Hindi, Bengali, Punjabi, many other Indic languages&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;MENA/T&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Turkey, Jordan, Morocco&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Turkish, Arabic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;post__small&quot;&gt;* grouped with South America due to work on same language wiki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-did-we-discover-in-these-conversations&quot;&gt;What did we discover in these conversations?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;communications-1&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devices and access.&lt;/strong&gt; Even given the characteristics of this cohort (juggling a wide range of audiences and channels both on and off wiki, high volume of communication, high relative access to digital resources), none of the participants indicated that they used their mobile as a primary device for their communications. Many indicated that laptop/desktop access made many tasks easier to accomplish as some on wiki tasks are not yet mobile-friendly or lack appropriate functionality (in addition to inherent screen and device limitations). Laptop/desktop use was also convenient as many classically mobile tasks (texting, sending images, calling) are increasingly available from a desktop version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/devices-used.png&quot; alt=&quot;Devices used to communicate for wiki work.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is the direct finding from this cohort, many from the cohort broached the issue that many existing and potential users, especially from the Southeast Asia and South Asia (India) regions, are facing device/digital resource limitations. They may face inconsistent internet infrastructure/access, limited/expensive data, and limited access to devices (no/shared access to a singular mobile device, paid entry to internet cafes with device access). To address this, optimizing our mobile experience in terms of accessibility/reliability and additional features while limiting bandwidth used where possible is key to reaching this audience further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On or off wiki communication?&lt;/strong&gt; This cohort bucked expectations again here; even though their wiki communication is heavily due to a wiki-related role/obligation and their individual capacities as volunteers, they tended to do most of the communication off the wikis. Those who utilized on-wiki communications more often indicated they did so primarily for posting official updates and documenting conversations and outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants often strategically move conversations between on and off wiki channels, most specifically moving discussions to off wiki channels and then returning on wiki to document the outcomes and decisions from those discussions. The reasons given for moving discussions off wiki included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expediency (having the discussions was logistically quicker to do on off wiki channels)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wider reach/more inclusive (more people quantitatively in general and more were engaged in the conversation than on on wiki alternative arenas)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more availability for private or otherwise sensitive conversation as needed (everything on wiki is visible for anyone)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, many participants empathetically said that being on wiki is a “disadvantage” and an “inequality”, especially for newer users. The learning curve overall, the invisibility of accessing help and finding communication channels, understanding the norms of communication in each wiki community – all contribute to why the cohort as a rule tends to try and meet newer users where they are, which is most often an off wiki channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/where-participants-communicate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Where do our participants communicate.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;“The more time you put in off wiki, the less time you need to defend it on meta&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;On and off wiki channels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Below you’ll find examples of channels being used both on and off wiki, an approximated scorecard of the pros and cons of the two main options, and basic flow charts of the most common use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main takeaways:&lt;/strong&gt; off wiki channels score higher on all listed criteria for our participants and provide the most helpful outcomes when it comes to the tasks and connections they need to make in their wiki work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Off wiki channels as a whole offer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quicker responses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more casual feel that can lead to more sincere communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;option for private conversations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better accessibility and mobile/UI-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Where does off wiki communication fall short as a category? The regard for on wiki legitimacy remains; it is a must for announcements, recording of important decisions and outcomes, and everything posted is public, documentable, and referenceable. The transparency and accountability on off wiki options are not as clear cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/on-off-wiki-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;On and off wiki chart.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/on-off-wiki-graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;On and off wiki graph.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do participants think could improve communication?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The participant suggestions below are charted on a continuum of simple to execute (left/green) to the more complex (right/red). They are also sorted into suggestions that could impact communications more directly (top half) and changes that have more of an indirect impact (bottom half).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/improve-communication.png&quot; alt=&quot;Improving Communication.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mentorship-1&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentorship as described by many participants is transactional and editing-centric. A few members of this cohort, while tackling task-based, editing-focused questions, have also emphasized and lived the importance of additional facets of a mentorship relationship. Moving forward, we should support a tailored approach to mentorship, one that spans the transactional/functional (knowing what/how to do) to the institutional/inspirational (understanding of the movement, engagement borne of interest, belonging and recognition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We need longevity and sustainability from good mentorship. Do we want 1 person who edits 100 times or get 10 people to do 10 edits each?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this framework, we’ll also need to address our users’ varying needs. While facilitating “human-powered” means of mentorship interactions, we should also take care to supplement learning with technical solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/examples-of-mentorship.png&quot; alt=&quot;Examples of mentorship and their impacts and frequencies, charted.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Examples of mentorship and their impacts and frequencies, charted&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answering questions about editing tasks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This could be on a one-off or an ongoing basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Specific, targeted Commons photo advice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A participant brought up this example; this individual received specific, actionable feedback on why photos were not being approved and what it would take for a photo to be approved and even featured&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating and disseminating tutorial type materials.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holding editing-focused workshops and events.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching about the movement and opportunities;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. Making mentees aware of the larger movement, organizational structures, and providing advice on mentees’ draft proposals for their own projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Involving people in a hobby-based campaign;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. The Wiki Loves Butterfly initiative involved finding butterfly enthusiasts on social media, motivating them to join wiki, having 1:1 chats with them and meeting in person, showing them commons/uploading/categories and other editing-related tasks, doing/coordinating fieldwork and taking butterfly lifecycle photos, holding photo workshops etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Constant communication and community;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. Wiki World Heritage User Group holds workshops and is in constant communication/collaboration. Its engagement plan also includes a skills assessment in which members and newcomers are asked about knowledge on various topics/tools, and where they’d like to learn more. This is used to match people up, invite them to specific topic/tool discussions or sessions, or set up curriculum for planned workshops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do participants think could improve mentorship?&lt;/strong&gt; There is some overlap in suggested solutions here, particularly the suggestion for forum-style, centralized discussion interface and for better documentation of various resources and FAQs. Participant suggestions range from simpler (left/green) to the more complex (right/red).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/improve-mentorship.png&quot; alt=&quot;Improving Mentorship.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communications-2&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some relatively quicker fixes we can make to make our on wiki communications options more accessible, intuitive, and visible to our community, especially on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a higher level, our Product teams need to weigh the pros and cons of making on wiki the go-to place for all wiki-related communications or acknowledge that on wiki is simply not meant to be that type of all-encompassing destination and support off wiki channels where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other general considerations include device and data limitations many of our community members and potential users face, differing cultural tendencies (e.g, security, privacy, building trust) and community-specific norms around policing, attitudes towards newcomers/anonymous users, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentorship-2&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communications ecosystem’s visibility and functionality are the foundation for mentorship to develop, flourish, and sustain. The functionality aspect should increasingly address not just transactional forms of newcomer help/training (documentation pages, FAQs, bots) but also allow for organic growth of mentorship connections and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mentorship connections do not arise organically, such as in structured newcomer programs, the resulting mentorship interactions tend to remain more transactional in nature and lack an inspirational element that fosters feelings of ownership and more naturally creates opportunities for challenge/reward dynamics to arise. These are factors that tend to establish additional connections, interests, and overall a more prolonged, lasting relationship with the mentor and the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-planning-collaboration-evaluation&quot;&gt;What’s next? Planning, collaboration, evaluation.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prioritization and planning current/future roadmap.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The findings inform ways (and focus areas) in which our Growth team’s Newcomer homepage/tasks initiatives can be improved and supplemented with concurrent efforts. The team can focus on ideation, prioritization, and planning for features in upcoming quarters/annual plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scoping &amp;amp; cross-team collaboration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Other Foundation teams may find this work relevant in their focus areas, both in and outside of Product. There are opportunities for the Growth team to coordinate with other teams (e.g. Editing, Android &amp;amp; iOS, Trust &amp;amp; Safety) on issues impacting communications and mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analytics/UX evaluations of Newcomer initiatives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; As Growth team’s newcomer initiatives are rolled out on test wikis and perhaps additional wikis, evaluating on an iterative basis how the features are or aren’t meeting the needs of a variety of user personas, using both analytics and usability testing/interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-strategic-research&quot;&gt;Further strategic research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Additional relevant personas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The next phase of this research should include newcomers and mentees (specific subset of newcomers) more specifically. This will provide first-hand knowledge of how those first experiencing communications related to the wikis become aware of the variety of channels, their expectations and the realities, and their experiences of the newcomer initiatives and interactions with experienced users (in a general or specifically mentorship-type capacity) in these spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Specific communities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Further research should include communities with limited device and connectivity and also cultural concerns whereby trust is primarily built through in-person connections to see what support possibilities exist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Where and how wiki users are communicating with one another, and how mentorship manifests within the communication ecosystem.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wikipedia and Apps: A Love Story</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wikipedia and Apps: A Love Story" /><published>2021-12-08T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-08T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schoenbaechler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/carolynlimadeo&quot;&gt;Carolyn Li-Madeo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/baba786&quot;&gt;Sudhanshu Gautam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Volker_E&quot;&gt;Volker E.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing for mobile apps presents unique challenges and opportunities compared to traditional websites. Mobile apps run natively on a device and have access to system resources that are harder to access within a web based architecture. Key characteristics of apps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apps are designed to fit with the rest of the operating system. When an app fits in with the rest of the OS, it not only looks and feels more at home, it lowers the users learning curve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A deep integration with the OS comes with benefits right out of the box, e.g. accessibility, performance, integration with voice assistants or &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;home screen widgets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offline capabilities and often reduced data usage: offline capabilities allow users to consume content from anywhere, even when they are not connected to the internet or connectivity is low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wikimedia Foundation’s apps are an essential piece to meet our &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#this-is-for-everyone&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“this is for everyone” design principle&lt;/a&gt;. Wikimedia apps are designed with the philosophy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile-first.abookapart.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;mobile first&lt;/a&gt; in mind. One of the core principles of mobile first is to embrace the constraints of a mobile environment and with it, prioritize essential information, as there’s simply not enough room for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited connectivity of people in certain areas of the world inspires us to create products that are performant and light on data. When building new features for people using mobile apps, we strive for excellency in user experience and aim to break down complex existing flows and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on Android&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on iOS&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on iOS&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on kaiOS&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on kaiOS&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are here to create mobile first experiences&lt;/strong&gt; and are not trying to replace existing desktop or community tools. Through the apps, we aim to meet potential users where they are. We are interested in understanding and addressing barriers of those that have been historically left behind, while not compromising the integrity of the workflows of our long-time users on other platforms. Making participation fit naturally the mobile first lives we live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are a place to experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; Due to development speed, richer capabilities and unique needs of our user base, we are able to experiment. It is on the apps where we think the future of mobile editing will be discovered. Notably, the apps are where we piloted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Suggested_edits#Welcome_to_Suggested_edits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;micro contributions&lt;/a&gt;, our most successful editing intervention to this date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are a forcing function to make our technologies future proof.&lt;/strong&gt; To provide an example: Right now Wikipedia’s web experience works as a website only and cannot be exported to new mediums. By building on the apps, we create technology that is platform independent and enables next generation experiences. Whether these use artificial intelligence, augmented reality or future technology that is changing our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theming&quot;&gt;Theming&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;Theming.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the introduction, iOS and Android both have platform specific guidelines. When building apps for the global Wikimedia movement, our goal is to create native experiences for the specific platform. When designing for mobile apps, guidelines for the platform sit at the top of the hierarchy. Throughout Wikimedia’s product suite, we follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Design’s visual design principles&lt;/a&gt; when providing solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a seamless and familiar experience within Wikimedia’s products and services, we apply theming that is based on Wikimedia’s visual style guidelines. Theming allows us to customize the app’s look and feel, to better represent our product’s brand. Theming is reflected in the entire UI, including individual components, like buttons. Here’s an example of applying Material Theming in the Wikipedia Android app:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/material-button.png&quot; alt=&quot;A standard Material button&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A standard Material button (&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/design/material-theming/overview.html#material-theming&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;image source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/material-wikipedia-button.png&quot; alt=&quot;A themed button in the Wikipedia Android app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A themed button in the Wikipedia Android app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ios-keyboard-messages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chat toolbar in iOS messaging&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Chat toolbar in iOS messaging (&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/resources/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;image source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ios-keyboard-wikipedia.png&quot; alt=&quot;Editing toolbar in the Wikipedia iOS app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Editing toolbar in the Wikipedia iOS app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/kaios-without-theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;KaiOS standard progress indicator.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;KaiOS standard progress indicator.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/kaios-with-theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;We used a planet animation progress indicator to show the vast amount of knowledge available on Wikipedia.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;We used a planet animation progress indicator to show the vast amount of knowledge available on Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design style guide’s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_colors.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;color palette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is also used in the apps. Since both the Android and iOS Wikipedia app is available in four different reading themes (Light, Sepia, Dark and Black), they are using an enhanced color palette for an optimal reading experience. Check out more details about the color palette for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_theme_guidelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2017/12/04/ios-app-dark-theme/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt; here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/google-fonts.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Wikipedia Android app uses on Material Icons&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Wikipedia Android app uses on &lt;a href=&quot;https://fonts.google.com/icons&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Material Icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/sf-symbols.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Wikipedia iOS app uses SF Symbols&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Wikipedia iOS app uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/sf-symbols/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;SF Symbols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As defined in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_typography.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;typography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; section of Wikimedia’s Design Style Guide, the app’s rely on the operating system’s default sans-serif typeface. The app’s mostly use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_icons.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provided by the platform, e.g. from &lt;a href=&quot;hhttps://material.io/design/iconography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Material&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/sf-symbols/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Apple Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, except for icons that are associated with established Wikimedia products or services (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/OOUI_icons#userTalk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia’s icon for user talk pages&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;principles&quot;&gt;Principles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus&quot;&gt;Focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The “Picture of the day” on Wikipedia for Android puts content from Wikimedia Commons in the spotlight.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The “Picture of the day” on Wikipedia for Android puts content from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; in the spotlight.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia for iOS focuses on the essential in its homescreen widgets.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia for iOS focuses on the essential in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://uxdesign.cc/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios-fcf8548ae449&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;homescreen widgets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content. &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How clear is the goal? Based on Wikimedia Design’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#content-first&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“content first” principle&lt;/a&gt;, we aim to &lt;strong&gt;design apps that are easy to understand and focus on the essential&lt;/strong&gt;. When designing, content comes first, control comes second. On mobile, screen real estate is limited, places of usage are unforeseeable and the user’s focus is reduced. We strive to reduce information density while not neglecting an interface’s functional essence. Guiding questions like: What is the essence of this feature? What is the purpose of this particular screen? How much information can be deprioritized (or left out) to convey a UI’s purpose? Clarity stands for designing user interfaces with clear call to actions, generous use of white space, accessible contrast and hierarchy when designing with type or icons. Writing concise and suitable multilingual UI copy supports in reaching their goals more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orientation&quot;&gt;Orientation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The &apos;More&apos; navigation for Wikipedia on Android is designed to maintain the user’s context.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The &apos;More&apos; navigation for Wikipedia on Android is designed to maintain the user’s context.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;The off-canvas menu on Wikipedia for iOS is one tap away from anywhere in the app.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The off-canvas menu on Wikipedia for iOS is one tap away from anywhere in the app.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content. &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The &apos;Options&apos; menu lets readers easily navigate an article. It avoids unnecessary key presses.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where am I? &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#design-for-consistency&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Design for consistency and orientation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are key aspects to help users navigate through an interface in a mobile app. We put explicit effort in communicating where users are and where they can go. Spatial awareness in a digital product helps users in achieving goals more directly. This is exemplified by using a consistent navigation, usage of depth and the application of motion. Deliberate usage of animation and transitions help users navigate an interface. Visual layers and realistic motion convey hierarchy, emotion and understanding when using a device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;emotion&quot;&gt;Emotion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/emotion-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The &apos;Thanks&apos; interaction in the Wikipedia for Android app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The &apos;Thanks&apos; interaction in the Wikipedia for Android app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/emotion-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;The onboarding experience in the Wikipedia for iOS app educates and resonates emotionally&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The onboarding experience in the Wikipedia for iOS app educates and resonates emotionally&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the design feel on an emotional level? An often forgotten and invisible theme but yet one of the most impactful: emotional design. Along the lines of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#trustworthy-yet-joyful&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;”trustworthy yet joyful” design principle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;we believe that preserving the human touch and showing ourselves with our values in our work is essential&lt;/strong&gt;. Especially on a device that is as personal as your mobile phone. Instead of creating one more cheap and fast mass feature, we follow a philosophy that has been paved by artists, designers, and architects of the arts and crafts movement. After all, we design for humans and strive to create humane and emotional experiences. Through design, we can see and connect with other human beings. To design experiences that are emotional, we consider understanding the needs of the people we are designing for, as the core mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ergonomics&quot;&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of ergonomically supporting users in the Wikipedia for Android app.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Example of ergonomically supporting users in the Wikipedia for Android app.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Relevant actions are located near the bottom of the screen for easy access.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Relevant actions are located near the bottom of the screen for easy access.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;For non-touch interfaces, placement of key actions (e.g. search, read, edit) is important. We linked key actions with commonly used phone keys to make them easy to perform&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;For non-touch interfaces, placement of key actions (e.g. search, read, edit) is important. We linked key actions with commonly used phone keys to make them easy to perform&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the design feel in my hand? &lt;strong&gt;Ergonomics, posture, context, and the tactile nature of touch have implications on how users interact with a design&lt;/strong&gt;. Our design principle “this is for everyone” is part of our core mission and designing for touch is different than designing for a keyboard, mouse or trackpad. When designing for apps, we embrace principles of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_manipulation_interface&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;direct manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, an interaction model where effect are immediately visible on the screen to the user. Designing for a touch device goes beyond enlarging buttons for bigger fingers. We deeply consider placement and positioning of elements to achieve an ergonomic user experience while being aware of different device usage types. And, as voice is considered as the most natural machine-human input method available, we make sure the interface reflects it. We design experiences that provide ergonomics on smartphones, tablets and hybrid laptop/touch devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get involved&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia iOS, Android and kaiOS apps are each designed and developed by a specific team to that platform. If you’re interested in learning more about the apps or if you want to get involved, please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Apps on mediawiki.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;android&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_FAQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android team page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/apps-android-wikipedia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=US&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6UkFHYqVsbc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android App promo video on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_theme_guidelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Android color guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Google Material Design Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ios&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS team page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for iOS on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/wikipedia/id324715238&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for iOS in the App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T169148&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;iOS color guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/overview/themes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Apple Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kaios&quot;&gt;kaiOS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikipedia_for_KaiOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for KaiOS project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-kaios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for kaiOS on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimedia.github.io/wikipedia-kaios/sim.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia KaiOS app simulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.kaiostech.com/docs/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;KaiOS documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Jazmin Tanner &amp;amp; Josh Minor for their contributions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Designing for mobile apps presents unique challenges and opportunities compared to traditional websites. Mobile apps run natively on a device and have access to system resources that are harder to access within a web based architecture.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrolling Unregistered Editors on Wikipedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrolling Unregistered Editors on Wikipedia" /><published>2021-11-17T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://prtksxna.com/&quot;&gt;Prateek Saxena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On most Wikipedias, you don’t need an account to make an edit. While there are benefits to making an account — such as a single place to see all communications, or a place to store articles that you’re interested in — there is no requirement to make one. This reduced barrier to entry means that people around the world can contribute to our projects — whether it’s a small typo fix or a new article — without ever having to make an account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it also means that it’s easier to vandalize and make destructive edits to our projects. To counter this, our editors and administrators patrol edits made by registered and unregistered editors alike. These watchful editors are also known as &lt;em&gt;patrollers&lt;/em&gt;. To keep out bad faith edits from our projects, patrollers need to have an understanding of who is making the edits. In the case of unregistered editors though, the information that they rely on most is their &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IP_address&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IP address&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An IP address is a unique address that is given to any device that is connected to a network like the Internet. When an unregistered user makes an edit, the change isn’t attributed to their name, but their device’s IP address instead. An IP address is like a home address, it cannot reveal your identity but one can deduce a lot about you by knowing where you live. So, what might seem to some as an &lt;em&gt;anonymous&lt;/em&gt; way of editing actually reveals more about them than a simple pseudonym would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrollers copy these IP addresses into external &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WHOIS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WHOIS tools&lt;/a&gt; to understand where the editor is coming from. These tools tell them information about where the editor might be and how they’re connecting to the Internet. To reduce the extra step of copy-pasting addresses, and providing a single place to get IP  information, the Anti-Harassment Tools team started work on an &lt;em&gt;IPInfo&lt;/em&gt; tool within Wikipedia. This tool would give our patrollers the needed information right where they need it — when analyzing an unregistered user’s contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designing-ip-info&quot;&gt;Designing IP Info&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-research&quot;&gt;Initial Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we wanted to get a better understanding of the patrolling process and specifically how IP addresses are used while evaluating edits. To do this we conducted interviews with editors who often patrol our projects and asked them to show and talk us through their process. This gave us an overview of the different ways patrollers go about keeping our projects vandalism free. After a few rounds of feedback from design, research, engineers and Trust &amp;amp; Safety folks we had the following task model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-risk-vs-usefulness-matrix-wikimedia-design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_lmUSH8s=/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; for a full view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand now that IP patrolling usually starts from RecentChanges, an editor’s Watchlist, or from a page that the editor knows gets vandalized often. When looking at the edits of such a page the patroller first looks for clear red flags like edit flooding (lots of minor edits in a short amount of time), no edit summary, large deletions etc. They then look for more specific on-wiki information like if the IP has a talk page, if it has ever been blocked, and its global and local contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this initial fact-finding, patrollers decide if an IP is worth looking into further. If it is, they use external tools to find more information about the IP. They’re looking for details  like — location, proxy usage and organization that the IP might be linked to. This process is not completely accurate since different databases have different information on the same IP. Oftentimes, based on the location of the IP and the location of the tool the editors are using, the information provided might vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, based on the information collected, patrollers decide which action would be most appropriate. Again, this decision takes into account various factors like the policies of that wiki, the scale of the collateral damage caused by a range block, consistency in editing patterns, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mock-ups&quot;&gt;Mock-ups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrollers need on-wiki information about the IP before they decide to investigate it, so, we decided to add a popup that shows block and contribution information. The popup would be accessible by clicking an information icon next to the IP address on pages like RecentChanges, Watchlist and History.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-popup-wikimedia-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;The IP Info popup that’ll be accessible from pages like RecentChanges that patrollers monitor for edits.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The IP Info popup that’ll be accessible from pages like RecentChanges that patrollers monitor for edits.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the patroller decides to dig deeper into an IP address by going to their Contributions page, they’ll be able to see a collapsible box that shows more IP related information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-box-wikimedia-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;The IP Info box shown on the Contributions page gives detailed information to the patrollers.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The IP Info box shown on the Contributions page gives detailed information to the patrollers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing these mocks internally brought up three questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much information is useful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who should have access to this information?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should some patrollers have access to partial bits of information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;balancing-needs&quot;&gt;Balancing needs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our projects have a wide variety of contributors and vary in socio-demography, accessibility and motivations. These and other factors were captured in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Knowledge_Gaps_Index/Taxonomy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Knowledge Gap Taxonomy&lt;/a&gt; research, which not only looked at the gaps in Wikipedia’s content but the gaps in the contributors as well. In turn, we reframed our design questions as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How might we make sure that revealing IP information doesn’t put our most marginalized contributors at risk?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How might we ensure that access to information and tools doesn’t become a barrier to contributions for our least technically skilled contributors?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While IP information needs to be available to all, we wanted to make sure that it doesn’t put anyone at risk and it isn’t so technical &amp;amp; overwhelming that it becomes meaningless to most patrollers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;team-workshop&quot;&gt;Team Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-Harassment Tools team and the Trust &amp;amp; Safety teams came together for a small workshop to discuss these items. We acknowledged that we want both non-technical and technical users to have easy access to IP information. We also acknowledged that we can’t put our unregistered editors at risk especially because some of the IP information, like location and organization, can potentially help in identifying a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our discussions around accessibility for patrollers we noted questions and concerns around information overload, accuracy of information and false confidence in IP data. We also considered if having IP information more readily available might lead to its misuse. The following clusters began to form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we make sure that people understand the data they’re looking at, and understand its accuracy too?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal information:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we make sure that information is accessible to those who need it, without putting unregistered editors at risk?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agency:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we inform unregistered editors of the data they are leaving traces of and show them ways to protect it (create an account)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After brainstorming on the questions we started to organize our thoughts in the following manner — we need to balance the concerns of ease of use for patrollers and risk to unregistered editors. To do this we plotted the different pieces of IP information on a graph with Risk on the Y axis and Usefulness to patrolling on the X axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-task-model-wikimedia-design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Plotting the different pieces of IP information based on Risk (to editor) and Usefulness (to patroller). See &lt;a href=&quot;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_lmUSH8s=/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; for a full view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise was based on the learnings from research as well as the team’s experience. Two clear clusters appeared, the high risk one mostly containing information that could reveal an editor’s location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, we are planning to show a limited set of information to most users and give access to more sensitive information to only our most trusted users — Administrators and CheckUsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;gathering-feedback&quot;&gt;Gathering feedback&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-input&quot;&gt;Community input&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing our findings with the community led to some interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Talk:IP_Editing:_Privacy_Enhancement_and_Abuse_Mitigation/IP_Info_feature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conversations and feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Some common themes were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increasing or deepening the scope of a particular piece of information. IP Information is complex and having more context and data usually helps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding more data sources to get a wider picture of the IP information. This would also help in figuring out if the data being shown is reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specific points about IP ranges and IPv6 addresses and how to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;usability-tests&quot;&gt;Usability tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also able to do some usability tests with Patrollers in the community. Overall, the feature was well-received and they liked that they won’t have to rely on external tools in the future. We were given some specific feedback around:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The distribution of information between the popup and the box. Some information is more helpful in the popup to decide whether or not to investigate further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having more guidance on how to use this information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Showing some of this information on Diff pages so that editors have access to it while comparing revisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation is currently in the works and we’ll be rolling it out to wikis slowly as a BetaFeature, incorporating improvements based on usability testing. We’ll also be implementing feedback mechanisms in the tool so that we can learn more about how people are using the tool. To follow the updates on this feature and join the discussion, check out the project’s page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/IP_Editing:_Privacy_Enhancement_and_Abuse_Mitigation/IP_Info_feature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia’s Meta-Wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover image by Tristan J. Wilson. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:TJDW_Stonehenge_20111107.tif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed.en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CC0 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Carolyn Li-Madeo, Rita Ho, Aida Ramirez, Jessica Klein &amp;amp; Niharika Kohli for your feedback and editing help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Balancing the needs of patrollers and unregistered editors on the wikis</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/stonehenge.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/stonehenge.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>