<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-09T02:54:09+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wikimedia Design Blog</title><subtitle>Make sharing of knowledge easy and joyful, for everyone.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Design Strategy Website Launch</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design Strategy Website Launch" /><published>2020-12-08T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-08T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/12/08/design-strategy-website-launch.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;Making design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Design Strategy Team&lt;/strong&gt; is pleased to announce the launch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/&quot;&gt;a new site&lt;/a&gt; which makes years of design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community. While most of this work is specific to the user experience of content creators and readers of Wikipedia on our various platforms, some of these studies are more generally applicable - for example, work related to &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/online-social-behavior.html&quot;&gt;online social behavior&lt;/a&gt; and use and training of &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/machine-augmentation.html&quot;&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt; applications may be of more general interest. If you find this to be the case &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:desresadmin@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;we’d love to hear from you&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/team.html&quot;&gt;Design Strategy&lt;/a&gt; supports product development at the Foundation by providing the qualitative and quantitative research that enables Product teams to make informed and inspired decisions. From explanations of what people do and want, to evaluations of what they experience, to experiments with new and emerging technologies, the research team answers the most urgent and impactful questions that stand in the way of achieving our vision of &lt;strong&gt;a world in which every single human being can freely share in the sum of all knowledge&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Making design research more accessible to our wiki project contributors and to the global design community</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wiki-pins.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wiki-pins.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Transparency by Design</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Transparency by Design" /><published>2020-11-16T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-16T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/11/16/transparency-by-design.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;How making page issues more visible on Wikipedia mobile helps foster trust and participation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Alex Hollender&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today when reading a Wikipedia article on your phone you might see a notice at the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-transparency-by-design.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia notices on mobile&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be more familiar with how they look on a computer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-arizona-state-university.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia notices on desktop&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We call these notices &lt;em&gt;page issues&lt;/em&gt;, and 2018 we made them more visible on the mobile website. This blog post is about page issues: what they are, how they increase transparency, and our design process around increasing their visibility on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are page issues?&lt;/strong&gt; — Page issues let you know that there are unresolved issues with the article you’re reading. These issues range from the article not having sufficient citations, to the article not being neutral in its viewpoints, to the article having spelling and grammar mistakes. They usually do a good job of summarizing the issue, and then invite you to help fix it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-four-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of four different notices&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Page issues are manually added to articles by Wikipedia editors, and on English Wikipedia there are around 340 different kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Page issues are inherently revealing. They are perhaps uncommonly honest. And they seem so unmistakably Wikipedian; I can’t quite imagine Facebook or Airbnb putting up such a notice — &lt;em&gt;this isn’t quite right, help us fix it&lt;/em&gt; — on one of their pages. So before proceeding to some of the specifics about how we increased their visibility on mobile I want to think aloud about some general questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you’re trying to establish a website as a trustworthy source of information, why would you tell your audience that a certain page is sub-par, or lacking in some way? Could this bit of transparency actually help build trust with them? Maybe it shows them that you’re more interested in finding the knowledge together than you are as being perceived as already having the knowledge on your own. At the same time imagine you’re trying to facilitate collaboration between a huge number of volunteer encyclopedia editors. Might it be helpful if they could leave little notes and clues for each other on articles, helping direct attention and effort? Is there some bigger purpose page issues serve, beyond just giving people a heads up? Or in other words, are page issues symbolic of some larger truth or value within the Wikipedia community?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust through transparency&lt;/strong&gt; — In 2007 David Weinberger gave a talk about his book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2695&quot;&gt;Everything is Miscellaneous&lt;/a&gt;” at Google. Forty-five minutes in he comments on page issues on Wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&quot;https://cdn.embedly.com/widgets/media.html?src=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fembed%2FWHeta_YZ0oE%3Fstart%3D2695%26feature%3Doembed%26start%3D2695&amp;amp;display_name=YouTube&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.youtube.com%2Fwatch%3Fv%3DWHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;image=https%3A%2F%2Fi.ytimg.com%2Fvi%2FWHeta_YZ0oE%2Fhqdefault.jpg&amp;amp;key=a19fcc184b9711e1b4764040d3dc5c07&amp;amp;type=text%2Fhtml&amp;amp;schema=youtube&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; title=&quot;Everything is Miscellaneous&quot; class=&quot;ev hy ew hz w&quot; scrolling=&quot;auto&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WHeta_YZ0oE&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;amp;t=2695&quot;&gt;Everything is Miscellaneous&lt;/a&gt;” David Weinberger, 2007&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“Wikipedia is very happy to have these notices stuck in…they encourage you to put up these notices saying this article isn’t good enough, don’t fully believe this article. And because of that we know that Wikipedia is on our side. [Wikipedia] becomes more credible because they’re willing to admit their lack of credibility, their lack of authority. It’s not trying to convince us that it’s the world’s greatest authority, it’s trying to help us know.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His observation rang true to me. To reiterate and expand: because Wikipedia is more interested in having correct information than it is in being perceived as authoritative, it is able to be transparent about issues and shortcomings. Wikipedia is happy to show its hand, happy to let you know when something might be wrong, because it empowers you as a reader to be alert and discerning. This transparency also reminds readers that every Wikipedia page is a work in progress, and hopefully encourages them to get involved (which is where collaboration comes in).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Participation through (intimate?) transparency&lt;/strong&gt; — Imagine that you walked into a coffee shop, sat down at a table, and on the table there was a note saying: &lt;em&gt;Hello, we’re not entirely sure if this table works well here. How does it feel to you? Do you have enough space/privacy from the next table over? Do you think it’s annoying when people slide by to get to the bathroom? Please feel free to let us know your thoughts, or move the table elsewhere. This experiment will end next week.&lt;/em&gt; What would you think or do? How would that information and invitation change your relationship to that coffee shop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking of this note as a display of transparency. The coffee shop is being transparent about what it knows (or doesn’t know), and how it makes decisions. But the note is different from publishing an annual report, or some other kind of formal transparency statement. Instead it’s intimate, direct, and timely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve seen during my time as a Wikipedia community member, this kind of transparency, often in the form of handwritten signs (so to speak), guiding people’s attention towards what’s going on, what needs additional work, is a fundamental aspect of how and why people choose to participate. This transparency seems to inspire a spirit of independent participation. Which is to say that you’re empowered to fix things on your own, while also being supported by others if you need help. So I wonder if page issues function in this way; showing newcomers where help is needed and inviting them to jump in? They also seem to help experienced editors stay organized and direct energy appropriately. And in their humble, handwritten way maybe they reinforce the spirit of intimacy that is so necessary for a community-run project. Again these are questions, hopes, guesses; not a proven understanding of what’s happening. Now onto the more concrete stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increasing the visibility of page issues on mobile&lt;/strong&gt; — Wikipedia community participation isn’t limited to writing and editing Wikipedia articles. The community is also involved with the planning, design, and development of Wikipedia as a website/piece of software. Just as anyone can edit, anyone can also voice their opinion about the functionality or look of the website and propose improvements, which is how page issues on mobile came to be prioritized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September, 2016 Wikipedian McGeddon posted on Village Pump (a Wikipedia discussion board):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-mobile-page-issues.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;(left) McGeddon’s post, (right) how page issues looked on mobile in 2016&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;“If an article is up for [deletion] and flagged as a possible hoax with insufficient medical sourcing, any reader visiting that article on a computer is greeted by three large red and orange boxes at the top of the page, one with a cautionary stop sign… If a reader instead visits the same hoax medical article on their phone… they just get two tiny grey words “Page issues” under the article title…”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while the fix wasn’t made until 2018, all in all it was a great demonstration of Wikipedia at its best — a community member voiced their question/opinion, a discussion began, and eventually an improvement to the site was made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design challenge&lt;/strong&gt; — A page issue is like the note on the coffee table. They come in all shapes and sizes. They are not particularly standardized. Look at some of them, how much personality they have:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Collage of different types of notices&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our goal seemed relatively straightforward: show these page issues to people reading Wikipedia on their phones to make them aware of any known issues with the article they were reading. However if you try the straightforward thing, and just show them on the mobile website, you get this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-language-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Notices in different languages&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They don’t just automatically get smaller and look good on the mobile website. And to make matters worse, articles that have one issue often have others, so you get these boxes stacked on top of each other which pushes the article text way down the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how should they look on the mobile website? What’s the right balance between making them noticeable and them overwhelming the article? Keep in mind there aren’t just the 340 different page issues on English Wikipedia to test out, there are hundreds of others across various Wikipedia projects (e.g. French, Arabic, Thai, etc.). Some contain one image, some contain two or three. Many contain links to pages that also aren’t formatted to look good on a phone. We understood that we needed to come up with a systematic way of creating smaller, “mobile-friendly”, versions. To begin we identified that mostly all of them have: an icon/image, a text description, and a color. So it wasn’t too difficult to imagine the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-mobile-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Notices on mobile&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the type of visual consistency we were hoping to achieve. Since page issues aren’t standardized from a code/template perspective the technical challenge to isolate the relevant pieces (image, description, color/severity) was significant, though I won’t be getting into that here. A few other questions naturally occurred as well (partly curiosity, partly things that we thought might inform our design process):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;What are all the different page issues that exist?&lt;/em&gt; There was no straightforward way to get this information. &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.wikimedia.org/~jdrewniak/page_issues_inventory/en.index.html&quot;&gt;This gallery&lt;/a&gt; shows page issues for some of the largest Wikipedias (thanks to Jan, an engineer on our team, who did this audit programmatically).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Is there any structure or categorization to their level of importance?&lt;/em&gt; Thankfully yes, most page issues have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&quot;&gt;type&lt;/a&gt; parameter, which is a consistent way of programmatically knowing how severe a given issue is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How common are the different types of page issues? Are there a small few that show up a disproportionately large percentage of the time?&lt;/em&gt; There was no straightforward way to get this information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While we loved the personality of the custom icons/images many of them weren’t able to effectively communicate at a small size. We also hoped that using a simple visual system consistently across all page issues would make it easier for readers to quickly understand their importance. So we adopted the scale from English, using simplified versions of the icons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-types.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Template:Ambox#type&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design criteria were also relatively simple: 1) people should see them (without them being distracting), 2) people should see the severe ones most easily, 3) the notices shouldn’t clash with other notices that appear at the top of the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-prominence.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Sketches showing different prominence of notices&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Initial sketches&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-other-notices.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of page issues on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Other notices and elements that appear at the top of some articles&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also questioned whether the placement on desktop — at the top of the article — was appropriate for mobile. We considered whether it might make sense to put important notices above the article, and less important ones perhaps below the first section. But we opted for simplicity here, and decided they should all just go in the same place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;alignwide&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notice-severity.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Position of notice according to severity&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that point we felt like our solution was good enough to start testing. The main thing we wanted to learn from our test was: do people notice the page issues, and interact with them, more than before? This was the goal for the project and was admittedly a pretty low bar (considering that previously they were very understated). We also wondered about the secondary effects of exposure to page issues. Would exposing page issues on mobile affect trust and/or participation in Wikipedia, even for people reading from their phones? Here is what we found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the main goal we succeeded: the new page issues were noticed and interacted with significantly more than the old ones. And furthermore, more severe issues are noticed and interacted with significantly more than less severe ones&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On the secondary goals the outcome was less clear: we saw no immediate increase in editing as a result of the updated treatment, and we didn’t end up measuring trust.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can view the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Reading/Web/Projects/Mobile_Page_Issues/AB_tests?useskinversion=2&quot;&gt;full report here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
And so we labor on, continually trying to bring transparency to every corner of our experience. The more people know about the information they are reading the better equipped they are to be discerning. We believe that transparency has value in and of itself, and this project was about furthering that value. We didn’t see an immediate increase in editing, but we also know that editing from a mobile is more difficult to begin with, and we are still continuing to learn about the different mentalities different people have when reading Wikipedia on their mobile device versus on a computer. In other words, we’re far from finished yet. But now people reading on their phones will see the notices, and over time more of them may be inspired to participate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  Alex Hollender is a lead designer at the Wikimedia Foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How making page issues more visible on Wikipedia mobile helps foster trust and participation</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/tbd-notices.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Organizing a remote offsite for a global team</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Organizing a remote offsite for a global team" /><published>2020-10-15T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-15T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/10/15/organizing-remote-offsite-global-team.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Lucy Blackwell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started working at the Wikimedia Foundation as a Senior Design Manager in March of this year, just after the lockdown began in London, UK where I’m based. Whilst this design team has always been a fully remote team, they annually get together in person for a few days somewhere in the world for a team offsite, but this year, all travel was cancelled! This blog post will share a bit about how I set up a remote offsite for the team and what I learnt in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-defining-the-goals&quot;&gt;1. Defining the goals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a difficult time to organise an event with the coronavirus adding a new layer of stress to peoples lives. I realised we were going to have think carefully about what we wanted to achieve with this offsite, and what capacity people were likely to have to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gathering-information&quot;&gt;Gathering information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began like any designer, researching and reading everything I could find about how others had run remote off sites previously, and then started discussions on the topic with the other members of our design leadership group. Our director, Margeigh Novotny, suggested the theme of ‘cooperation’ and how we work together, which we all felt was very appropriate. We also agreed that it should have a light-hearted and fun tone, as a lot of the year so far had been quite difficult for many people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also keen to understand what the team wanted to get out of the offsite, so I created a survey to gather their opinions including questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the single most important thing you personally want to achieve by attending the team offsite?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What inspires you most about how our team works together?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you think could be improved in how our team works together?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communicating-goals&quot;&gt;Communicating goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After collating all the responses, some pretty clear topics emerged – team bonding, learning from each other, small group collaboration and fun. There were a few other topics from one or two individuals which we decided not to do this time. I presented the survey results back to the team in our team meeting (about a month before the actual offsite) and explained the decisions we’d made for what to include and what to leave out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By defining our goals early on, this helped set the expectations for the team, and created a blueprint for me to build the agenda and activities upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-planning-logistics-and-tools&quot;&gt;2. Planning, logistics and tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design and research team is truly global, with a total of 17 designers and researchers located all over the world from Bangalore to San Francisco.  We span a 12 hour time difference, so when it’s 8am in San Francisco, its 8pm in Bangalore. This requires some careful planning to make things run smoothly if we all want to connect at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scheduling&quot;&gt;Scheduling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a group we use google calendar to schedule our meetings which displays events in the right time zone for each individual, and allows users to define their working hours so we can identify the overlaps which is very important for remote teams. However, sometimes folks haven’t got around to putting in holidays they’re planning in the future, so I decided to use a tool called &lt;a href=&quot;https://doodle.com/en/&quot;&gt;doodle poll&lt;/a&gt; to determine what dates everyone was free and lock down the week for the offsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;screen-time&quot;&gt;Screen time&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the dates agreed upon, I needed to work out which activities would require all 17 team members together on a screen, versus which ones would be more effective in smaller groups, pairs, or even alone. I learnt some great tips from Jasmin Tanner in &lt;a href=&quot;https://jazmintanner.com/blog/2020/5/15/a-wikimedia-foundation-product-team-had-productive-virtual-strategy-sessions-and-meaningful-team-bonding-in-a-remote-environment-across-various-time-zones&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; where she talked about limiting the amount of time on screen with others to just 4 hours a day, broken into sessions of 2 hours maximum at a time.  I realized that I needed to be more aware of the cognitive load during screen time to be sure people didn’t disengage. This is quite different to the physical off sites I’ve run previously, where I often included a walk or a physical activity to break up the sessions throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we decided we would connect as a whole team for one 2 hour session every day, we chose the only reasonable time slot we could find, which was 8am - 10am in SF, which made it 8pm - 10pm in India.   In addition to these all team sessions, I then arranged some smaller break out sessions between individuals and people located in similar time zones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-schedule.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Schedule for the offsite activities day by day&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tools&quot;&gt;Tools&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I started to gather ideas, I realised there were a number of activities that needed to happen before the group sessions, so I was going to need somewhere to provide instructions for what everyone needed to do, by when, and with whom.  I decided to use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.notion.io/&quot;&gt;Notion&lt;/a&gt;, which is a lovely user-friendly in-browser tool for creating and sharing content that the team had been starting to experiment with. I prepared instructions for each day in Notion and then shared each page with the team the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-notion.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of prep page in Notion&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team are already very active &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.slack.com/&quot;&gt;slack&lt;/a&gt; users so I created a special channel in Slack for all our offsite banter and chatting.  For some of the activities I also created some collaborative boards in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.miro.com/&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; which is an online whiteboard used primarily for visual collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborators&quot;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always useful to seek help from within the team when running an event as it brings a fresh perspective to the planning, lightens the load on the organizer and also engages some of the team in the process.  For this offsite, our research manager, Ana Chang and I brainstormed all the plans together, then she took over the activities for the last day with a couple of other designers, Carolyn Li-Madeo and Jess Klein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon hearing that the theme of the offsite was ‘cooperation’, Bethany Gerdemann in the research team offered to share her facilitation skills, as it turned out she is a qualified Coop developer and has lots of experience helping groups establish workplace democracy.  We discussed the best way to weave her contribution into the event. In the end she made a great presentation and video for us all to watch about cooperation, which was very well received by the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people didn’t have much time with busy day jobs in their product teams and I think for many it felt challenging enough just to clear their calendar for 3 days to attend the event.  But a couple of the designers offered to organize an icebreaker, which is a short 10 minute warm up session which normally happens at the start of a meeting. These were really effective and didn’t take too much prep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the organizer, I was responsible for the bulk of the prep work, but I felt part of my role was to bring as many people into the process as I could, so it would really feel like a team effort, after all the offsite was for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;swag&quot;&gt;Swag&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like at every great event, everyone enjoys a little swag, and fabulously our team director, Margeigh Novotny, had already made some really awesome pins for everybody and ordered a small hardback book titled ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/why-we-cooperate&quot;&gt;Why We Cooperate&lt;/a&gt;’  by Michael Tomasello, so we got these sent off to everyone in advance. It’s a bit like sending out the VIP passes before the festival, it creates a little excitement and anticipation for the event and makes people feel special!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-swag.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikimedia swag: 'The last best place on the internet' pins&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-team-building-activities&quot;&gt;2. Team building activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed to think of activities that could be done anywhere in the world, keeping in mind that some people were in lockdown and unable to leave their homes. We started by breaking the overarching themes into sub-themes for each day:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals - learn about our teammates and their personality traits&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Groups - explore ways to work together in small groups and learn facilitation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 3:&lt;/strong&gt; Diversity - develop an appreciation for the diverse backgrounds in the team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did all sorts of different activities including a series of games around our personality profiles and making a set of guidelines for collaboration following a small group activity. Here’s a bit more detail about just a few of the activities that went pretty well…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ice-breakers&quot;&gt;Ice Breakers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice breakers are short warm up activities to get everyone in the spirit of interacting together. Carolyn Li-Madeo ran a super fun activity which some may know as ‘A big wind blows’.  It went as follows…. we were all on the call with our cameras on, Carolyn asked us all to turn our cameras off, whilst she kept hers on.  She then said ‘Who had avocado for lunch?’ and anyone who did have avocado for lunch had to turn their camera back on. The last person to turn their camera on, who had had avocado is now ‘it’ and the process starts again….  So again each round started with everyone turning their camera off except the person whose turn it was…. they then asked a new question like… ‘Do you wear glasses?’  and the game continued… People really loved this activity as it allowed us to see how similar and different we all are, it was very interactive without any effort, and many people said they could have kept playing it for ages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;diy-user-manuals&quot;&gt;DIY User Manuals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve read that lots of teams have had success getting to know each other better by writing their own personal user manuals and sharing them with each other. In case you’re not familiar with the term, basically a user manual explains things like how you like to communicate best, if you’re a morning person, how you manage challenges etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I searched through different options, it occurred to me that many of the examples I’d found felt a bit heavy and serious and we had agreed to keep things light, so in a highly unscientific manner, I decided to create my own list of 10 questions. I pulled from all sorts of different sources like a game from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theschooloflife.com/shop/100-questions-work-edition/&quot;&gt;School of Life&lt;/a&gt; where they ask the question ‘Which of your talents is the world in danger of overlooking?’, and a question from my favourite radio BBC show &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b006qnmr&quot;&gt;Desert Island Discs&lt;/a&gt;,  which asks ‘If you were going to be cast away to a mythical desert island and could only take one thing with you, what would you take and why?’  I even remembered an application form I’d filled out the year before in order to attend the &lt;a href=&quot;https://thedolectures.com/&quot;&gt;Do Lectures&lt;/a&gt; in Wales, where they’d asked me ‘If you had a life motto, what would it be?’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared the list of 10 questions with the team and asked everyone to fill them in on their own. Then I paired each person up with another person in the team who they said they’d spent less time with, and  encouraged them to spend an hour sharing their user manuals with each other and diving deeper into their answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our collaborative all team session each person had to describe the person they’d chatted with, to the whole group. There were some amazing facts and stories revealed which allowed us all to gather some new perspectives on our team mates, such as the fact that one person said the living thing they feel most similar to is ‘slime mold’ - that same person also said that their ‘secret talent that the world might overlook’ was that they were an awesome parallel parker!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;photo-walks&quot;&gt;Photo Walks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the last day some of the other folks in the team came up with the idea of asking everyone to take a walk around their neighbourhood to take photos. They wanted to encourage people to pause and really look at their physical environment objectively as a designer. The team were asked to take photos of; things that inspired them, things that they thought were good or poor design, and examples of inclusive or exclusive design. (If folks couldn’t leave their homes due to a lockdown, we suggested they found inspiration inside their home instead, or even using photos they’d taken before, or found relevant images online.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We then asked everyone to upload their photos to a shared collaborative Miro board, adding their initials and any notes they wanted to add about the images. Later that day, in our full team group session we took turns sharing some of the stories behind the images we’d taken with each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-board.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of our miro board from our photo walks.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a fully remote team we usually only see each other on Google meet and have no idea about the context our colleagues live in that inspire and inform their lives. This exercise really helped build an appreciation of the diverse environments and perspectives within our group, from Indian streets to European towns, to the American countryside, each image full of cultural nuance with its own unique story to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-reflection-and-learnings&quot;&gt;4. Reflection and learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the offsite was a great success, we had a good time and got to know each other better and achieved many of the goals we’d set out to do. But there’s always more to learn, so here’s a few of my reflections after the event…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-keeping&quot;&gt;Time keeping&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectively running a series of sessions requires quite a bit of preparation, not least a clear minute-by-minute plan of how long everything should take, especially when many folks in the team are working unusual hours already in order to attend the session. One of the key roles of the facilitator is to keep everything on track time-wise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first day, I had planned a series of activities and games based upon the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.16personalities.com/&quot;&gt;personality type profiles&lt;/a&gt; we’d identified for ourselves before that session. However, each activity had taken longer than I’d expected, so this meant the whole session ran over by about 20 minutes.  About a third of the group had to leave promptly at the agreed end time and it meant a few folks didn’t get to share back their user manuals with the team.  The beauty of being online was that we could easily record the remaining part of the session, so those who had to leave could watch it later, but it meant they had more to do to catchup and be ready for the next day.  The following day I did manage to keep the group session to time, but learning how to nail this every time is something I will be focusing on in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-anti-climax&quot;&gt;The anti-climax&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of our offsite I felt exhausted and a bit deflated, I found this to be a rather strange reaction, given that I thought things had generally gone fairly well. But it occurred to me as I cycled home that night on my own, that it was kind of sad not to be able to go and have a drink or a cup of tea with some folks from the team that evening, or even over lunch the next day. I wanted to hear their banter about the event, to know what they thought!  This is also contrary to my previous experiences, as in my last role I’d never been overly keen on the after work get togethers and usually would have to skip them anyway due to childcare responsibilities, but suddenly not having this option made me feel a bit empty. So how might we celebrate and wrap projects better in a remote world, without spending the evening on a screen again?  I think I will be exploring this question on the next remote offsite, but do let me know if you have any ideas…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback-survey&quot;&gt;Feedback survey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of there being no wrap party to speak of, I did ask the team to fill in a short survey after the offsite to reflect upon what they’d learnt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more positive results was that the team unanimously gave top marks for ‘having fun’. Before I began planning the event, I had not been totally sure if this was possible online, besides you can’t really tell people to ‘Have fun!’, you can only create an environment for it to happen and hope it does. It turns out the fact it was online really made no difference to this. I also think agreeing this as an objective early on helped us collectively create an experience that we all enjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the loveliest piece of feedback that came from multiple people in the survey, was that they really enjoyed the one-on-one sessions they’d had in the offsite with people in the team that they don’t normally work with. This is of course the easiest thing to organise of everything. It is so often the simplest things in life that take us the farthest. Perhaps the simple act of finding time to get to know our teammates, and making this a pattern in our busy routines, might be the thing that really helps us bond as a team overtime.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Whilst this design team has always been a fully remote team, they annually get together in person for a few days somewhere in the world for a team offsite, but this year, all travel was cancelled!</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-design-web.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/offsite-design-web.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wikipedia is getting a new look for the first time in 10 years. Here’s why.</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/09/23/wikipedia-is-getting-a-new-look.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wikipedia is getting a new look for the first time in 10 years. Here’s why." /><published>2020-09-23T07:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-23T07:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/09/23/wikipedia-is-getting-a-new-look</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/09/23/wikipedia-is-getting-a-new-look.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By Olga Vasileva&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia has remained a critical and widely-used resource for knowledge across the world for the past two decades.  Over this time, the site has expanded significantly to contain unparalleled amounts of reliable and thorough information, including 53 million articles across over 300 languages. While Wikipedia’s content has grown rapidly, our interface has not kept pace.  We’re proud that our website is more direct, simple, and advertisement-free than the rest of the internet.  Yet, the design of desktop Wikipedia and other &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/our-work/wikimedia-projects/&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Foundation projects&lt;/a&gt; have not seen any substantive changes for the past 10 years, leaving certain elements of the site’s navigation feeling clunky and overwhelming to readers and editors whose main purpose is to create, learn, and curate content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The desktop design is particularly important to new users who have come to the internet for the first time over the last decade.  To these users, much of the wide range of functionality on the site can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Reading/Web/Desktop_Improvements/Hureo_User_Research_Report&quot;&gt;feel overwhelming&lt;/a&gt; and difficult to understand.  In order to welcome them to our projects and entice them to come back, we need to provide not only excellent content and an experience that is engaging and easy to use, but also an experience that is on-par with their perceptions of a modern, trustworthy, and welcoming site. At the same time, we wish to keep the core of our identity and evolve in a way such that the final product indisputably looks and feels like a Wikimedia project. We want to create an experience that feels similar to our long-time users, yet straightforward and intuitive for new folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is with these goals in mind that the Wikimedia Foundation began a multi-year project to improve Wikipedia’s desktop. Since May 2019, we have been working to strengthen the Wikipedia desktop interface — focusing on bringing our content to the forefront, and making the site easier to navigate. Our goal is to create a more welcoming experience for all who come to our projects, regardless of background or level of experience with Wikimedia sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forthcoming changes to the desktop include a reconfigured logo, collapsible sidebar, table of contents, and more! You can see the full list of new features on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Reading/Web/Desktop_Improvements#What_features_will_be_added&quot;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt;. These changes will happen incrementally over a long period of time, to allow for ample user testing and feedback. If all goes to plan, these improvements will be the default on all wikis by the end of 2021, timed with Wikipedia’s 20th birthday celebrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, we deployed the first of many changes to a set of early adopter projects: Basque Wikipedia, Farsi Wikipedia, French Wikipedia, Hebrew Wikipedia, French Wiktionary, and Portuguese Wikiversity. Users with accounts on other projects can also view these changes by selecting the latest version of the Vector skin within their user preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first change, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Special:MyLanguage/Reading/Web/Desktop_Improvements/Features/Collapsible_sidebar&quot;&gt;a collapsible sidebar&lt;/a&gt;, allows users to collapse the lengthy menu found on the left side of each page. This change helps improve usability and focus by allowing people to concentrate on the content itself, whether reading or editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our second change introduces a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Special:MyLanguage/Reading/Web/Desktop_Improvements/Features/Limiting_content_width&quot;&gt;maximum line width&lt;/a&gt; to our content on pages where reading is the focus, such as article pages and discussion pages. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.tc-library.org/Edlab/eye-tracking%20article.pdf&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that limiting the width can lead to better retention of the content itself, as well as a decrease in eye strain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the first of many changes in a long and complex process. There will be bugs, adjustments, and iterations. We welcome anyone curious about our changes to try them out and give us feedback. Have additional questions about the desktop improvement project? See answers to some of our most frequently asked questions on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Reading/Web/Desktop_Improvements/Frequently_asked_questions&quot;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  Olga Vasileva, Lead Product Manager at the Wikimedia foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The desktop design is particularly important to new users who have come to the internet for the first time over the last decade.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-under-construction.gif" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-under-construction.gif" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Democratizing Modern UI Design From The Bottom Up</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/08/26/democratizing-modern-ui-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Democratizing Modern UI Design From The Bottom Up" /><published>2020-08-26T17:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T17:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/08/26/democratizing-modern-ui-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/08/26/democratizing-modern-ui-design.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-a-m-goldberg-900961b2/&quot;&gt;David A. M. Goldberg&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://pauginer.com/&quot;&gt;Pau Giner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia Foundation [WMF] has established the ambitious vision of making the sum of the world’s knowledge accessible to all the world’s people, by 2030. This vision necessitates a focus on scale: how to scale up content production, globally, and how to scale up access to this content in emerging contexts. Behind this need to scale is a critical design challenge: how to ensure a useful, usable and consistent reading experience while enabling rapid growth. To meet this challenge, WMF’s small but mighty Product Design team has developed a set of best practices and guidelines for product development across all of the Wikimedia Projects. This Design Style Guide, the first of its kind since the founding of Wikipedia in 2001, is both a means of maintaining consistency while scaling, and also a key contribution that product design is uniquely positioned to make –  in the Free Knowledge Movement, and across Wikimedia projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/consistency.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Wikipedia mobile in different writing systems&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The Wikipedia experience adapts to different contexts such as different mobile platforms and languages, while keeping the experience consistent. In the example, Android, web and iOS experiences are shown on top and part of the icon system at the bottom.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus of  the Guide is to translate the core values of the Foundation into a language of design: this is for everyone, content has priority, usability guides aesthetics, and there is joy to be discovered in honest, open, and free communication. These values are not just idealizations, they are concretely expressed in the Design Team’s comprehensive suite of user interface visual elements (available for &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/resources.html&quot;&gt;download&lt;/a&gt; and use) and Wikimedia’s evolving  &lt;a href=&quot;https://doc.wikimedia.org/oojs-ui/master/demos/?page=widgets&amp;amp;theme=wikimediaui&amp;amp;direction=ltr&amp;amp;platform=desktop&quot;&gt;Object Oriented User Interface&lt;/a&gt; (OOUI) JavaScript library that puts them to use. Taken together, the WMF Design Team has created a spectrum of engagement that includes those who want to see better-looking, more accessible and consistent design across Wikimedia projects (or the Web at large!), and folks who want to work with free design and interface-development resources. Even if you have never reflected on the effort that goes into creating the best user experiences—we take icons and UI components for granted until they break or confuse us—it is worth casually exploring these resources to get a sense of exactly how the Web can and should work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope and reach of the Design Team’s web UX conventions puts the Foundation in the company of other free, standards-based, and open source initiatives like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://designsystem.digital.gov/design-principles/&quot;&gt;United States Web Design System&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://getuikit.com/docs/introduction&quot;&gt;UIKit&lt;/a&gt; project, and in the same class as influential commercial giants like Apple, Facebook, and Google. However, unlike the design requirements of the governmental public sector, or multinational for-profit corporations, the Design Style is informed by the unique challenges associated with the heterogeneity that exists at all levels of large-scale, global, volunteer-driven projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked Pau Giner, one of the Design Team’s leads, how they negotiated a balance between the technical rigors of modern UX design, its pleasure principles (design is, after all, about a goodness), and inviting the participation of communities who do not take the first two actors for granted. This would include people who are new to working with Wikimedia projects, and designers who have never seen their expertise and insights play a part in pursuing the Foundation’s mission. One cannot design a comprehensive design standard by consensus, via self-organized volunteerism, or in direct response to every individual need. He provided an urban metaphor, contrasting the smaller winding streets of older cities like Barcelona (the utopian), with the regular and presumably more practical grids of Chicago or New York. I believe that part of Giner’s intent was to give a sense of what it would be like to introduce necessarily binding rules into a system that had developed in a largely organic fashion, but his metaphor goes further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/paper-ink.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ink and the Wikipedia wordmark on a paper&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Inspiration for the visual direction of the style guide came from traditional elements to capture knowledge such as paper and ink.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compared to Google’s Material Design, he describes the WMF Design Style Guide and its supporting resources as less “complete.” For now, it lacks Material’s formal guidelines for approaches to media, motion, and visual density for example, but according to Giner’s urban metaphor, a totalizing approach to all possible modalities of design would run counter to the bespoke intricacies developed during the lifetime of a collaborative project like Wikipedia. That said, some of what is considered “charming” about the plans of very old cities is a record of old solutions remaining  in service long after their original problems were solved. This creates some interesting tensions that the Design Team has tried to resolve through an open and flexible approach rather than a fixed set of top-down “universal” standards that demand adherence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giner describes the team’s approach as co-evolutionary in the sense that it works closely with various Wikimedia communities that are already deeply invested, both conceptually and technically, in their tools and approaches to content. Working across a number of time zones and specialties, using hackathons and project management tools, the Design Team has collaborated with Wikimedians like Samantha Nguyen (&lt;a href=&quot;https://brickipedia.fandom.com/wiki/LEGO_Wiki&quot;&gt;Brickipedia&lt;/a&gt;), Nislihan Turan (volunteer on the Android Commons app), and numerous internal and cross-Foundation folks. Their contributions ranged from feedback to specifications design, to coordination and connecting normally separated communities such as designers and developers. Giner has also seen increased usage of the Style Guide among new Wikimedia editors and readers, coming—importantly—from non-English speaking communities all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a Wikimedia project itself, the Style Guide serves as a kind of global ambassador, presenting itself to other communities as a demonstration of its own standards, and offering its own DNA, so to speak, as a solution. Communities with great passion and expertise in their field of knowledge, but varying levels of design and technical literacy, work transparently and collaboratively with Giner and his peers to pose and answer questions. This iterative responds to new questions that are raised, and avoids infinite regression, unilateral appeals to expertise, and the blandness of design-by-committee. The argument for a unified—but not necessarily comprehensive—design is not forced, but developed from the inside out, and guided by a respect for the specificity and diversity in communication that underlies the Foundation’s mission to make all of human knowledge available to everyone, without relying on any given human’s exclusive perspective. The Wikimedia Design Team’s particular alignment with the mission makes it real in that special way that steering wheels, doorknobs, light switches, and traffic signs simultaneously tell us what to do, and how things can be done, in a system where individuals are ultimately responsible for their own actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-a-m-goldberg-900961b2/&quot;&gt;David A. M. Goldberg&lt;/a&gt; is a writer, teacher, cultural critic, whose work focuses on issues of innovative democratic access to computing and communications technologies.
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://pauginer.com/&quot;&gt;Pau Giner&lt;/a&gt; is a Principal User-Experience Designer in the Wikimedia Foundation’s Product Design department and has been leading language projects.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Designing the way millions of users access knowledge requires lots of considerations. The Wikimedia Style guide is an effort to compile good practices to facilitate this task for designers and developers</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/democratizing-modern-ui.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/democratizing-modern-ui.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Content Moderation and Anti-Vandalism Works on Wikipedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/07/30/content-moderation-anti-vandalism-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Content Moderation and Anti-Vandalism Works on Wikipedia" /><published>2020-07-30T17:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-30T17:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/07/30/content-moderation-anti-vandalism-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/07/30/content-moderation-anti-vandalism-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-a-m-goldberg-900961b2/&quot;&gt;David A. M. Goldberg&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/claudiawylo&quot;&gt;Claudia Lo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/margeigh&quot;&gt;Margeigh Novotny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 6 million articles on the English language version of Wikipedia, and 217 million more across the 731 other &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WikiProject&quot;&gt;wikiprojects&lt;/a&gt; worldwide.  These are mind-boggling numbers when considering the scale of human effort it takes to improve and police this much content, let alone monitor their online activities to detect and mitigate harassment. However, the Wikimedia Foundation and the Free Knowledge Movement remain vigilant, and dedicated to cultivating the most democratic practices and confronting some of the most antagonistic elements of Internet culture that Hermosillo&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; recognized and theorized about so long ago: the “black hole”&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of toxicity, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HyperNormalisation&quot;&gt;hypernormalization&lt;/a&gt;, deepfakes and mass sock puppetry&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that define online culture today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then does a free and open volunteer-driven project like Wikipedia manage disinformation? The truth is that there is considerable effort to mitigate user harassment and article vandalism (editing in bad faith or with malicious intent­) on Wikipedia. I spoke to Claudia Lo, design researcher on the Wikimedia Foundation’s Anti-Harassment Tools team, and learned that the Foundation’s commitment to establishing ever-widening circles of inclusive participation makes one-size-fits-all solutions hard to come by (whether they’re policy-driven or technical). What remains consistent however, is the need for active human participation in moderation processes that involve complex technical and ethical challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lo’s background includes practical “in the trenches” experience as a volunteer moderator on Reddit and Discord, and academic media studies research that focused on the tools and technologies that Twitch moderators used during video game tournaments. Unlike these platforms where discourse is transient, and content was relatively unregulated,  Wikipedia’s editorial standards call for objective and citation-driven contributions. Wikipedia deals in truth and factuality over opinion and speculation, so when antagonism and disruption do emerge, the stakes are higher. Though Wikipedia &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Wikipedia_is_not_a_reliable_source&quot;&gt;does not consider itself a reliable source&lt;/a&gt;, it is trustworthy enough to attract those who would exploit privileges that the platform extends to all users in order to sow dissent, attack others, disrupt collaboration, push agendas, execute vendettas, and cultivate uncertainty. Such “bad actors” may see nothing of value in the Foundation’s mission to make all of the world’s knowledge available to all of the world’s people, but they know that a considerable portion of cyberspace’s netizens do, and that third-party search and knowledge base systems are making increasing use of its product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikipedia content is always in-progress or in a state of being edited, so how does one distinguish active trolling, fierce but otherwise healthy partisanship, genuine disputes, and naivete or inexperience? Lo has seen it all: poor writing and incompetently structured pages, frivolous vanity articles, edit wars over celebrity birthdays, and people seeking revenge on their high school alma maters. There are also behind-the-scenes battles and truly ugly behavior on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MediaWiki#Talk_page&quot;&gt;talk pages&lt;/a&gt; behind articles, as well as intense (and possibly state-sponsored) conflicts surrounding polarizing political figures and historical events. Fortunately, the emotional or epistemological aspects of vandalism and harassment activities can be separated from their technical ones, and such behavior leaves patterns in server logs and edit histories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as a denial of service attack on a webserver can be automatically recognized based on the source and frequency of requests, a Wikipedia article that sees a high number of edits in a short period of time, or coming from the same IP address(es), can be flagged as potential vandalism. Because the ability to contribute and edit anonymously keeps barriers to participation low, reducing vandalism by banning accounts or blocking individual or ranges of Internet Protocol (IP) addresses contradicts the core aspects of the Wikimedia philosophy. As Hermosillo warned: “cyberspace is an increasingly efficient tool of surveillance with which people have a voluntary relationship,” so restricting contribution to registered users challenges the WMF commitment to privacy, as does the need to retain usage logs in order to perform systematic analysis of accounts associated with abusive behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For their part, IP blocking tactics are not only surmountable by dedicated bad actors, but they run afoul of broader protocol-related issues such as IP addresses that are assigned dynamically or in blocks. The risk of blanket restrictions preventing access for users that are not identified as bad actors is real. And yet tools that facilitate blocks, track spurious accounts, and initiate bans are the primary  means of thwarting abuse. In typical Wikimedia fashion, the chosen solution does not involve restricting access to these tools—thereby creating a kind of police force—but making them more accessible to the broader community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with moderation technology requires the ability to parse and cross-reference lots of information, to recognize patterns, and pay attention to constantly-shifting details. Such forensic skills are not exclusive to any one group of people, but the complexity of the tools themselves restricts their use to those who are already in the technical and/or cultural position to use them. As a designer, Claudia Lo wants to make these tools easier to use—right now they can involve a headache-inducing combination of spreadsheets and dozens of browser tabs. Put another way, Lo believes that one should not have to be an alpha nerd if one wants to contribute to the community moderation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to hear Lo describe this as a “utilitarian” effort, but as I listened to her describe the straightforward strategies that Twitch moderators used to do their jobs I came to understand that this remains a deeply human challenge. AI may eventually be able to execute some of the Twitch moderators’ heuristics, such as using lists of inappropriate words or phrases in various languages in conjunction with real-time parsing of text streams’ content and points of origin. But Wikipedia’s problems are not reducible to flagging inappropriate language and booting trolls, especially in a political era that has considerable trouble grappling with issues of censorship, and what “free” speech and expression means when one’s identity online is effectively disposable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the impression from Lo that there were no magic bullets to be crafted, but this is far from a concession or a retreat. The Anti-Harassment Team’s approach is consistent with the Foundation’s tendency to work incrementally to gradually improve the system over time, and in cooperation with community volunteers. But in this particular case, applying human-centered design to the problem of moderation tools’ overwhelming complexity will give more people the opportunity to address vandalism and harassment in their respective communities rather than relying exclusively on a highly technical and top down moderation strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; In 1994 Carmen “humdog” Hermosillo wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/kolber/2131643&quot;&gt;pandora’s vox: on community in cyberspace&lt;/a&gt;, a prescient and pioneering critique of online life’s everyday practices. In this  essay she calls cyberspace a “black hole” that, in commodifying our attention spans, “absorbs energy and personality and then re-presents it as spectacle.” Today, such a description could be applied to any online platform whose technical infrastructure and/or community model is descended from the glory days of Web 2.0’s “user-generated content.”&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;A sockpuppet is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_identity&quot;&gt;online identity&lt;/a&gt; used for purposes of deception. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sockpuppet_(Internet)&quot;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Ever wonder how content moderation works on Wikipedia?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/moderation-groups.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/moderation-groups.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How might we… conduct a virtual design sprint in ~3 hours?</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/06/30/hmw-conduct-a-virtual-design-sprint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How might we... conduct a virtual design sprint in ~3 hours?" /><published>2020-06-30T17:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-30T17:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/06/30/hmw-conduct-a-virtual-design-sprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/06/30/hmw-conduct-a-virtual-design-sprint.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@reetssydney&quot;&gt;Rita Ho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being a designer at the Wikimedia Foundation means I am reasonably accustomed to working remotely – both geographically, and in the sense of being the sole designer in a cross-functional team. For the past 2 years I’ve worked in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot;&gt;Growth team&lt;/a&gt;, whose goal is to increase the number of new contributors on wiki projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2019, for a number of reasons (logistics of scheduling 10 people spread all around the world, financial prudence, desire to reduce the carbon footprint of travel), we decided to trial holding our team offsite virtually. At the time it seemed like a novel experiment to try, but in the wake of the COVID-19 pandemic, I have since realized that this might be the new normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our team’s program manager, Jazmin Tanner published a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ItsJazTanner/how-planning-a-virtual-offsite-prepared-me-for-covid-19-remote-work-c0e92bb4fefb&quot;&gt;richly detailed piece&lt;/a&gt; on her experience organizing the entire offsite virtually, I decided to write this post based on my specific role as the designer tasked with running a “mini-design sprint” virtually as part of the proceedings, with reflections on what things worked well (and not so well) for more virtual design sprints that will likely be in our futures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-the-scene&quot;&gt;Setting the scene&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goals-and-expectations&quot;&gt;Goals and expectations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to do was to set clear objectives for the event. For the Growth team, our aims were two-fold. Firstly, it was to finalise work on our current project to introduce “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth/Personalized_first_day/Newcomer_tasks&quot;&gt;Suggested edits&lt;/a&gt;” (small editing tasks) to new users in the Wikipedia languages we work with to pilot our new features. As the designer on the team, it was my responsibility to lead ideation for the offsite’s second aim: to address our longer term goal of creating a &lt;strong&gt;cohesive newcomer experience&lt;/strong&gt; so that new Wikipedia users feel welcomed and encouraged to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;audience-and-constraints&quot;&gt;Audience and constraints&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To meet these challenges we had to integrate the diverse perspectives of our team, which consisted of myself, a product manager, a program manager, three engineers, an engineering manager, a QA analyst, a data analyst, and a community relations specialist. Some members of our team had participated in a couple of design sprints before, others had limited experience with the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I saw it there were 3 main challenges in adapting the traditional / formal design sprint format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: How might we complete a nimble ~3 hour design sprint when it typically takes a few days? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distance&lt;/strong&gt;: How might we successfully discuss and sketch together to generate ideas when everyone is remote? &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engagement&lt;/strong&gt;: How might we encourage participation amongst non-designers who may be unfamiliar, daunted and/or plain dislike the format and tools used? (sketching is not enjoyable for everyone!) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An additional constraint on time was that the design “mini-sprint” was to be broken up into two sessions on days #2 and #4 of a four-day long virtual offsite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;over-planning-ahead&quot;&gt;(Over) Planning ahead&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the oft-quoted saying that “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Blaise_Pascal&quot;&gt;I would have written a shorter letter, but I did not have the time&lt;/a&gt;” applies to sprint planning too. Doing more pre-planning including creating pre-reading for participants was important in ensuring the shorter sprint format had a chance of being executed well, and in time.  Prior to the whole offsite, the team responded to a short survey with their hopes and fears, which helped immensely with deciding the mix of passive/active participation and level of group vs individual work to include.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also essential to planning was determining the focus of the design sprint activity, and then tailoring (and paring down) only the most relevant activities to achieve that goal. Taking cues from a few other blog posts about &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@designsprintstudio/the-one-hour-brain-sprint-409fc5417e10&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.prototypr.io/the-2-hour-design-sprint-9e2bbc14ee1&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://ux.shopify.com/the-4-hour-design-sprint-b05b516cede7&quot;&gt;four hour&lt;/a&gt; design sprints, I decided in session #1 to use some parts of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://designsprintkit.withgoogle.com/methodology/overview&quot;&gt;Google Ventures design sprint&lt;/a&gt; method, with the question of “How might we create an integrated newcomer homepage” as the overarching prompt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/virtual-sprint-slides.png&quot; alt=&quot;Virtual sprint slides&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Slides used to introduce the design sprint activity.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sprinting-what-happened-on-the-growth-sprint&quot;&gt;Sprinting: What happened on the Growth sprint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This section discusses what we did during the sprint, before I then delve into more details on the tools and resources used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;session-one-diverging-and-ideating&quot;&gt;Session One: Diverging and ideating&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The product manager and I gave lightning talks on different key themes around the newcomer experience, while each person wrote down their ideas in the “How Might We…” (HMW) format: a way of describing ideas and challenges positively in the form of an opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Growth team already had a pretty comprehensive understanding of the project, so as anticipated there was a diverse range of HMWs generated. I then took the team through an affinity mapping exercise – essentially a fancy term for organizing similar ideas into groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We voted for the top five ideas from the affinity groups and proceeded to the sketch phase (the third Google DS Methodology phase) where participants created “pitch posters” (see example in the facilitation deck linked at the end resources). During these break-out sessions people worked in pairs to design interaction flows and user experiences in as high or low fidelity as they were comfortable working with, and returned to the group to present to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Facilitation_deck_for_Design_exercise_1_Growth_2019_Virtual_Offsite.pdf&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/virtual-sprint-figma-session-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Facilitation deck&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot from the Figma board used in Design Session One during the HMW exercise.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;session-two-converging-on-key-insights&quot;&gt;Session Two: Converging on key insights&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the “wrap-up” session where we reviewed the top ideas generated in the first session, and ended with a fun exercise to help each team member reflect on the different perspectives brought to the newcomer homepage’s upcoming feature work. From here, the intention was that each team member could better articulate and advocate for priorities from their preferred position, and help drive the product direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We needed a collaborative decision-making activity that wasn’t purely democractic, but was still open, transparent, and hopefully fun. I invented the “Marry, Move, Kill” activity in which each person would describe their dream newcomer homepage based on the existing homepage as well as sections that had been voted on the previous day. From these candidates, each team member must “marry” sections to their home page, “move” others, and “kill” at least one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figma.com/file/atUa8TCT65bu1tMBx1Q571/Growth-Design-Fall-2019-Offsite-%E2%80%93%C2%A0Design-Session-2?node-id=216%3A13&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/virtual-sprint-figma-session-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Template page on Figma for Marry, Move, Kill activity&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot from the Figma board used in Design Session Two during the Marry, Move, Kill exercise.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;documenting-the-outcomes-post-sprint&quot;&gt;Documenting the outcomes post-sprint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One benefit of the virtual sprint is that format lends itself for easier documenting.  In the case of many conference call apps, you can literally record the sessions. Whilst we didn’t do so for the design sessions this time around, there were a few key outcomes documented in the various notes and artefacts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identified a future feature&lt;/strong&gt;: Building out a Mentor dashboard to help experienced editors better guide new contributors&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insights about tailoring specific features to Mobile or Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;: Experimenting with different experiences and on mobile and desktop - realising that a cohesive experience does not necessarily require parity of features available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confirmation about product direction&lt;/strong&gt;: Driving editing as the focus of the newcomer homepage feature&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Meta-outcome&lt;/strong&gt;: Getting a better sense of each team member’s priorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;choosing-suitable-tools-for&quot;&gt;Choosing suitable tools for…&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;remote-friendly-participation&quot;&gt;Remote-friendly participation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Design sprints can be challenging even when people are face-to-face. Managing the process remotely had to address such variables as connection speeds, platform diversity, familiarity with remote collaboration tools, and general comfort with doing this kind of work via video conference. So much can be lost without the cues and subtleties of being co-located, so it was important to choose remote-collaboration tools that were both reliable, and relatively familiar for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Meet was used for all video conferencing and communication, Google Slides to create and present the facilitation deck (and supporting materials), and Figma for our collaborative design sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;video-conferencing&quot;&gt;Video conferencing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used Google Meet for both the main event, as well as breaking out  into smaller groups in ‘side Meets’ for the sketch phase, but only on the first day, as it seemed like too much time spent out of group discussion dissipated focus. We did no breakout sessions on day two to allow the team to concentrate on the Marry, Move, Kill exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facilitating&quot;&gt;Facilitating&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a facilitation deck that communicated each session’s goals and served as the roadmap for the sprint. I chose Google Slides because as with Meet, everyone was already familiar with the tool. For presenting over a video call, it turned out to be very useful to not only have this deck, but having it under the management and control of a single presenter meant easy incorporation of useful facilitator tools like countdown timers (via embedding YouTube videos like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Vn31KFenBIo&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;) and reaction GIFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborating&quot;&gt;Collaborating&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the sketch phase I used Figma, a web-based collaborative design tool, to create templates and design elements that were intended to help non-designers participate more easily (through being able to copy and paste existing visual elements). In retrospect, even Figma proved to be too finicky for some on the team (and this was even with a “warm-up exercise” to get team members familiar with using it). I recommend using collaboration tools that everyone in a group is familiar with or can get up to speed on quickly. Google slides could have been used instead, and so could paper and pencil sketches that could have been photographed and shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr-checklist-for-the-next-virtual-sprint&quot;&gt;TL;DR: Checklist for the next virtual sprint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst there is definitely value in having in-person meetings that a remote event can never match completely, there are some benefits of the format that may help offset the social/bonding cost. Being alone in their own environments may be beneficial in helping participants to focus, albeit in shorter online doses. The following are some thoughts for how I would try to plan the next sprint so that folks go from being a captive audience to a captivated participant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan&quot;&gt;Plan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set clear objectives for what should be accomplished at the end of the sprint.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tailor to your audience. Determine how much onboarding for an idea or activity may be necessary for the particular group’s knowledge/skill set/interests.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Preview content if possible. Sharing the agenda, introducing tools, rubrics, etc. &lt;em&gt;beforehand&lt;/em&gt; can reduce the amount of introduction required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the scope. Don’t try to shoot the moon in 3 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide enough time, then add a few more minutes for transition time for good measure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Assign a moderator and note-taker.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incorporate some ‘fun’ activities too. Interspersing sessions with some short ice-breaker type activities will help folks get comfortable chatting and sharing ideas over video&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;provide&quot;&gt;Provide&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An overview of goals, activities, and metrics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Warm-up exercises to get familiar and comfortable with relatively new collaboration tools.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;More interactive and entertaining-framing on activities can help inject some more social enjoyment that is missed from not having an in-person event&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opportunities for smaller sessions and regrouping.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Templates for collaboration and assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collaborate&quot;&gt;Collaborate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use templates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pick the right tool for the collaborative job.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on enabling everyone to contribute.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Break out and regroup as necessary.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reflect&quot;&gt;Reflect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look back on what has been done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Measure against stated goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Share the results.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide opportunity for group feedback.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-feedback-always-welcome&quot;&gt;More feedback always welcome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the opinions in this writing are my own, the Wikimedia Design team strives to design in the open with a transparent and participatory process. With that in mind, we welcome any thoughts and experiences you may have on running a virtual design sprint, especially in a group where not everyone is a designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  Written with the assistance of David A.M. Goldberg
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Reflections from my first fully remote offsite</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/virtual-sprint-lead-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/virtual-sprint-lead-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Is it Possible to Improve User Experience on Wikipedia While Including Everyone? Absolutely.</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/05/21/improve-ux-for-everyone.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is it Possible to Improve User Experience on Wikipedia While Including Everyone? Absolutely." /><published>2020-05-21T17:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-21T17:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/05/21/improve-ux-for-everyone</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2020/05/21/improve-ux-for-everyone.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-a-m-goldberg-900961b2/&quot;&gt;David A. M. Goldberg&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Volker_E&quot;&gt;Volker Eckl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activist and political theorist Dr. Angela Y. Davis once stated that the most ethical way to assess the health of a society or institution is in terms of how it treats those who have been marginalized. Put another way, Dr. Davis is arguing that outliers are the true measure of a system’s values, not those who are assumed to be “typical,” “average,” “healthy,” or “normal.” More often than not, such adjectives describe the degree to which a person conforms to a system’s requirements, not a system’s ability to accommodate the diversity of their needs. In line with its democratic mission to make all of the world’s information available for free, across differences in culture, tradition, and language, the Wikimedia Foundation believes that everyone should have access to computing’s ever-increasing powers of content creation, distribution, and consumption. This ethic and its problem-solving strategies are part of inclusive design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have ever removed or put on your glasses, or held your device at arm’s length to better perceive a screen, then you have encountered issues that inclusive design tackles. The same can be said if you have done a text search on a video stream’s closed-captions, prefer your applications in “dark mode,” or struggled with a screen in bright sunlight. If you are a person using a screen reader or your operating system’s text-to-speech functions to access these words, or if you’ve ever dug deep into your system settings to adjust contrast and the scale of interface elements like pointers or text then you are also already literate in and benefitting from some aspects of inclusive design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikimedian &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Volker_E&quot;&gt;Volker Eckl&lt;/a&gt; is leading the team of Foundation designers that are pursuing the Foundation’s mission by implementing inclusive design at the level of the user-interface: that’s the geeky system of buttons, checkboxes, form patterns, typeface decisions, and careful considerations of spacing, color, and visual and behavioral consistency. We tend to notice a user-interface when it’s confusing or stops working, not when it is making content easier to read, recognize, and navigate. Projects that follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Design Style Guide&lt;/a&gt; implement the best practices in modern web design, leading to clean and reliable content experiences that are effective on your mobile device, laptop monitor, or gigantic flatscreen. These best practices also address web-specific accessibility issues, thereby making sure that the widest possible range of people can enjoy and participate in the creation of free knowledge content in the Wikimedia movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimism, it turns out, is highly technical work. Creating the Design Style Guide was one thing, but providing a world of volunteer producers, organizers, and users with the technology to implement it was another. To do so Volker and company pursue a couple of broad strategies: 1) making the work freely available, and open to modification by the global community the Foundation serves; and 2) doing a considerable amount of non-trivial, and largely invisible, work “under the hood” that makes the first strategy possible. These two pursuits involve managing a daunting array of technical, cultural, and aesthetic variables that include the character set for your language’s alphabet and the direction it reads, supporting text alternatives for multimedia content, balancing color contrast ratios to ensure readability, and ensuring content presentation in assistive technologies such as screen readers, speech-to-text systems, and braille translators. After several years of hard work, Volker and his peers have created clear aesthetic and technical guidelines for implementing design principles and fundamentals, provided tools to assist in producing accessible content, created a modern user interface library that anyone can integrate into their web-based projects, and built Wikimedia projects that meet these standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we do is both for and with our bodies, though the convenience of technology can sometimes make us pretend like we don’t have them. “As our bodies change, we encounter more mismatched designs,” writes Kat Holmes in &lt;em&gt;Mismatch: How Inclusion Shapes Design&lt;/em&gt;, “simply because the designs that once worked well for us don’t change with us” (29). Access to some things we interact with are already segregated by factors such as age, so we don’t necessarily complain when we become physically incapable of doing something like skateboarding. Driving a vehicle has fuzzier edges, as anyone who has negotiated with a senior friend or relative well knows. Holmes also tells us that losing one’s privileges hurts, and it causes “anxiety, insecurity, anger, hostility, feelings of inadequacy, [and] a sense of being out of control” (33). The promise of inclusive design, for all of its challenges and complexities, is that it can contribute to someone experiencing the polar opposite of each one of these feelings. Volker and his peers aren’t just concerned with people who can’t or can no longer interact with certain aspects of the web. They are also addressing the mistaken thinking that people in that position are the only ones who benefit from rich and robust accessible design strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia Foundation leaders like Volker and his design team, and the community that make its projects viable and possible understand that notions of “ability/disability” and “capability/impairment” are flexible. They aren’t bound to fixed identities or politicized categories, and they aren’t imaginary or abstract either. Pursuing inclusive and accessible web design and development practices can establish infrastructure that is taken for granted in the future, like today’s searchable transcripts, automatic doors, and ramped curbs. Similarly, alternate descriptions and metadata that is goes unnoticed by most web users could be interpreted and translated into a language “spoken” through the vibrations of your phone, or used to create smart summaries of large data sets. Imagine getting a sense of an incoming message’s content without taking out your device, or being alerted to cool images in your social media feed without having to scroll through all of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia Foundation aims to support a diverse audience, and it is committed to not raising barriers for one group of people as it seeks to improve the experience another has with its products and projects. Because Wikimedia projects are, at the level of their foundations, open and collaborative, a commitment to inclusive design that addresses more than the formal category of “disability” or “handicap” is a natural fit. Making all of the world’s knowledge freely available is a monumental task that some consider to be impossible. It is undoubtedly a slow process that cannot be managed from the top down in a fundamentally volunteer-driven movement, but it is absolutely worth it, because with the philosophical, ethical, and technical basis that Volker and his peers have provided, we are one step closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-a-m-goldberg-900961b2/&quot;&gt;David A. M. Goldberg&lt;/a&gt; is a writer, teacher, cultural critic, whose work focuses on issues of innovative democratic access to computing and communications technologies.
  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Volker_E&quot;&gt;Volker Eckl&lt;/a&gt; is a Senior User-Experience Engineer in the Wikimedia Foundation’s Product Design department and has been leading design system and accessibility projects.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How designers at the Wikimedia Foundation are ensuring that all the world’s knowledge is accessible to everyone.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/everyone.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/everyone.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>