<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-20T23:42:21+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Wikimedia Design Blog</title><subtitle>Make sharing of knowledge easy and joyful, for everyone.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Understanding the Wiki Communications and Mentorship Ecosystems</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding the Wiki Communications and Mentorship Ecosystems" /><published>2021-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-20T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/20/understanding-the-wiki-communications-and-mentorship-ecosystems.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:dchen@wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;Daisy Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Growth&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Editing_team&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Editing&lt;/a&gt; teams were respectively making plans and progress on Newcomer features and Talk Pages in recent quarters, the teams were curious about where and how wiki users are communicating with one another, and how mentorship manifests within the communication ecosystem. As a first step in this process, &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/strategy/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Product Design Strategy&lt;/a&gt; completed an initial round of research with a participant cohort of primarily affiliate group members, Foundation staff, and other long-time volunteers to illuminate the communications/mentorship ecosystem  and identify areas of potential future study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-we-wanted-to-learn&quot;&gt;What we wanted to learn&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Growth and Editing teams wanted to keep the research and discovery process open-ended, they both had some goals in mind for their respective teams’ work. The Growth team hoped the research outcomes would inform the mentorship and collaboration opportunities being tested in the Newcomer program initiatives. The Editing team wanted to understand use cases, benefits and impacts of various communication channels being utilized and how that might feed their work on Talk Pages and New Discussion Tool. Both teams felt this research would impact ongoing work and future plans around communication features/support and mentorship/collaboration opportunities, and we jointly created a couple grounding sets of research questions to that end:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;communications&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the various communication tools used by different communities to have these discussions?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What types of work are done on these channels?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do community members communicate besides on wiki (ie., besides Talk pages, Village Pump, etc) across different language wikis?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the motivations for using on and/vs off wiki channels? What are the benefits and tradeoffs of each?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Why are these tools used instead/as well, and what are their efficacies as effective/positive communication tools?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mentorship&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How is mentorship defined? What does it look like on the ground?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What factors influence mentorship motivation? How can users be encouraged to mentor others, and see their impacts?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How has/does communicating with other contributors affect newcomers’ understanding of Wikipedia as a community of people working together and their connection to it?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the efficacy of the off wiki channels specifically in attracting and fostering new contributors?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can productivity tools that promote collaborative editing/communication/tracking, potentially integrated on wiki, also affect mentorship effectiveness?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-research-participants-and-process&quot;&gt;Our research participants and process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To contain the scope of this initial round of research (with a second round envisioned to expand our research into other segments), we decided to keep our first participant cohort to those who have had more experience working in the various wiki communities. These folks worked in a wide range of wiki-related roles both in various organizational and volunteer capacities; the goal was to hear about their communications and mentorship experiences at length. Interviews were conducted in English.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few target languages/regions came into focus after reviewing geographic areas of interest the Growth and Editing teams pinpointed and where ongoing recruitment of potential participants seemed to be proving most fruitful. Ultimately, the participants were determined after evaluating languages, regions and genders represented, and diversity of roles within the wiki movement, among other factors. The languages/regions in particular were determined when we were able to establish a ‘critical mass’ of sorts, where we spoke with enough participants in each to start observing patterns in their responses and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We concluded the project with 18 participant interviews across 4 primary geographic regions. Each of the interviews were semi-structured, with a prepared discussion guide to provide a basic framework for the exploration while allowing for the participants to freely express both directly and tangentially relevant experiences and feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;post__table&quot;&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Primary Location&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Country(/ies)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;Language(s)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th&gt;# participants&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;South America&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Brazil, Portugal*&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Portuguese&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Southeast Asia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Indonesia, Philippines, UK*&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Bahasa indonesian, Nias, Bikol, Tagalog, Pangasinan&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;South Asia&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;India&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Hindi, Bengali, Punjabi, many other Indic languages&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;MENA/T&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Turkey, Jordan, Morocco&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;Turkish, Arabic&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p class=&quot;post__small&quot;&gt;* grouped with South America due to work on same language wiki&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-did-we-discover-in-these-conversations&quot;&gt;What did we discover in these conversations?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;communications-1&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Devices and access.&lt;/strong&gt; Even given the characteristics of this cohort (juggling a wide range of audiences and channels both on and off wiki, high volume of communication, high relative access to digital resources), none of the participants indicated that they used their mobile as a primary device for their communications. Many indicated that laptop/desktop access made many tasks easier to accomplish as some on wiki tasks are not yet mobile-friendly or lack appropriate functionality (in addition to inherent screen and device limitations). Laptop/desktop use was also convenient as many classically mobile tasks (texting, sending images, calling) are increasingly available from a desktop version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/devices-used.png&quot; alt=&quot;Devices used to communicate for wiki work.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though this is the direct finding from this cohort, many from the cohort broached the issue that many existing and potential users, especially from the Southeast Asia and South Asia (India) regions, are facing device/digital resource limitations. They may face inconsistent internet infrastructure/access, limited/expensive data, and limited access to devices (no/shared access to a singular mobile device, paid entry to internet cafes with device access). To address this, optimizing our mobile experience in terms of accessibility/reliability and additional features while limiting bandwidth used where possible is key to reaching this audience further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On or off wiki communication?&lt;/strong&gt; This cohort bucked expectations again here; even though their wiki communication is heavily due to a wiki-related role/obligation and their individual capacities as volunteers, they tended to do most of the communication off the wikis. Those who utilized on-wiki communications more often indicated they did so primarily for posting official updates and documenting conversations and outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants often strategically move conversations between on and off wiki channels, most specifically moving discussions to off wiki channels and then returning on wiki to document the outcomes and decisions from those discussions. The reasons given for moving discussions off wiki included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expediency (having the discussions was logistically quicker to do on off wiki channels)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wider reach/more inclusive (more people quantitatively in general and more were engaged in the conversation than on on wiki alternative arenas)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more availability for private or otherwise sensitive conversation as needed (everything on wiki is visible for anyone)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, many participants empathetically said that being on wiki is a “disadvantage” and an “inequality”, especially for newer users. The learning curve overall, the invisibility of accessing help and finding communication channels, understanding the norms of communication in each wiki community – all contribute to why the cohort as a rule tends to try and meet newer users where they are, which is most often an off wiki channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/where-participants-communicate.png&quot; alt=&quot;Where do our participants communicate.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;“The more time you put in off wiki, the less time you need to defend it on meta&quot;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;On and off wiki channels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Below you’ll find examples of channels being used both on and off wiki, an approximated scorecard of the pros and cons of the two main options, and basic flow charts of the most common use cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main takeaways:&lt;/strong&gt; off wiki channels score higher on all listed criteria for our participants and provide the most helpful outcomes when it comes to the tasks and connections they need to make in their wiki work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Off wiki channels as a whole offer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quicker responses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more casual feel that can lead to more sincere communication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;option for private conversations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better accessibility and mobile/UI-friendly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Where does off wiki communication fall short as a category? The regard for on wiki legitimacy remains; it is a must for announcements, recording of important decisions and outcomes, and everything posted is public, documentable, and referenceable. The transparency and accountability on off wiki options are not as clear cut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/on-off-wiki-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;On and off wiki chart.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/on-off-wiki-graph.png&quot; alt=&quot;On and off wiki graph.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;What do participants think could improve communication?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The participant suggestions below are charted on a continuum of simple to execute (left/green) to the more complex (right/red). They are also sorted into suggestions that could impact communications more directly (top half) and changes that have more of an indirect impact (bottom half).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/improve-communication.png&quot; alt=&quot;Improving Communication.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mentorship-1&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentorship as described by many participants is transactional and editing-centric. A few members of this cohort, while tackling task-based, editing-focused questions, have also emphasized and lived the importance of additional facets of a mentorship relationship. Moving forward, we should support a tailored approach to mentorship, one that spans the transactional/functional (knowing what/how to do) to the institutional/inspirational (understanding of the movement, engagement borne of interest, belonging and recognition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We need longevity and sustainability from good mentorship. Do we want 1 person who edits 100 times or get 10 people to do 10 edits each?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this framework, we’ll also need to address our users’ varying needs. While facilitating “human-powered” means of mentorship interactions, we should also take care to supplement learning with technical solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/examples-of-mentorship.png&quot; alt=&quot;Examples of mentorship and their impacts and frequencies, charted.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Examples of mentorship and their impacts and frequencies, charted&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Answering questions about editing tasks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This could be on a one-off or an ongoing basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Specific, targeted Commons photo advice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; A participant brought up this example; this individual received specific, actionable feedback on why photos were not being approved and what it would take for a photo to be approved and even featured&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creating and disseminating tutorial type materials.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Holding editing-focused workshops and events.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Teaching about the movement and opportunities;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. Making mentees aware of the larger movement, organizational structures, and providing advice on mentees’ draft proposals for their own projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Involving people in a hobby-based campaign;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. The Wiki Loves Butterfly initiative involved finding butterfly enthusiasts on social media, motivating them to join wiki, having 1:1 chats with them and meeting in person, showing them commons/uploading/categories and other editing-related tasks, doing/coordinating fieldwork and taking butterfly lifecycle photos, holding photo workshops etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Constant communication and community;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; e.g. Wiki World Heritage User Group holds workshops and is in constant communication/collaboration. Its engagement plan also includes a skills assessment in which members and newcomers are asked about knowledge on various topics/tools, and where they’d like to learn more. This is used to match people up, invite them to specific topic/tool discussions or sessions, or set up curriculum for planned workshops.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do participants think could improve mentorship?&lt;/strong&gt; There is some overlap in suggested solutions here, particularly the suggestion for forum-style, centralized discussion interface and for better documentation of various resources and FAQs. Participant suggestions range from simpler (left/green) to the more complex (right/red).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/improve-mentorship.png&quot; alt=&quot;Improving Mentorship.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;communications-2&quot;&gt;Communications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some relatively quicker fixes we can make to make our on wiki communications options more accessible, intuitive, and visible to our community, especially on mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a higher level, our Product teams need to weigh the pros and cons of making on wiki the go-to place for all wiki-related communications or acknowledge that on wiki is simply not meant to be that type of all-encompassing destination and support off wiki channels where possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other general considerations include device and data limitations many of our community members and potential users face, differing cultural tendencies (e.g, security, privacy, building trust) and community-specific norms around policing, attitudes towards newcomers/anonymous users, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mentorship-2&quot;&gt;Mentorship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communications ecosystem’s visibility and functionality are the foundation for mentorship to develop, flourish, and sustain. The functionality aspect should increasingly address not just transactional forms of newcomer help/training (documentation pages, FAQs, bots) but also allow for organic growth of mentorship connections and opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When mentorship connections do not arise organically, such as in structured newcomer programs, the resulting mentorship interactions tend to remain more transactional in nature and lack an inspirational element that fosters feelings of ownership and more naturally creates opportunities for challenge/reward dynamics to arise. These are factors that tend to establish additional connections, interests, and overall a more prolonged, lasting relationship with the mentor and the movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next-planning-collaboration-evaluation&quot;&gt;What’s next? Planning, collaboration, evaluation.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prioritization and planning current/future roadmap.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The findings inform ways (and focus areas) in which our Growth team’s Newcomer homepage/tasks initiatives can be improved and supplemented with concurrent efforts. The team can focus on ideation, prioritization, and planning for features in upcoming quarters/annual plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scoping &amp;amp; cross-team collaboration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Other Foundation teams may find this work relevant in their focus areas, both in and outside of Product. There are opportunities for the Growth team to coordinate with other teams (e.g. Editing, Android &amp;amp; iOS, Trust &amp;amp; Safety) on issues impacting communications and mentorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analytics/UX evaluations of Newcomer initiatives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; As Growth team’s newcomer initiatives are rolled out on test wikis and perhaps additional wikis, evaluating on an iterative basis how the features are or aren’t meeting the needs of a variety of user personas, using both analytics and usability testing/interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-strategic-research&quot;&gt;Further strategic research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Additional relevant personas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; The next phase of this research should include newcomers and mentees (specific subset of newcomers) more specifically. This will provide first-hand knowledge of how those first experiencing communications related to the wikis become aware of the variety of channels, their expectations and the realities, and their experiences of the newcomer initiatives and interactions with experienced users (in a general or specifically mentorship-type capacity) in these spaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Specific communities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; Further research should include communities with limited device and connectivity and also cultural concerns whereby trust is primarily built through in-person connections to see what support possibilities exist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Where and how wiki users are communicating with one another, and how mentorship manifests within the communication ecosystem.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/understanding-wiki-communications/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wikipedia and Apps: A Love Story</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wikipedia and Apps: A Love Story" /><published>2021-12-08T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-08T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/12/08/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schoenbaechler&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/carolynlimadeo&quot;&gt;Carolyn Li-Madeo&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/baba786&quot;&gt;Sudhanshu Gautam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Volker_E&quot;&gt;Volker E.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing for mobile apps presents unique challenges and opportunities compared to traditional websites. Mobile apps run natively on a device and have access to system resources that are harder to access within a web based architecture. Key characteristics of apps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apps are designed to fit with the rest of the operating system. When an app fits in with the rest of the OS, it not only looks and feels more at home, it lowers the users learning curve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A deep integration with the OS comes with benefits right out of the box, e.g. accessibility, performance, integration with voice assistants or &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;home screen widgets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Offline capabilities and often reduced data usage: offline capabilities allow users to consume content from anywhere, even when they are not connected to the internet or connectivity is low.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Wikimedia Foundation’s apps are an essential piece to meet our &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#this-is-for-everyone&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“this is for everyone” design principle&lt;/a&gt;. Wikimedia apps are designed with the philosophy of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mobile-first.abookapart.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;mobile first&lt;/a&gt; in mind. One of the core principles of mobile first is to embrace the constraints of a mobile environment and with it, prioritize essential information, as there’s simply not enough room for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limited connectivity of people in certain areas of the world inspires us to create products that are performant and light on data. When building new features for people using mobile apps, we strive for excellency in user experience and aim to break down complex existing flows and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on Android&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on iOS&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on iOS&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/app-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia app on kaiOS&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia app on kaiOS&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;Strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are here to create mobile first experiences&lt;/strong&gt; and are not trying to replace existing desktop or community tools. Through the apps, we aim to meet potential users where they are. We are interested in understanding and addressing barriers of those that have been historically left behind, while not compromising the integrity of the workflows of our long-time users on other platforms. Making participation fit naturally the mobile first lives we live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are a place to experiment.&lt;/strong&gt; Due to development speed, richer capabilities and unique needs of our user base, we are able to experiment. It is on the apps where we think the future of mobile editing will be discovered. Notably, the apps are where we piloted &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Suggested_edits#Welcome_to_Suggested_edits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;micro contributions&lt;/a&gt;, our most successful editing intervention to this date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The apps are a forcing function to make our technologies future proof.&lt;/strong&gt; To provide an example: Right now Wikipedia’s web experience works as a website only and cannot be exported to new mediums. By building on the apps, we create technology that is platform independent and enables next generation experiences. Whether these use artificial intelligence, augmented reality or future technology that is changing our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theming&quot;&gt;Theming&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;Theming.&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in the introduction, iOS and Android both have platform specific guidelines. When building apps for the global Wikimedia movement, our goal is to create native experiences for the specific platform. When designing for mobile apps, guidelines for the platform sit at the top of the hierarchy. Throughout Wikimedia’s product suite, we follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Design’s visual design principles&lt;/a&gt; when providing solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a seamless and familiar experience within Wikimedia’s products and services, we apply theming that is based on Wikimedia’s visual style guidelines. Theming allows us to customize the app’s look and feel, to better represent our product’s brand. Theming is reflected in the entire UI, including individual components, like buttons. Here’s an example of applying Material Theming in the Wikipedia Android app:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/material-button.png&quot; alt=&quot;A standard Material button&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A standard Material button (&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/design/material-theming/overview.html#material-theming&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;image source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/material-wikipedia-button.png&quot; alt=&quot;A themed button in the Wikipedia Android app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A themed button in the Wikipedia Android app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ios-keyboard-messages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Chat toolbar in iOS messaging&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Chat toolbar in iOS messaging (&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/resources/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;image source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ios-keyboard-wikipedia.png&quot; alt=&quot;Editing toolbar in the Wikipedia iOS app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Editing toolbar in the Wikipedia iOS app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/kaios-without-theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;KaiOS standard progress indicator.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;KaiOS standard progress indicator.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/kaios-with-theming.png&quot; alt=&quot;We used a planet animation progress indicator to show the vast amount of knowledge available on Wikipedia.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;We used a planet animation progress indicator to show the vast amount of knowledge available on Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design style guide’s &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_colors.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;color palette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is also used in the apps. Since both the Android and iOS Wikipedia app is available in four different reading themes (Light, Sepia, Dark and Black), they are using an enhanced color palette for an optimal reading experience. Check out more details about the color palette for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_theme_guidelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2017/12/04/ios-app-dark-theme/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/a&gt; here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/google-fonts.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Wikipedia Android app uses on Material Icons&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Wikipedia Android app uses on &lt;a href=&quot;https://fonts.google.com/icons&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Material Icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/sf-symbols.png&quot; alt=&quot;The Wikipedia iOS app uses SF Symbols&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Wikipedia iOS app uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/sf-symbols/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;SF Symbols&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As defined in the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_typography.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;typography&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; section of Wikimedia’s Design Style Guide, the app’s rely on the operating system’s default sans-serif typeface. The app’s mostly use &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/visual-style_icons.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;icons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; provided by the platform, e.g. from &lt;a href=&quot;hhttps://material.io/design/iconography&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Google Material&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/sf-symbols/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Apple Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, except for icons that are associated with established Wikimedia products or services (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/OOUI_icons#userTalk&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia’s icon for user talk pages&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;principles&quot;&gt;Principles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus&quot;&gt;Focus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The “Picture of the day” on Wikipedia for Android puts content from Wikimedia Commons in the spotlight.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The “Picture of the day” on Wikipedia for Android puts content from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; in the spotlight.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wikipedia for iOS focuses on the essential in its homescreen widgets.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Wikipedia for iOS focuses on the essential in its &lt;a href=&quot;https://uxdesign.cc/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios-fcf8548ae449&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;homescreen widgets&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/focus-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content. &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How clear is the goal? Based on Wikimedia Design’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#content-first&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“content first” principle&lt;/a&gt;, we aim to &lt;strong&gt;design apps that are easy to understand and focus on the essential&lt;/strong&gt;. When designing, content comes first, control comes second. On mobile, screen real estate is limited, places of usage are unforeseeable and the user’s focus is reduced. We strive to reduce information density while not neglecting an interface’s functional essence. Guiding questions like: What is the essence of this feature? What is the purpose of this particular screen? How much information can be deprioritized (or left out) to convey a UI’s purpose? Clarity stands for designing user interfaces with clear call to actions, generous use of white space, accessible contrast and hierarchy when designing with type or icons. Writing concise and suitable multilingual UI copy supports in reaching their goals more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;orientation&quot;&gt;Orientation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The 'More' navigation for Wikipedia on Android is designed to maintain the user’s context.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The 'More' navigation for Wikipedia on Android is designed to maintain the user’s context.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;The off-canvas menu on Wikipedia for iOS is one tap away from anywhere in the app.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The off-canvas menu on Wikipedia for iOS is one tap away from anywhere in the app.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/orientation-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Trending article list for readers to discover regionally relevant content. &quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The 'Options' menu lets readers easily navigate an article. It avoids unnecessary key presses.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where am I? &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#design-for-consistency&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Design for consistency and orientation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; are key aspects to help users navigate through an interface in a mobile app. We put explicit effort in communicating where users are and where they can go. Spatial awareness in a digital product helps users in achieving goals more directly. This is exemplified by using a consistent navigation, usage of depth and the application of motion. Deliberate usage of animation and transitions help users navigate an interface. Visual layers and realistic motion convey hierarchy, emotion and understanding when using a device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;emotion&quot;&gt;Emotion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/emotion-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;The 'Thanks' interaction in the Wikipedia for Android app&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The 'Thanks' interaction in the Wikipedia for Android app&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/emotion-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;The onboarding experience in the Wikipedia for iOS app educates and resonates emotionally&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The onboarding experience in the Wikipedia for iOS app educates and resonates emotionally&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the design feel on an emotional level? An often forgotten and invisible theme but yet one of the most impactful: emotional design. Along the lines of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#trustworthy-yet-joyful&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;”trustworthy yet joyful” design principle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;we believe that preserving the human touch and showing ourselves with our values in our work is essential&lt;/strong&gt;. Especially on a device that is as personal as your mobile phone. Instead of creating one more cheap and fast mass feature, we follow a philosophy that has been paved by artists, designers, and architects of the arts and crafts movement. After all, we design for humans and strive to create humane and emotional experiences. Through design, we can see and connect with other human beings. To design experiences that are emotional, we consider understanding the needs of the people we are designing for, as the core mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ergonomics&quot;&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-android.png&quot; alt=&quot;Example of ergonomically supporting users in the Wikipedia for Android app.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Example of ergonomically supporting users in the Wikipedia for Android app.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-ios.png&quot; alt=&quot;Relevant actions are located near the bottom of the screen for easy access.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Relevant actions are located near the bottom of the screen for easy access.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/ergonomics-kaios.png&quot; alt=&quot;For non-touch interfaces, placement of key actions (e.g. search, read, edit) is important. We linked key actions with commonly used phone keys to make them easy to perform&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;For non-touch interfaces, placement of key actions (e.g. search, read, edit) is important. We linked key actions with commonly used phone keys to make them easy to perform&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the design feel in my hand? &lt;strong&gt;Ergonomics, posture, context, and the tactile nature of touch have implications on how users interact with a design&lt;/strong&gt;. Our design principle “this is for everyone” is part of our core mission and designing for touch is different than designing for a keyboard, mouse or trackpad. When designing for apps, we embrace principles of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_manipulation_interface&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;direct manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, an interaction model where effect are immediately visible on the screen to the user. Designing for a touch device goes beyond enlarging buttons for bigger fingers. We deeply consider placement and positioning of elements to achieve an ergonomic user experience while being aware of different device usage types. And, as voice is considered as the most natural machine-human input method available, we make sure the interface reflects it. We design experiences that provide ergonomics on smartphones, tablets and hybrid laptop/touch devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;get-involved&quot;&gt;Get involved&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia iOS, Android and kaiOS apps are each designed and developed by a specific team to that platform. If you’re interested in learning more about the apps or if you want to get involved, please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Apps on mediawiki.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;android&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_FAQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android team page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/apps-android-wikipedia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;gl=US&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6UkFHYqVsbc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android App promo video on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Android_theme_guidelines&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Android color guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://material.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Google Material Design Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ios&quot;&gt;iOS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/iOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS team page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for iOS on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.apple.com/us/app/wikipedia/id324715238&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for iOS in the App Store&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T169148&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;iOS color guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/overview/themes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Apple Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kaios&quot;&gt;kaiOS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikipedia_for_KaiOS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for KaiOS project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-kaios&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for kaiOS on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimedia.github.io/wikipedia-kaios/sim.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikipedia KaiOS app simulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.kaiostech.com/docs/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;nofollow&quot;&gt;KaiOS documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Jazmin Tanner &amp;amp; Josh Minor for their contributions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Designing for mobile apps presents unique challenges and opportunities compared to traditional websites. Mobile apps run natively on a device and have access to system resources that are harder to access within a web based architecture.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-and-apps-a-love-story/header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Patrolling Unregistered Editors on Wikipedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Patrolling Unregistered Editors on Wikipedia" /><published>2021-11-17T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-17T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/11/17/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://prtksxna.com/&quot;&gt;Prateek Saxena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On most Wikipedias, you don’t need an account to make an edit. While there are benefits to making an account — such as a single place to see all communications, or a place to store articles that you’re interested in — there is no requirement to make one. This reduced barrier to entry means that people around the world can contribute to our projects — whether it’s a small typo fix or a new article — without ever having to make an account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, it also means that it’s easier to vandalize and make destructive edits to our projects. To counter this, our editors and administrators patrol edits made by registered and unregistered editors alike. These watchful editors are also known as &lt;em&gt;patrollers&lt;/em&gt;. To keep out bad faith edits from our projects, patrollers need to have an understanding of who is making the edits. In the case of unregistered editors though, the information that they rely on most is their &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IP_address&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IP address&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An IP address is a unique address that is given to any device that is connected to a network like the Internet. When an unregistered user makes an edit, the change isn’t attributed to their name, but their device’s IP address instead. An IP address is like a home address, it cannot reveal your identity but one can deduce a lot about you by knowing where you live. So, what might seem to some as an &lt;em&gt;anonymous&lt;/em&gt; way of editing actually reveals more about them than a simple pseudonym would.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrollers copy these IP addresses into external &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WHOIS&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WHOIS tools&lt;/a&gt; to understand where the editor is coming from. These tools tell them information about where the editor might be and how they’re connecting to the Internet. To reduce the extra step of copy-pasting addresses, and providing a single place to get IP  information, the Anti-Harassment Tools team started work on an &lt;em&gt;IPInfo&lt;/em&gt; tool within Wikipedia. This tool would give our patrollers the needed information right where they need it — when analyzing an unregistered user’s contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designing-ip-info&quot;&gt;Designing IP Info&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;initial-research&quot;&gt;Initial Research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we wanted to get a better understanding of the patrolling process and specifically how IP addresses are used while evaluating edits. To do this we conducted interviews with editors who often patrol our projects and asked them to show and talk us through their process. This gave us an overview of the different ways patrollers go about keeping our projects vandalism free. After a few rounds of feedback from design, research, engineers and Trust &amp;amp; Safety folks we had the following task model:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-risk-vs-usefulness-matrix-wikimedia-design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_lmUSH8s=/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; for a full view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand now that IP patrolling usually starts from RecentChanges, an editor’s Watchlist, or from a page that the editor knows gets vandalized often. When looking at the edits of such a page the patroller first looks for clear red flags like edit flooding (lots of minor edits in a short amount of time), no edit summary, large deletions etc. They then look for more specific on-wiki information like if the IP has a talk page, if it has ever been blocked, and its global and local contributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this initial fact-finding, patrollers decide if an IP is worth looking into further. If it is, they use external tools to find more information about the IP. They’re looking for details  like — location, proxy usage and organization that the IP might be linked to. This process is not completely accurate since different databases have different information on the same IP. Oftentimes, based on the location of the IP and the location of the tool the editors are using, the information provided might vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, based on the information collected, patrollers decide which action would be most appropriate. Again, this decision takes into account various factors like the policies of that wiki, the scale of the collateral damage caused by a range block, consistency in editing patterns, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mock-ups&quot;&gt;Mock-ups&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patrollers need on-wiki information about the IP before they decide to investigate it, so, we decided to add a popup that shows block and contribution information. The popup would be accessible by clicking an information icon next to the IP address on pages like RecentChanges, Watchlist and History.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-popup-wikimedia-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;The IP Info popup that’ll be accessible from pages like RecentChanges that patrollers monitor for edits.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The IP Info popup that’ll be accessible from pages like RecentChanges that patrollers monitor for edits.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the patroller decides to dig deeper into an IP address by going to their Contributions page, they’ll be able to see a collapsible box that shows more IP related information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-box-wikimedia-design.png&quot; alt=&quot;The IP Info box shown on the Contributions page gives detailed information to the patrollers.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The IP Info box shown on the Contributions page gives detailed information to the patrollers.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing these mocks internally brought up three questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much information is useful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who should have access to this information?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Should some patrollers have access to partial bits of information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;balancing-needs&quot;&gt;Balancing needs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our projects have a wide variety of contributors and vary in socio-demography, accessibility and motivations. These and other factors were captured in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Research:Knowledge_Gaps_Index/Taxonomy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Knowledge Gap Taxonomy&lt;/a&gt; research, which not only looked at the gaps in Wikipedia’s content but the gaps in the contributors as well. In turn, we reframed our design questions as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How might we make sure that revealing IP information doesn’t put our most marginalized contributors at risk?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How might we ensure that access to information and tools doesn’t become a barrier to contributions for our least technically skilled contributors?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While IP information needs to be available to all, we wanted to make sure that it doesn’t put anyone at risk and it isn’t so technical &amp;amp; overwhelming that it becomes meaningless to most patrollers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;team-workshop&quot;&gt;Team Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Anti-Harassment Tools team and the Trust &amp;amp; Safety teams came together for a small workshop to discuss these items. We acknowledged that we want both non-technical and technical users to have easy access to IP information. We also acknowledged that we can’t put our unregistered editors at risk especially because some of the IP information, like location and organization, can potentially help in identifying a person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our discussions around accessibility for patrollers we noted questions and concerns around information overload, accuracy of information and false confidence in IP data. We also considered if having IP information more readily available might lead to its misuse. The following clusters began to form:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we make sure that people understand the data they’re looking at, and understand its accuracy too?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal information:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we make sure that information is accessible to those who need it, without putting unregistered editors at risk?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agency:&lt;/strong&gt; How might we inform unregistered editors of the data they are leaving traces of and show them ways to protect it (create an account)?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After brainstorming on the questions we started to organize our thoughts in the following manner — we need to balance the concerns of ease of use for patrollers and risk to unregistered editors. To do this we plotted the different pieces of IP information on a graph with Risk on the Y axis and Usefulness to patrolling on the X axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/ip-info-task-model-wikimedia-design.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Task model for IP Patrolling on wikis.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Plotting the different pieces of IP information based on Risk (to editor) and Usefulness (to patroller). See &lt;a href=&quot;https://miro.com/app/board/o9J_lmUSH8s=/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Miro&lt;/a&gt; for a full view.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise was based on the learnings from research as well as the team’s experience. Two clear clusters appeared, the high risk one mostly containing information that could reveal an editor’s location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this, we are planning to show a limited set of information to most users and give access to more sensitive information to only our most trusted users — Administrators and CheckUsers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;gathering-feedback&quot;&gt;Gathering feedback&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-input&quot;&gt;Community input&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sharing our findings with the community led to some interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/Talk:IP_Editing:_Privacy_Enhancement_and_Abuse_Mitigation/IP_Info_feature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conversations and feedback&lt;/a&gt;. Some common themes were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Increasing or deepening the scope of a particular piece of information. IP Information is complex and having more context and data usually helps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Adding more data sources to get a wider picture of the IP information. This would also help in figuring out if the data being shown is reliable.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Specific points about IP ranges and IPv6 addresses and how to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;usability-tests&quot;&gt;Usability tests&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were also able to do some usability tests with Patrollers in the community. Overall, the feature was well-received and they liked that they won’t have to rely on external tools in the future. We were given some specific feedback around:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The distribution of information between the popup and the box. Some information is more helpful in the popup to decide whether or not to investigate further.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Having more guidance on how to use this information.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Showing some of this information on Diff pages so that editors have access to it while comparing revisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implementation is currently in the works and we’ll be rolling it out to wikis slowly as a BetaFeature, incorporating improvements based on usability testing. We’ll also be implementing feedback mechanisms in the tool so that we can learn more about how people are using the tool. To follow the updates on this feature and join the discussion, check out the project’s page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/IP_Editing:_Privacy_Enhancement_and_Abuse_Mitigation/IP_Info_feature&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wikimedia’s Meta-Wiki&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cover image by Tristan J. Wilson. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:TJDW_Stonehenge_20111107.tif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/deed.en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CC0 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Carolyn Li-Madeo, Rita Ho, Aida Ramirez, Jessica Klein &amp;amp; Niharika Kohli for your feedback and editing help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Balancing the needs of patrollers and unregistered editors on the wikis</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/stonehenge.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/patrolling-unregistered-editors-on-wikipedia/stonehenge.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving the reading experience for smart feature phones</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/09/23/improving-the-reading-experience-for-smart-feature-phones.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving the reading experience for smart feature phones" /><published>2021-09-23T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-23T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/09/23/improving-the-reading-experience-for-smart-feature-phones</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/09/23/improving-the-reading-experience-for-smart-feature-phones.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/baba786&quot;&gt;Sudhanshu Gautam&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading a Wikipedia article on a feature phone is time consuming. The article about Tiger might take 25-30 minutes to read on a smartphone; alternatively, it would take much longer to read on a feature phone. While smartphones are almost ubiquitous in some parts of the world, over 100M&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; people across the globe still use feature phones to connect to the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wikimedia has significant room to expand in emerging communities where access to inexpensive devices and cheap data is quickly growing. To help people overcome barriers to access free knowledge on our projects and be a trustworthy source of knowledge and information, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Inuka_team&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Inuka team&lt;/a&gt; at Wikimedia Foundation decided to improve the Wikipedia reading experience on feature phones to accommodate the unique needs and preferences of historically underrepresented users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;about-the-devices&quot;&gt;About the devices&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KaiOS, a mobile operating system based on HTML5 power these phones. It supports 4G/LTE, Wi-Fi, Bluetooth, and GPS. India is one of the biggest markets for KaiOS, where it powers Jiophone. These phones have limited computing capabilities, small displays, and most actions are performed using a keypad. Their low cost, combined with the ability to use apps like Google, Facebook, Youtube, etc., make them a top choice among first-time internet users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the phone, all actions are presented on a softkey panel linked to physical keys on the keypad. Most actions are performed using center, left, and right hardware keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;design-process&quot;&gt;Design process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team started using feature phones to familiarize ourselves with keypad-based interactions, challenges when using apps, impact of limited infrastructure on user experience, and how the Wikipedia reading experience feels. In parallel, we worked with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hureo.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hureo&lt;/a&gt;, a user research firm based in India, to conduct foundational research&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; with 25 participants in different cities in India. Research aimed to learn about how they used these devices, their motivations to use them, their awareness of Wikipedia, and their experiences reading Wikipedia articles. These are some of the findings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Smart features, durability, and good battery life at an affordable price are the main reasons to use feature phones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Primary usage is social media, entertainment, and look for information online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Wikipedia awareness is low. Informed users use it to read about famous people, entertainment, places to visit, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reading a long Wikipedia article on its browser is quite laborious as typing and scrolling is difficult.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Participants mentioned that the small font size required extra effort to read, and caused strain on their eyes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For quick navigation, users wished to have easy access to the table of contents, images, and other parts of articles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These insights from our research, combined with our own experiences and frustrations when reading Wikipedia articles on feature phones, indicated that we should try to provide a better reading experience for all of these people. These were the improvements we were interested in testing with users:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An onboarding flow to define What Wikipedia is in simple language to users who may or may not have used it before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/brief-onboarding.png&quot; alt=&quot;Brief onboarding to share about Wikipedia, language diversity, and the volume of articles available.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Brief onboarding to share about Wikipedia, language diversity, and the volume of articles available.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A “quick links panel” to directly access a section of an article, view images, or  read an article in different languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/quick-links.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quick links to access different parts of an article.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Quick links to access different parts of an article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead of continuous scrolling using the keypad while moving through an article, readers can read clear segments of a Wikipedia article on the small screen one page at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt; 
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/page-navigation.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Animation showing page by page navigation on the Wikipedia app for KaiOS&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Animation showing page by page navigation on the Wikipedia app for KaiOS&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option to read an article in different text sizes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/change-article-text-size.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Change article text size from options menu.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Change article text size from options menu.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Option to use the app in different languages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/change-app-language.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Change app language from settings menu.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Change app language from settings menu.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-we-learn&quot;&gt;What did we learn?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the pandemic, conducting remote sessions in India was quite challenging as screen sharing is not directly supported by KaiOS. Luckily, all participants had access to smartphones either through their family members or friends. Twenty participants(12 Male, 8 Females) were recruited within the 20 to 40 years age group. Interviews were conducted in English, Hindi, Marathi, and Telugu to cover language diversity. Usability tasks involved installing the app, searching &amp;amp; reading an article of their choice, and any additional feedback to improve the app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;half-width centered&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/android-participant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A participant is using an android device to screen share on a zoom call.&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A participant is using an android device to screen share on a zoom call.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of session learnings.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users appreciated the ease of discovering articles in multiple languages and the simplicity of changing the app language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I can change before searching only. I will use this feature because I can use it  whenever I want to read in Marathi. - User 12&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users liked quick links to help them access different sections of an article, view images, and quickly access important facts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is part of the same article. This is like a shortcut, so from here I can read any topic related to the article. - User 6&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users were confused when certain articles were unavailable when they changed the app language to their regional language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I search for ‘Dosa recipe in hindi’ using voice search I get the results, here maybe the information is available in English only and not Hindi. - User 10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users could not understand the icon used for quick facts and considered it a map icon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I expected to see a map here, as the icon used for it was of a location. - User 11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Most users did not read the onboarding descriptions as they mostly ignore that part in other apps too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app was first released in India in September 2020 and was later released globally in December 2020. It has been downloaded over 2.5M times since its first release. In the next update, we are looking forward to improving article discovery and the overall reading experience. Improvements would include contextual onboarding to quickly start the app, a trending article list to find content beyond search functionality, and other minor changes to improve issues observed during usability sessions. Stay tuned for all the amazing work the Inuka team does to support new internet users in emerging markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/contextual-onboarding.png&quot; alt=&quot;Tips section for Contextual onboarding.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Tips section for Contextual onboarding.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/trending-article-list.jpg&quot; alt=&quot; Trending article list for regional content discovery. &quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Trending article list for regional content discovery. &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Thanks Angie Muigai, Prateek Saxena, Rita Ho, Nicolas Ayoub, Alex Hollender, and Aishwarya Vardhana for your feedback and editing help. A special thanks to Carolyn Li-Madeo, who did a fantastic job designing the app’s early experience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;related-links&quot;&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikipedia_for_KaiOS&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for KaiOS project page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-kaios&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for kaiOS on Github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimedia.github.io/wikipedia-kaios/sim.html&quot;&gt;Wikipedia KaiOS app simulator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.kaiostech.com/docs/&quot;&gt;KaiOS documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaiostech.com/kaios-2019-year-in-review/&quot;&gt;https://www.kaiostech.com/kaios-2019-year-in-review/&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/File:Understanding_KaiOS_users_in_India_-_Report.pdf
&quot;&gt;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/File:Understanding_KaiOS_users_in_India_-_Report.pdf
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Inuka team at Wikimedia Foundation decided to improve the Wikipedia reading experience on feature phones to accommodate the unique needs and preferences of historically underrepresented users</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/improving-reading-experience.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/improving-reading-experience/improving-reading-experience.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Improving search on Wikimedia Commons</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/08/12/media-search.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Improving search on Wikimedia Commons" /><published>2021-08-12T07:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-08-12T07:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/08/12/media-search</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/08/12/media-search.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/derrellwilliams&quot;&gt;Matthew Williams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people don’t realize that along with Wikipedia, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Foundation&lt;/a&gt; hosts a number of other projects, ranging from reference projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/Wiktionary:Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wiktionary&lt;/a&gt; to software projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/MediaWiki&quot;&gt;MediaWiki&lt;/a&gt;. These projects belong to everyone and like Wikipedia, are free to use to further our goal of providing the essential infrastructure for free knowledge &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; is one of these projects and is the world’s largest free-to-use library of illustrations, photos, drawings, videos, and music. Wikimedia Commons hosts more than 71 million freely usable media files&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to which anyone can contribute. It also hosts and organizes a majority of the media you encounter on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, one of the tasks of the structured data team, a cross-functional product team at the Wikimedia Foundation, was to focus on how to improve the search experience on Wikimedia Commons to better surface all of the media files contributed by people from around the world. One of the key tenets of this work was making the experience less intimidating, in particular to those not familiar with Wikimedia Commons. Being able to support a wide range of use-cases, from power users like museums digitizing their photography collection to a high school student using Wikimedia Commons for the first time to find free usable media to complete a science project, was critical to building a successful search experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious area the team focused on was ways to improve search accuracy since it doesn’t matter what you do with the presentation if the actual results aren’t mapping to the expectations of the searcher. However, this article, being written by the designer on the team, will be focused on the work that was done to ensure a much better experience that was created to complement these improved search results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the average person hears that I’m the designer on the Growth team for Wikipedia, there’s a common misconception that it’s about growing the number of readers, the more commonly thought of “Wikipedia user”. However, our team was formed almost three years ago with a different challenge and audience as our focus. This article aims to tell the six-part story of how and why we started this team, and all the failures, learnings, and successes we’ve had since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;baseline-research&quot;&gt;Baseline research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Special_Search_on_Commons.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Special Search on Commons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Largely untouched in its 17-year history, a screenshot of search on Wikimedia Commons before we started this project. | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Special_Search_on_Commons.jpg&quot;&gt;Special Search on Commons&lt;/a&gt; | Public Domain&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We kicked this project off with a round of research to get a more honest understanding of the strengths and weaknesses of search on Wikimedia Commons. With only a few quotes from the participants of this research, you can see what we were up against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is so much text and details, it was hard to find what I was looking for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It was frustrating to find all of the advanced search options, I figured it out after a while but didn’t expect to find them where I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It doesn’t feel like a very nice display of results…difficult to see the details and evaluate the results with such small images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It feels complicated and the images are hard to see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s extra work to  navigate back and forth between the file page and search to get everything I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I don’t trust it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can read, there was room for improvement. We needed to make the search experience more familiar and easy to use. Image search on the web is not a novel problem but the uniqueness of search on Wikimedia Commons was detrimental to casual users and those not intimately familiar with the project. With over 3 million daily page views&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on Wikimedia Commons, it’s more than obvious we needed to build a tool that made sense to everyone and aligned closer to their expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also knew that our most passionate contributors to the Wikimedia Commons project needed certain features and tools to help with their work. Would it be possible to make an experience that both catered to those unfamiliar with Wikimedia Commons and those that use it every day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;creating-a-more-functional-and-familiar-interface&quot;&gt;Creating a more functional and familiar interface&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the search experience on Wikimedia Commons&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Upon clicking of a result, you can see more information in a “quick view panel” | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg&quot;&gt;Search on Wikimedia Commons with Quick View&lt;/a&gt; | By Matthew Williams | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working through a myriad of wireframes, ideas, and approaches with the team, we began to arrive at some key areas we were going to focus on. One of the more visually obvious changes we started with was moving towards a grid layout that more effectively uses the space and highlights the media shown. Even with images around twice as large, we are able to show around three times as many results before needing to scroll. With as many results as we have, this helped users more quickly parse what Wikimedia Commons has to offer. Other interface improvements included surfacing all the different media types available upfront, making filters easier to find and use, and adding more information to a “quick view panel” upon clicking to eliminate the need to leave the page as often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Media_Search_and_Other_File_Types.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of Media Search while searching for other file types&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Examples of the different search experiences per file type | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Media_Search_and_Other_File_Types.jpg&quot;&gt;Media Search and Other File Types.jpg&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also separated the different types of media files into tabs. It became clear throughout the conversations with research participants that combining all file types into one result set was overwhelming, especially when the majority of visitors just wanted to search for images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/Media_Search_on_Mobile_Web.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of the search experience of Commons on Mobile Web&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshot of the new search on Wikimedia Commons on mobile web | &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Media_Search_on_Mobile_Web.jpg&quot;&gt;Media Search on Mobile Web&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With 30% of all Wikimedia Commons usage&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-3&quot; id=&quot;ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; on mobile web, we also wanted to make sure that all of these improvements were considered and easy to use on a mobile device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;community-input&quot;&gt;Community Input&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was clear from research and usability studies that we were making progress with those less familiar with Wikimedia Commons, but what about those who use it the most frequently, like the countless contributors and volunteers, galleries, libraries, and museums?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new search experience was designed and built with these communities’ involvement from the ground up, with Wikimedia Commons contributors involved from conception and design to prototyping to the final push for feature completion prior to launch. The team planned a robust feedback cycle for sharing, bringing in information, iterating, and communicating with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Community involvement began in May 2020 with sharing the ideas and designs, and by June the community was using a prototype. Over the next nine months, the development team would go through six distinct feedback cycles, with a total of 24 community members participating and leaving detailed ideas, comments, concerns, and questions to improve the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initial feedback was positive and helped us refine many aspects of the new experience. For example, one of the many pieces of useful feedback was a request for a filter that was able to search specifically for images that had received an assessment. Assessments are a system that the community has created to recognize important contributions across Wikimedia Commons, with groupings such as featured pictures, valued images, quality images, and picture of the day. This filter in particular was an excellent suggestion that we were able to implement that really sets Wikimedia Commons apart from other image searching tools with its human-powered curation at scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;results&quot;&gt;Results&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After making significant progress, we completed a wide array of usability tests to understand if the answers and changes we had applied from the initial baseline research were actually improving the experience. Here are some of the quotes from those interviews:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Much clearer and simpler to use. I prefer this version because the images are bigger. There were so many details in the old search that it was hard to see what was going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is comparatively much simpler and clearer to understand, with less space wasted in this format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It feels easier because it requires less clicking and the options are more visible. It also had more images to see at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is more intuitive, user friendly and easier to navigate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This feels much easier to operate and it is comfortable to use. It was much simpler in style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also conducted a survey in late December 2020/early January 2021, asking users directly if they had a preference for the new search experience or legacy search. We received 40 responses, again showing a preference for the new search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the evidence from that research and analysis, as well as the qualitative and quantitative feedback from the community, we decided to make this new search experience the default search on Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this update, we hope to have made finding and discovering this amazing treasure trove of freely usable media on the internet just a bit easier while honoring all of the hard work and contributions people around the world have made to Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Statistics&quot;&gt;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Special:Statistics&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=all-access&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=all-access&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=mobile-web&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&quot;&gt;https://pageviews.toolforge.org/siteviews/?platform=mobile-web&amp;amp;source=pageviews&amp;amp;agent=user&amp;amp;range=latest-20&amp;amp;sites=commons.wikimedia.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The new search experience on Wikimedia Commons</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/Search_on_Wikimedia_Commons.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Nurturing newbies: Growing Wikipedia contributors by Design</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nurturing newbies: Growing Wikipedia contributors by Design" /><published>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/06/12/growing-wikipedia-by-design.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@reetssydney&quot;&gt;Rita Ho&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the average person hears that I’m the designer on the Growth team for Wikipedia, there’s a common misconception that it’s about growing the number of readers, the more commonly thought of “Wikipedia user”.  However, our team was formed almost three years ago with a different challenge and audience as our focus. This article aims to tell the six-part story of how and why we started this team, and all the failures, learnings, and  successes we’ve had since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify the problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plant the seeds for Growth: Research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The set up: Team process &amp;amp; principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design experiments 1, 2, and 3: Down, up, and up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now what? Doubling down and scaling up&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-identify-the-problem&quot;&gt;1. Identify the problem&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s commonly known that Wikipedia is a multilingual project, one thing that may be surprising is how much variation there is between articles on the same topic in different languages. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canel%C3%A9&quot;&gt;French canelé article&lt;/a&gt; has a fairly different history on the origins for the small pastries than its &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canel%C3%A9&quot;&gt;English version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-1&quot; id=&quot;ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This is because each article version is written by its own community of editors, not machine translated&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-2&quot; id=&quot;ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The diversity and breadth of content across around 300 languages is awesome, but it also presents a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How might we grow knowledge across all languages?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Currently the largest Wikipedia language is English, with ~6.3 million articles&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-3&quot; id=&quot;ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Contrast this with the Hindi version (the 4th most spoken first-language, just behind English&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-4&quot; id=&quot;ref-4&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) with ~147K articles&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-5&quot; id=&quot;ref-5&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. This highlights the many knowledge gaps that exist on Wikipedia – and how it is a massive barrier to information access for those who don’t know English. To continue on the case of the canelé, (as of writing) there is no article about the deliciously rich heritage of these pastries documented on Hindi Wikipedia at all. Or to give a more ‘serious’ example of the knowledge gap (though one would argue pastries are a culturally significant item), the Hindi edition also lacks biographies for prominent figures like Nobel laureate &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ir%C3%A8ne_Joliot-Curie&quot;&gt;Irène Joliot-Curie&lt;/a&gt;, or conservationist &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dian_Fossey&quot;&gt;Dian Fossey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/irene-screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Iréne Joliot-Curie's English Wikipedia page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; Screenshot of “Irène Joliot-Curie” from &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irène_Joliot-Curie&quot;&gt;English Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; (2021) with a pop-up dialog on the bottom left with a message that the article does not yet exist in Hindi Wikipedia. | Accessed 2021-05-18 | text CC-BY-SA-3.0 | ™ Wikipedia logo | Other media in this image may be subject to other terms.
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia Foundation’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/vision/&quot;&gt;vision&lt;/a&gt; is to ensure that every single human being can freely share in the world’s knowledge, which can only be accomplished if more people contribute to that corpus of knowledge across all languages. Unfortunately Wikipedia has seen the number of contributors (a.k.a. editors) either stagnate or shrink over the years, and struggle to attract and retain new folks. A notable metric is that around 94% of first time editors don’t ever stick around to make a second edit&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-6&quot; id=&quot;ref-6&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The Growth team was formed at the Wikimedia Foundation in July 2018 to directly address this problem. There need to be significant increases in the number of contributors  as well as a more diverse contributor pool in order to supply knowledge that is relevant to everyone in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this in mind, the Growth team’s objective is to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase contributor &lt;strong&gt;activation&lt;/strong&gt; (people who make a first edit)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase contributor &lt;strong&gt;retention&lt;/strong&gt; (people who come back another day to make subsequent edits)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have also concentrated on working with smaller-to-medium sized Wikipedias to help promote the diversity of the contributors (rather than the larger, established language Wikipedias who tend to be an established homogenous group).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-planting-the-seeds-for-growth-research&quot;&gt;2. Planting the seeds for Growth: Research&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inception of our work actually began a year earlier with the “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/New_Editor_Experiences&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences&lt;/a&gt;” research project in 2017. This was a foundational research project aimed at learning as much as possible about new editors in Korean and Czech Wikipedias – two languages chosen as representative of many smaller Wikipedias. The project was conducted not only in collaboration with a research partner Reboot, but also with Wikipedians in Korea and Czech, with a “Community ambassador” role created for a long-term active member in each language, to encourage their communities’ participation in the project. In all, 64 interviews were conducted in Korea and Czechia to draw out a number of important insights about new editors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/new-editor-research.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a page of the new editors experiences research.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Left: &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:New_Editor_Experiences_summary_of_findings,_August_2017.pdf&amp;amp;page=12&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences summary of findings, August 2017 - Page 12&lt;/a&gt; | By Reboot and the Wikimedia Foundation | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; || Right: &lt;a href=&quot;https://meta.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences_user_personas,_August_2017.pdf&quot;&gt;New Editor Experiences user personas, August 2017 - Page 1&lt;/a&gt; | By Reboot and the Wikimedia Foundation | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of the research was identifying that contributors have very different motivations for editing (represented in the personas). Despite their differences, all these newcomer personas encountered one or more of these key barriers to editing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical barrier (e.g. How do I write in code?)&lt;/strong&gt; – Newcomers have trouble finding and using editing tools.  A lot of our editing tools can seem too overwhelmingly open-ended and complex for them to know where to even start.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptual barrier (e.g. What is “notability”?)&lt;/strong&gt; – How do they write the “Wikipedia way”? What does it mean when their subject is not notable enough? What is NPOV?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultural (e.g. Why are people so mean?)&lt;/strong&gt; – Newcomers are often unaware of the collaborative effort involved in writing Wikipedia. In turn, they can’t easily become part of the “community” of established and active editors, because they don’t know it exists. And for many, their first interaction is not positive because it’s someone telling them they did something wrong, or reverting their edit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/new-editors-barriers.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration showing three icons - no wikitext, warning sign and a sad message emoji&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration of the three key barriers (Technical, Conceptual, and Cultural) newcomers face when editing Wikipedia. By Rita Ho | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the different newcomer needs, motivations, and challenges being surfaced, the research concluded with a number of recommendations. This was where the Growth team came into the picture, as it was formed to take action on these recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Our aim was to experiment with design interventions to drive increases in activation and retention of newcomers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-the-set-up-team-process-and-principles&quot;&gt;3. The set up: Team process and principles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vanilla Ice once sang, “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ice_Ice_Baby&quot;&gt;Stop, collaborate and listen&lt;/a&gt;”. Our team works according to similar principles, but in a different order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-collaborate-in-the-open&quot;&gt;1. Collaborate in the open&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modelling on the success of the New Editor Experiences research approach, a core part of our process is to ensure close communication and collaboration with the communities in which we work. The first thing we did when the team was formed was to partner with four “pilot” languages (Korean, Czech, Arabic, and Vietnamese) that we would collaborate with in controlled experiments. In addition to the team’s Community Relations Specialist (a liaison between Wikimedia product teams and volunteer community members), we created a “Community Ambassador” role for each pilot language – a representative who helps us to collaborate with their respective members on a range of tasks such as translation, communicating our progress, and recruiting others to participate in our project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/growth-team-wikipedias-logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Logos of the Growth team and pilot wikis&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Top: &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Growth_team_logo_-_en.svg&quot;&gt;Growth team logo - en&lt;/a&gt; | By Rita Ho | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;  || Bottom (left to right): &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia/2.0#SVG&quot;&gt;Wikipedia logo 2.0&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-ar.svg&quot;&gt;Arabic&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-cs.svg&quot;&gt;Czech&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-ko.svg&quot;&gt;Korean&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Wikipedia-logo-v2-vi.svg&quot;&gt;Vietnamese&lt;/a&gt; | By Wikimedia Foundation &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt; (™ Wikipedia logo)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notably, not only do we collaborate with our communities, but because it’s Wikipedia – anyone can be a part of the community – so we work in the public. We post in-progress designs and engineering updates that anyone interested can react to and give feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-listen&quot;&gt;2. Listen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We listen to all the feedback coming back on our work, from usability testing on early stage designs through to analysing data from our released experiments in order to decide how to improve. We also listen to our community partners, and try to ensure there is sufficient flexibility and adaptability in designs to work for different groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-stop-if-its-not-working&quot;&gt;3. Stop (if it’s not working)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very important work principle we try to keep in mind is that experiments fail. When we see something is not working, we try to make a clean stop and take learnings from that failure to make the next experiment better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, nested in this last principle is making sure we are measuring results rigorously, and running &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Treatment_and_control_groups&quot;&gt;controlled experiments&lt;/a&gt; for everything we try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-design-experiments-1-2-and-3-down-up-and-up&quot;&gt;4. Design experiments 1, 2, and 3: Down, up, and up&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate our process and journey, I’d like to talk about three key experiments our team has worked on based on major recommendations from the design research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-help-panel-a-helpful-failure&quot;&gt;#1 Help panel: A helpful failure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/growth-help-panel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of the help panel&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Screenshots of the Help panel open over the “Hamlet” article from four Wikipedia languages (left to right: Arabic, Czech, Korean, and Vietnamese). | Text from Wikimedia projects are &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-3.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our first experiments was based on research recommendations for better &lt;strong&gt;in-context help&lt;/strong&gt; (small doses of help relevant to the activity being done at that moment), as well as &lt;strong&gt;human-to-human help&lt;/strong&gt; (providing a real connection to a friendly person in the community). In a nutshell, the feature was a help panel tool available to newcomers when they opened an article for editing, and allowed them to search and/or ask questions to experienced users about how to edit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for this design to work in practice, not only did we consult with all our pilot wikis for buy-in on the idea, via our ambassadors, but we needed these very experienced editors from each language to sign up to answer questions. So community engagement was doubly important for this experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The engagement with the help panel was quite high&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-7&quot; id=&quot;ref-7&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; considering its ancillary placement and function, so we considered it a positive sign that newcomers want in-context and human help.  An interesting tidbit was that there were cultural differences in the usage, where Koreans asked very few questions compared to the other pilot wikis. However, per our “Stop if it’s not working” principle, we ultimately didn’t see any change in more people starting to edit or being retained, so we paused further iteration and went to try a different idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-newcomer-homepage-a-welcoming-place&quot;&gt;#2 Newcomer homepage: A welcoming place&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Newcomer homepage was the second project built as a result of  the usability testing of our earlier work, where we noticed a lot of test participants expected a dashboard or some homepage to orient themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we created this “newcomer homepage” that gives them that clear place to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its first iteration, it contained a few different modules that help someone learn about editing, encourage them to create a user page, and seek help from both the help desk or from a specific experienced editor assigned as their mentor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was encouraging to see people engaging with this page and returning to it on multiple days to take different actions. One of our most important observations was that the most popular button was for creating a “user page”, which is like a user profile in which newcomers can identify themselves to others.  The engagement with this button gave us a very strong signal that newcomers will start contributing if given a call-to-action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/interaction-percentage.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot showing interaction percentages&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Image is a derivative of &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Homepage_mockup_2019-04-24.png&quot;&gt;Homepage mockup 2019-04-24&lt;/a&gt;, by Alessandro Contini, used under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;, with percentage values added to indicate the different amount of interactions from newcomers on various parts of the homepage, showing the “create user page” call to action as having the highest percent of clicks. This image is licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt; [Rita Ho].&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-newcomer-tasks-suggestions-to-get-started&quot;&gt;#3 Newcomer tasks: Suggestions to get started&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A natural next step after seeing newcomers interacting and seeking out editing actions on the newcomer homepage was to give them opportunities to edit actual Wikipedia articles. We did this in the form of newcomer task recommendations, a feature we call “Suggested edits” on the homepage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on foundational research and cumulative feedback from previous experiments, we knew that many newcomers either arrive with a very challenging edit in mind (e.g., write a new article from scratch) from which failure becomes a demoralising dead-end, or else they don’t have any edits in mind at all, and never find their footing as contributors. The “Suggested edits” module offers tasks ranging from easy tasks (like copyediting or adding links), to harder tasks (like adding citations or expanding articles) that newcomers can filter to based on their specific interests (e.g., copyedit articles about “Food and drink”). This feature is intended to cater to both groups – a clear way to start editing for those who don’t know what they want to do, and for those who do have a difficult edit in mind, it provides a learning pathway to build up their skills first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/suggested-edit-mobile.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshots of Suggested edits on mobile&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Suggested_edits_-_sample_mobile_screens.png&quot;&gt;Suggested edits - sample mobile screens&lt;/a&gt; | By RHo (WMF) | &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY 4.0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since its launch, and as we added more editing guidance and improvements to the homepage design over multiple iterations and variant tests (a subject for another post), we’ve seen steady increases in edits and number of editors using it. In other words, the release of this experimental feature saw us succeed in increasing editor activation and retention. 🙌 🙌&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-now-what--doubling-down-and-scaling-up&quot;&gt;5. Now what?  Doubling down and scaling up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The success we saw in the pilot languages meant that we are able to work on the next great problem to solve: how can we scale up and encourage all the other Wikipedias to adopt our features?&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#note-8&quot; id=&quot;ref-8&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Luckily, one of the benefits of working in this somewhat slow-and-steady approach is that as the team consults with the different language communities, we’ve got a lot of supporting data and built up a lot of trust from collaborating with our pilot communities which has helped encourage many language communities to sign up. To date, we’ve added the features to 35 Wikipedias, which, when accounting for the relative sizes of the languages, amounting to nearly half (42% to be exact) of all newcomers to Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/languages-with-growth-features.png&quot; alt=&quot;List of languages where growth features are enabled&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Illustration showing that the 35 Wikipedia languages which currently have the Growth team’s newcomer features accounts for nearly half of all newcomers (new accounts) on Wikipedia. | By Rita Ho CC BY-SA 4.0, Wikimedia Foundation CC BY-SA 3.0 (™ Wikipedia logo)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the time it has taken from the initial failed experiment with the help panel to the modest success we’ve had so far in increasing new contributors, these were my biggest realisations about what it is to design with and for the open community of communities that is Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of collaborating with communities for adoption &amp;amp; understanding.&lt;/strong&gt; Collaborating with our communities is paramount for trust, acceptance, and improved user experience&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experimenting with an open mind&lt;/strong&gt; (and being ready to fail with a next plan).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There’s no one size fits all for everyone.&lt;/strong&gt; Accepting that actually, there is no perfect design for everyone. Seeing how different cultures and languages react to and use the same design differently has made me realise the importance of allowing a degree of customization, to empower different communities to figure out what’s best for them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change takes time and perseverance&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-whats-next&quot;&gt;6. What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve now established a good cadence to our experiment-and-scale-up-on-success approach, and as the Growth team features become available on more Wikipedias, our ultimate goal is that one day these will no longer be experiments but a core part of welcoming editors to the Wikipedia community. So, mission accomplished right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thankfully, my job as a designer is not done here.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that all the design interventions so far have been about trying to get newcomers to succeed by giving them access to help and suggestions to edit using the existing editing interface. At the moment, if someone selects a suggested edit to “copy edit” an article, they don’t receive any specific pointers about what part of the article needs help with fixing spelling or grammar. Our newcomers still need to know which of the many editing tools they should be using, and will often need to ask for more guidance. And that’s what instigated our team’s latest design exploration: &lt;strong&gt;Structured tasks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea is that instead of guiding people through the current complex, open-ended editing UI, we create new, easier ways to edit. And we will do this by breaking down editing tasks you can do on Wikipedia into a series of single smaller steps or “structured tasks” instead. Something that newcomers can quickly and easily accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very first structured task that we have designed is to review suggestions by an algorithm to make words in a Wikipedia article link to other articles, and we are again approaching this by seeing how this new task type is working firstly for our pilot Wikipedias by the start of June 2021. I’m anxiously optimistic about  how this next experiment goes, fodder for  another post, but until then (and until there’s time for another blog post), you can learn more about our work on our &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Growth&quot;&gt;team page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;
Cover image by Rizzelli Stefania. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:MUFFE_E_LIEVITI_ISOLATI_NELLE_FARINE_ALIMENTARI.jpg&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-4.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks Marshall Miller, Jessica Klein, and Margeigh Novotny for your feedback and editing help.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;footer&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;note-1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;Digression: As of 2021-05-17, the French version of the Canelé article talks about its creation being connected to wine production in the Bordeaux region: since only egg whites were used in the “fining” wine process, the excess egg yolks were used in canelé-making. This is contrasted with the English article which focuses on the origins of the name, and is much more circumspect about its origins.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;Wikipedia does, however, also offer a pretty great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Content_translation&quot;&gt;Content Translation&lt;/a&gt; tool that helps multilingual people translate articles into different languages they know.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-3&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-4&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-4&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_languages_by_number_of_native_speakers&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_languages_by_number_of_native_speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-5&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-5&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindi_Wikipedia&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindi_Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-6&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-6&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; Ripstra, A. &amp;amp; Quinn, N. (2018). “New Editor Experiences, Wikimania 2018” [PDF Presentation]. Slides 4-5. Available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimania2018.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences,_Wikimania_2018.pdf&quot;&gt;https://wikimania2018.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:New_Editor_Experiences,_Wikimania_2018.pdf&lt;/a&gt; (Accessed 2021-05-18)
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-7&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-7&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; 13-29% of newcomers opened the help panel. Of those, 43-59% took some action.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;note-8&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref-8&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;Some of you may be flummoxed that it is a necessary step at all to encourage the different communities to adopt our features. This is one of the interesting things about designing for Wikipedia! Communities have the option to not adopt the features we create, literally being able to change or turn off features if their particular community has not reached consensus. This is what makes developing trust and collaboration particularly vital, and also helps explain our slower pace of change.
&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/footer&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Reflections on a multi-year effort now bearing fruit</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/isolated-food-flours.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/nurturing-newbies/isolated-food-flours.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bringing Wikipedia to the homescreen on iOS</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bringing Wikipedia to the homescreen on iOS" /><published>2021-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/26/bringing-wikipedia-to-the-homescreen-on-ios.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://carolynlimadeo.com/&quot;&gt;Carolyn Li-Madeo&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepakmantena.com/&quot;&gt;Deepak Mantena&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Apple introduced an update to &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/system-capabilities/widgets&quot;&gt;widgets&lt;/a&gt; with iOS 14, the Wikipedia iOS team was excited to take the opportunity to rethink our own. With the ability to place widgets right on the home screen, the team was curious about how we could highlight Wikipedia content in a way that was visually engaging, glanceable and up-to-date. For our first suite of home screen widgets, we built off of elements from the app’s Explore Feed to design and build three new widgets for iOS 14: On this day, Picture of the day and Top read on Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, we’ll share some of our widget building process – from design to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of various iOS widgets&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Widget designs we explored throughout our product process&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;design-principles-for-the-wikipedia-ios-widgets&quot;&gt;Design principles for the Wikipedia iOS widgets&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iOS team defined the following design principles at the start of the project, which helped us to decide what features to highlight in our new widgets as well as to prioritize features like dark mode and supporting all three sizes for each of our widgets. These principles also guided the visual and interaction design of the widgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;content-first&quot;&gt;Content first&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This design principle comes from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://design.wikimedia.org/style-guide/design-principles.html#trustworthy-yet-joyful&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Design Style Guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;People come to Wikimedia projects for their content. Our solutions should help to facilitate its creation, consumption, and sharing — without getting in the way. Our content (facts, images, quotes, etc.) is our most representative element, and needs to be emphasized in our solutions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came to applying this principle to our widgets, we used this guidance to place a strong focus on the beautiful images and community written content in our widgets. Great encyclopedic content is why many people love Wikipedia and we wanted to ensure that our designs placed Wikipedia content front and center, with other design elements like graphs and headings taking a supporting role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focused&quot;&gt;Focused&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Home screens can easily become cluttered or distracting. With so many different apps, widgets and notifications pulling readers in different directions each time that they open their phone, we didn’t want to add to the noise or create unnecessary friction. We aimed to design widgets that were beautiful, glanceable and focused on a single element or content type from Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dynamic&quot;&gt;Dynamic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Wikimedia projects are constantly changing and evolving. The projects are shaped by volunteer contributors from across the world. Readers also make their mark on Wikipedia, by following their unique interests and learning more about current events. With this in mind we want to highlight and celebrate the liveliness of Wikipedia with designs that reflect the dynamic nature of the Wikimedia projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;customizable&quot;&gt;Customizable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Widgets can come in three sizes (small, medium and large) and two reading themes (light and dark). We want to ensure that our readers can access the information that they are interested in, in a layout and theme that works well for them. Building off of the frameworks provided by Apple, we want to ensure that people can read comfortably (and in their preferred language, when available), regardless of the time of day or night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;designing-the-wikipedia-ios-widgets&quot;&gt;Designing the Wikipedia iOS widgets&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it came time to begin designing our widgets, we looked to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/videos/play/wwdc2020/10103/&quot;&gt;WWDC 2020 talk on designing widgets&lt;/a&gt; and the information available through &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/ios/system-capabilities/widgets&quot;&gt;Apple’s Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. We wanted to ensure that whatever widgets we designed would adhere not only to our defined design principles but also to Apple’s design guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some key takeaways from Apple’s guidelines were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilize a standard margin of 16pts for comfortable reading and design consistency.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on highlighting content that will change often to avoid widgets becoming stale.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create designs for both light and dark mode, or focus on creating designs that will work in both reading modes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase information with each widget size. Larger widgets should contain more information than their size small counterparts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SF Pro should be used over custom fonts so that widgets look at home with widgets from other apps.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remember that the associated app’s name will appear under each widget, so it isn’t necessary to include app icons or  app names on the widget itself unless the widget is related to a content aggregator.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shapes inside of a widget should match the corner radius of the widget.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be mindful of how many deep links each widget size supports. As small widgets only support a single deep link, while there may be room to include more information, small widgets will only be able to link to a single location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We utilized the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/design/resources/&quot;&gt;templates provided in the Human Interface Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; to jumpstart the sketching process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-picture-of-the-day-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the Picture of the day widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-picture-of-the-day-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the picture of the day widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Picture of the day widget features beautiful, hi-res imagery from Wikimedia Commons&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Vulpes_vulpes_Mallnitz_01.jpg?fastcci_from=2194179&amp;amp;c1=2194179&amp;amp;c2=3943817&amp;amp;d1=15&amp;amp;d2=0&amp;amp;s=200&quot;&gt;Vulpes vulpes image&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Uoaei1&quot;&gt;Uoaei1&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first widget we designed was the Picture of the day widget. We wanted to start with something that would be easy to implement but also visually striking. Every day, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/Main_Page&quot;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt; community selects a freely usable image to be the ‘Picture of the day.’ These high-resolution images range from composite images of &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Acropoclipse.jpg&quot;&gt;lunar eclipses&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Glaciar_Margerie,_Parque_Nacional_Bah%C3%ADa_del_Glaciar,_Alaska,_Estados_Unidos,_2017-08-19,_DD_33.jpg&quot;&gt;striking landscapes&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:D%C3%BClmen,_Wildpark_--_2015_--_8894-8.jpg&quot;&gt;around the world&lt;/a&gt; (and much more).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing this widget we wanted to make sure that the beautiful images were given as much room as possible, with other necessary information (like copyright and the widget title) coming second. This widget really embodies our design principle of ‘Content first’ by placing an emphasis on imagery over secondary information. When designing this widget, we also had to consider how cropping might affect different aspect ratios and photo subjects. With each increase in widget size, more of the image is shown and on the largest size the first three lines of the image description are also displayed. Tapping on the widget in any size deep links you into a full screen view of the featured image in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this design, we did not make separate light and dark mode designs as the content is full bleed and we typically display description text over a dark background in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-on-this-day-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the On this day widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-on-this-day-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of on this day widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The On this day widget highlights an event that occurred on this day in history
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We love helping to ignite new &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki_rabbit_hole&quot;&gt;rabbit holes&lt;/a&gt; for our readers, so we created a widget that would change each day and encourage readers to check out an article they might not have read before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of this widget was based off of the ‘On this day’ card from the app’s Explore feed. Both the widget and the Explore feed card highlight the work of Wikipedia’s volunteer editors, who &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Selected_anniversaries&quot;&gt;compile and annotate lists of important events throughout history&lt;/a&gt; for each day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering how to adapt this feature from the app to the three widget sizes, we began first with the largest widget size. The largest widget size allowed us to include multiple tap targets (linking directly to the associated article or to a timeline view of the day’s events) and to include a splash of typography that illustrates the day’s date and date range. Including the timeline element also helped to create a sense of continuity between the widget and the existing feature on the app which utilizes the same timeline design. With the smaller widgets we focused more on the event text (removing the card representing the related article) and utilized a single tap target for both of these sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the feature is already available on the app in &lt;a href=&quot;https://diff.wikimedia.org/2017/12/04/ios-app-dark-theme/&quot;&gt;our four reading themes&lt;/a&gt;, it was easy to support both light and dark modes for this widget.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-on-this-day-widget-changes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of changes made&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Changes made after receiving feedback from designers at Apple
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing a first draft of our widgets, we received some very helpful feedback from the designers at Apple, who suggested we move the puck on the timeline up in order to better mimic the widget’s corner radius. It was a change of just a few pixels, but really helped to balance the visual design of the widgets and we were super grateful to have their feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-the-top-read-widget&quot;&gt;Designing the Top read widget&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-top-read-widget.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of the top read widget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Top read widget highlights which articles are popular in your language’s Wikipedia
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing what the world is reading on Wikipedia is a constant source of fascination for many readers and editors (ourselves included!). We had previously supported a Top read widget in the older iOS style and were glad to have the time to be able to update this widget and bring it to the home screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the first considerations with this widget was how to display articles that might not have an associated image, without needing to use a placeholder image. We wanted to avoid placeholder images as they don’t include relevant, encyclopedic content and can be repetitive if reproduced multiple times in a list. This was most important for the smallest size widget which only has space to link to one article. For the small widget with an available image we went with a full bleed image with a small spark map representing the popularity of the article over the past week. This sparkline was then enlarged and used as the primary imagery for articles that did not have an associated image. The sparklines were also included in the largest widget size, where we had just enough room to fit the top four articles, their associated sparklines and their title descriptions. For the medium sized widget we wanted to ensure that we could show more articles than were available on the small widget, so we focused on presenting two articles without their sparklines vs. one article with more meta information than we could show on the small widget size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This widget was also quite easy to translate into both light and dark designs as we were able to utilize our existing color palettes, which were designed to share the green used in the sparklines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-the-widgets&quot;&gt;Building the widgets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These new widgets also gave the engineering team an opportunity to experiment with new platform technologies. The widgets are implemented using &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/xcode/swiftui&quot;&gt;SwiftUI&lt;/a&gt; – Apple’s new user interface toolkit that aims to help bridge the gap between design and implementation. Converting the Top read sparkline we currently use in the app to SwiftUI provided valuable practical experience. It was encouraging to see potentially complex interface elements translate elegantly to the new framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Engineering work began during the early betas of iOS 14. The biggest implementation challenge we faced was using the unfinished development tools. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Debugger&quot;&gt;debugger&lt;/a&gt;, a tool used during development to examine the state of running widgets, often failed to work at all. Another challenge we encountered was balancing the expectation of always updated widget data with being considerate of the device’s battery life. This remains something we’re interested in refining – &lt;a href=&quot;http://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;contributions are always welcome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;increased-multilingual-support&quot;&gt;Increased multilingual support&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently the widgets utilize each reader’s primary language as set in app settings. We would like to provide a way for multilingual readers to set a language preference on a per-widget basis, which would enable readers to keep an eye on what articles are trending on multiple Wikipedias or see what was happening on this day in history across the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-dynamic-on-this-day-widget&quot;&gt;More dynamic On this day widget&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The On this day widget currently updates once a day and highlights a single event each day. In the future we would like to make this widget more dynamic by featuring multiple events each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;future-widget-ideas&quot;&gt;Future widget ideas&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to time constraints we were unable to build all of the widgets that we dreamed up. In the future we would love to update three of our older style widgets: Today’s featured article, In the news and Continue reading. Additionally we had some ideas around a widget that would enable you to jump straight into exploring Wikipedia with deep links into features like randomizer or reading lists. Finally, we had designed a map based widget that built off of our Places feature and would have enabled readers to quickly locate and read Wikipedia articles about landmarks near them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;join-us-in-developing-and-designing-new-widgets&quot;&gt;Join us in developing and designing new widgets!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;Wikipedia iOS app is open source&lt;/a&gt; and contributions are always welcome! If you are interested in &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T257370&quot;&gt;developing one of our already designed widgets&lt;/a&gt; or if you have an idea for something new, please do reach out! You can follow along with the team’s work on &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/project/view/782/&quot;&gt;Phabricator&lt;/a&gt; and file design or development tickets there, or feel free to contribute to the project on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wikimedia/wikipedia-ios&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Rita Ho, Robin Schoenbaechler, Matt Cleinman and Toni Sevener for editing help. Thank you to Deepak Mantena for writing the ‘Building the widgets’ section.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How we designed and built our iOS 14 widgets</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets-lead.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/wikipedia-widget/wikipedia-ios-widgets-lead.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How we hire UX designers at Wikimedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How we hire UX designers at Wikimedia" /><published>2021-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/04/07/how-we-hire-ux-designers.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;In the interest of providing more clarity over our hiring process, this article will attempt to answer some of the questions that people who want to apply for a UX design job at Wikimedia may have...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/lucyblackwell&quot;&gt;Lucy Blackwell&lt;/a&gt; : Senior Design Manager&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mission-alignment&quot;&gt;Mission Alignment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re a mission driven organisation on a quest to support every human being in freely sharing knowledge.  We’re a non-profit operating one of the world’s top five websites, Wikipedia. We believe that those who are passionate about our cause will be the best contributors to our mission. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/mission/#:~:text=The%20mission%20of%20the%20Wikimedia,disseminate%20it%20effectively%20and%20globally.&quot;&gt;our mission&lt;/a&gt; and these are our &lt;a href=&quot;https://wikimediafoundation.org/about/values/&quot;&gt;values&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So first things first, check them out before going any further, and just be honest… is this what you’re into? If so, why?  We want to know! It’s also totally fine if it’s not, but we really only hire people who are as passionate about our mission as us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; The best way to show us your passion for the role is in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cover_letter&quot;&gt;cover letter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-skills&quot;&gt;Design skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to know that you have all the design skills needed to do the job. We have high standards in the team which we want to uphold, so we’re looking for people who are motivated to do their best work with us, people we can support to grow and evolve here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our job descriptions outline the specific skills we’re looking for in each role, but just to briefly summarise, for any of our UX designer roles we seek folks that can envision and create experiences that reduce complexity. English Wikipedia has just celebrated its 20th birthday, and we are a fairly small design team for the size of our main website, so there are many legacy UX issues to be addressed. Designers at Wikimedia need to be able to break down a complicated existing experience and come up with a much simpler, clearer solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are a highly user-focused organisation with two key user groups on Wikipedia; the readers, and the editors (who we refer to as our community). Our community is very active and engaged, with many of the editors volunteering huge amounts of their time to write and edit content on Wikipedia. They have lots of great perspectives to add and are often the drivers behind the changes we decide to make on our platform(s). This means that for designers, we look for people who are comfortable, or excited by the opportunity to be very engaged with the community throughout their design process.  We value a transparent work style using open source platforms and public task boards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And lastly, we are a truly global product.  Wikipedia is available in around 300 languages. We design for everyone!  This means that many of the design decisions we make have to consider carefully the global reach of our platform. In addition, we need to make sure the platform we’re evolving is accessible too, so we do require a basic knowledge of how to apply accessibility standards to your designs, as part of our interview process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;your-portfolio&quot;&gt;Your portfolio&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your portfolio is going to be one of the best ways for you to show us your work before we’ve met.  We review portfolios to decide if we should chat further. No portfolio = no interview. For designers, portfolios are often more important than your CV or resume, this is because this is the place we can see how you think! When we look at portfolios we are trying to understand a few key things which are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the people you are designing for come first in your process?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have the ability to simplify complex problems?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you communicate your ideas and process clearly and simply?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you deliver effective solutions and pay attention to detail?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a hiring manager, I’ve had the privilege of looking through hundreds of portfolios over the years, and in my experience the ones that stand out are always those with 3 or 4 solid projects that clearly frame an interesting problem they had to solve and explain to me how they did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know designers spend hours and hours making their portfolios.  As you focus on the design of your portfolio, don’t forget the UX of your portfolio too. Your core user is going to be a recruiter or a hiring manager. That’s me! So here’s a few of my user needs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to be able to scan your portfolio in less than a minute, and find something that makes me want to look longer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to see your best work first. (I don’t need to see everything you’ve ever done)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to see your thinking process and how you break down problems.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I need to know what your specific role was in the projects you’re presenting.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I understand that some of your work maybe under NDA, so I need you to tell me about this work in another way, like a blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Keep it simple and just show your best work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;people-skills&quot;&gt;People skills&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On our job descriptions we state ‘The right person is better than the right set of experiences.’ Of course we need to know you have the design skills, but we’re less concerned with ‘&lt;em&gt;where’&lt;/em&gt; you developed those skills. What we feel is more important is if you’re a great collaborator and can communicate your ideas clearly. This is not an optional skill, we actually see this as a core requirement for working in our team.  This doesn’t mean you have to be an extrovert though, you might have developed your own unique way of collaborating and communicating with others that fits your personality and abilities.  It also doesn’t mean english needs to be your first language, we just need to know that you can communicate your ideas in english to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we’re a global organisation, it’s really important to us that our team represents some of the different aspects of the communities we serve.  We’re always looking to bring different perspectives into the team, because fundamentally we know that diverse teams deliver better products. This is why we’re a fully remote team. By hiring in many different places in the world, we have the best chance of attracting a wide-range of perspectives.  We currently have designers across 12 timezones from India to the USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; In the interview, come prepared to share specific examples of how you’ve collaborated with people and overcome challenges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;levels&quot;&gt;Levels&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UX designers in our team sit at 4 different levels based upon experience going from UX designer to Seniors, Leads up to Principals.  For each role, the job title and job description will show you what level of experience we’re looking for and what our expectations for your skills at that level are. Generally we won’t hire someone if they are over-qualified, or under-qualified for the level of the role we have listed, as this creates inequity in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll normally mention how many years of experience we expect someone to have at the level we’re recruiting for on the job spec, but this is purely a guide. We know that people grow and develop at different speeds and this is fine, so we’re really assessing your experience based upon the skills you demonstrate in your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;design-tasks&quot;&gt;Design tasks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tools that we use to assess what level someone is at is a design task. We’re very aware that this is now a fairly controversial debate in the design community, for lots of good reasons.  We recently took a step back and reassessed the pros and cons of design tasks, but ultimately came back to the decision to continue to ask UX designers and Senior UX Designers to do design tasks in a time-boxed manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for this is that we have found that our design tasks serve a few key purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They allow us to see how candidates approach a problem within a time constraint.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They give the candidate an opportunity to demonstrate their thinking process to us.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They allow candidates to be assessed more fairly against other candidates in the process who may have wildly different backgrounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One thing we have realised, is that people with more time often spend longer on their tasks than the suggested time period. Whilst this clearly shows their passion for the role, it doesn’t feel entirely fair to those with other commitments that simply couldn’t put as much time into their task.  So, we’re now trialling a slightly different approach to the process in our next recruitment round, in the hopes that we can make things a bit fairer and less of a burden on candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve now explicitly time box the task to a maximum of 3 hours.  We’ll ask the candidate to let us know what time and date suits them to do the task, then we will send the task out at that exact time via email.  The candidate is then required to return the task by email within 3 hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;our-interview-process&quot;&gt;Our interview process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each role, a hiring team is put together, each with specific roles in the hiring process. We have a step-by-step approach to interviewing, where you will have a series of interviews with different people from Wikimedia. Whilst there maybe some overlaps in questions, generally we try to make sure different areas are covered in different interviews. This process allows us to gather a collective view on a candidate. On average it can take approx. 1-2 months to complete all the steps in our process, although we’re currently looking at ways to speed this up. At any stage we may decide not to proceed further with a candidate as we don’t want to waste anyone’s time. Our process is continually evolving, but here’s where it stands today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 1: Interview with Recruiter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss your experience and why you’re interested in working at Wikimedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 2: Interview with Senior Design Manager&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss your background and design skills and where you’re looking to go in your career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 3: Design task&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Task will be sent out at a time of your choosing, upon which you will have 3 hours to complete the task and return it by email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 4:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Panel interview with Designers, Product Manager &amp;amp; UX Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Part 1 - Designers:&lt;/em&gt; Present and discuss your design task, followed by UX and design focused discussion about how your design approaches and ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 2 - Product Manager &amp;amp; UX Engineer:&lt;/em&gt; Discuss how you collaborate, agile development processes, accessibility guidelines and design systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Step 5:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Interview with the Senior Director of Strategy and Design&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Discuss product strategy and other related questions specific to your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Top Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; The interview process is as much for your benefit at ours.  We try to leave time at the end of every interview for your questions, so come ready to ask all the things you want to know…&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feedback&quot;&gt;Feedback&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well that’s it for now, but we’re always looking to evolve and improve our processes.  We’re keen to be sure our hiring process is a good experience for you, the candidate.  If you’ve got any thoughts that could help us improve this experience, do let us know.  We’re especially interested in how we could make our hiring process even more inclusive.  Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;
Cover image by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/people/37804979@N00&quot;&gt;Tony Hisgett&lt;/a&gt; from Birmingham, UK. Taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Coloured_Lights_2_(5129805518).jpg&quot;&gt;Commons&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/deed.en&quot;&gt;CC-BY-2.0&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This article attempts to answer some of the questions that people who want to apply for a UX design job at Wikimedia may have.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/colored-lights-hiring-ux-designer.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/colored-lights-hiring-ux-designer.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">People are talking</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="People are talking" /><published>2021-03-10T00:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-10T00:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/03/10/people-are-talking.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;Embarking on a design refresh of Wikipedia Talk pages — in three acts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;http://jessklein.is/&quot;&gt;Jess Klein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;prologue&quot;&gt;Prologue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, when I started making edits to Wikipedia, it felt illicit; like doing graffiti or writing notes inside a library book. I would open up the article editor and stare at the screen in disbelief that I could change a page by just typing a few words and hitting “Publish changes”. But there I was, making changes to the world’s biggest encyclopedia, a site that sees 250 billion page views a year (on average). It was simultaneously exhilarating and anxiety-provoking. Was I editing the page correctly? Was the content that I was adding valuable? Was someone going to check my edits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not know that Talk pages existed for at least a year into my editing adventures, and when I did learn of them, I misunderstood their purpose. With a name like Talk pages (on English Wikipedia), I thought they were literally pages to discuss whatever article it was connected to (if it was attached in fact to an article page), assuming that the Talk page on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;Artemisia Gentileschi&lt;/a&gt; would be a fan forum of sorts for admirers of this 16th-century artist. I have since learned that it works like this: every single page on Wikipedia has a corresponding page associated with it for discussions and these pages are called “Talk pages.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/talk-pages-top-level-navigation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Talk pages on mobile web&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;You can access Talk Pages the same way that you access articles (in the top level page navigation) on Wikipedia.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the purpose of Talk pages (the ones connected to articles), is to discuss with other volunteers ways to improve the article. So the Talk page on Artemisia Gentileschi is not a fan forum for her, but a set of conversations around how to improve the Artemisia Gentileschi article on Wikipedia. The page was actually created so that I could ask questions, ask for help or get reviews! I had found the secret entrance to an underground club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/not-fan-forum.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of a Talk page&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Definitely not a fan forum! This is what the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk:Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;Talk page&lt;/a&gt; connected to the article on Artemisia Gentileschi looked like on January 6, 2021 at 11:58am EST. It contains lots of suggestions on how to improve the content of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artemisia_Gentileschi&quot;&gt;the article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the thing about clubs is that you have to know the rules (what to wear, how to talk to people, is it appropriate to dance?) in order to be part of the club. As you might have guessed, I didn’t know the rules — I didn’t even understand the language that I had to use in order to communicate with other people. This page sort of looked like people were writing and responding to questions, but when I went in to ask some questions myself, I was a mess. I couldn’t figure out where to post new topics, where to click to reply, how to sign my name, or, (if I even got this far) how to tell if someone was replying to my questions. Everything was written with what’s called wikitext (but at the time I just thought it was some sort of code), and it didn’t have any of the affordances that I expected from a forum. I couldn’t just click, type and publish. I had to type special characters to thread my conversations! Those were just the technical issues that I had with the page, to say nothing about understanding editing policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/fight-club-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF from the movie Fight Club&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;This club was more like the club in the David Fincher film &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fight_Club&quot;&gt;Fight Club&lt;/a&gt;, in that no one discussed the rules. Image src: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.syfy.com/&quot;&gt;Syfy.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the middle of 2019, and in my role as Lead Designer at Wikimedia Foundation, I was given the opportunity to make improvements to the club, aka the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_project&quot;&gt;Talk pages Project&lt;/a&gt;. I knew it was going to be an important project because I could help other volunteer editors connect with each other and improve the quality of content on Wikipedia. But, did every new volunteer have to go on an adventure to discover these “secret” Talk pages? Did every volunteer have the same experience as I did? In this article I’m going to share how I’ve spent the past year approaching the research and user experience design of these powerful spaces within Wikipedia and I’ll wonder out loud about the future design interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-1-listen-to-the-experts&quot;&gt;Act 1. Listen to the experts.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I started to sketch, I did a lot of research to better understand how contributors were using Talk pages. Even though I had my personal experience on Talk pages to inform the work, I wanted to learn a few things: the history of Talk pages, how they are being used by people who are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_project/Glossary.&quot;&gt;Senior contributors&lt;/a&gt;, and how they are being used by more Junior Contributors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;community-consultation&quot;&gt;Community Consultation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I wasn’t starting from scratch. My colleagues had just completed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_1&quot;&gt;Talk page Community Consultation&lt;/a&gt;, which was basically listening to contributors evaluating their experiences with Talk pages. We heard from community members, who had a range of experience levels. However, at this stage we primarily were informed about the more experienced contributor’s experience (as Senior Contributors were the ones most likely to opt into conversations in the wiki forums). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_2_report&quot;&gt;We learned a few things about Senior Contributor’s experiences&lt;/a&gt;, including that some have important and complex workflows that any new design would need to respect. They identified opportunities for improvement of the look and feel, and interaction design of Talk pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a very small sampling of quotes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;threading-conversations&quot;&gt;Threading conversations&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“但一些编辑喜欢用“：”缩进，一些编辑则使用“*”。后者可以附带唯一ID，前者或会被视为页面内容（Content）的普通章节，可能有点问题.” — 笔尖留痕, Chinese Wikipedia&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some editors like to indent with “:” and some editors use “ * ”. The latter can be accompanied by a unique ID, the former may be considered a normal part of the page content. This may be a bit problematic. — 笔尖留痕, Chinese Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;templates&quot;&gt;Templates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Instead of actually moving the templates, perhaps this could be implemented as a “show/hide” option in the interface. Users who work with wikiprojects etc. could set all pages to “show templates” by default. A special “override” tag could be added to important administrative notices, making them visible to all users. — Dlthewave, English Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-list-the-good-and-the-bad&quot;&gt;A list. The good and the bad.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A list, trying to be brief. I’ll probably come back and update this. First the good:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(1) Everyone loves the idea of the talk page. Let’s keep them. :) (2) Pretty low barrier to participation. (3) Once you get the hang of it, it’s pretty easy. (4) Page history is indispensable. (5) Easy to revise what you’ve written.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The not good:(1) Overall formatting not as intuitive as they’re used to. (2) Too easy to forget signature. (3) Indenting and bulletting interchangeable and messy. Hard to keep track of where things are sometimes. (4) Accessibility issues. (5) Other people’s signatures don’t always make it clear who you’re talking to. Sometimes add to confusion. (6) Archives often hard to find. Harder to use. (7) Too often don’t get a response (only mention because there may be an intervention relating to discoverability of active editors). (8) Banners at the top can be overwhelming as the first thing you see. (9) Edit conflicts. (10) Some pages are overly long. — &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Rhododendrites&quot;&gt;Rhododendrites&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User_talk:Rhododendrites&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:Talk_pages_consultation_2019/Phase_1&quot;&gt;18:21, 24 February 2019 (UTC)&lt;/a&gt;, English Wikipedia&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The changes that contributors wanted to be made were clear. Talk pages are too similar to article pages in their appearance and functionality, but not similar enough in their interaction capabilities (including the use of the visual editor tool instead of solely the markup wikitext editing tool that I had first experienced when trying to add a comment several years ago). As you can see from the quotes above, different contributors had different pain points that they wanted to highlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, Danny Horn, Director of Product Management at the Wikimedia Foundation explained to me that “a key insight was that the users who are most impacted by feature changes should see a direct benefit of those changes.” This means that instead of expecting users to change their workflows and practices now, in order to benefit a different set of users in the future, we will need to focus on an approach that is informed by the experience of these contributors who have been using Talk Pages for frequently for many years (and in some cases, decades).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;previous-design-interventions&quot;&gt;Previous Design Interventions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people mentioned a previous attempt at rethinking the Talk page design called “Flow.” As Pau Giner, Principal Designer at the Wikimedia Foundation explained “Flow was conceived of as a new product to eventually replace Talk pages. Flow’s scope was around discussions, but Talk pages were used to support many other use cases such as a working space (drafting a paragraph before adding it to the article) or for decision making (voting). Part of the criticism was about the missing support for those.” Here’s an example of what Flow looks like below. In my opinion, it solves many problems that were identified in the consultation. It is easy to browse topics, it’s quick to start a new discussion, it’s obvious how to see responses, etc., so, why wasn’t everyone just using this? I followed up with Danny on this via a Slack conversation on January 6, 2021 asking him if the issue was the tool or maybe some larger issue with the way that the tool was socialized with the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It was a real problem with the tool, and the way that we were thinking about it. We assumed that it was okay to build a tool that couldn’t handle a lot of important senior editor use cases, because it would be easier for junior editors, and that was worth it. If we had gone ahead the way that we were planning to, we would have broken a lot of things without really understanding or respecting how important those broken things were. It was not the case that Flow was a great product direction, and the only problem was selling it to people. We had the wrong philosophy, and that led to bad product decisions.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow wasn’t compatible with the existing Talk pages. The strength of Flow and other interventions such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:LiquidThreads&quot;&gt;LiquidThreads&lt;/a&gt;, was that they were built around the constraint of providing a solid framework for structured discussions. For some, this constraint was freeing as commenting and starting new topics was finally clear to them. For others, it was too restrictive and the loss of source editing eliminated the flexibility core to their contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flow, if it had been fully developed, would have also provided new functionalities called “workflows”, such as the ability to count votes automatically, to close a discussion at a predetermined date, to conveniently hold cross-wiki conversations, to move individual discussions with their page histories, and to watch only specific discussions rather than whole pages — all things that experienced editors have requested. That said, it changed all the paradigms around page history and discussions and it limited experienced contributors from using the page the way they had been using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things that I took away from reviewing the work on Flow is 1. the new tool needed to consider the use of the tons of metadata that gets collected on Talk pages. 2.Many wikis actually still have Flow deployed and use it, so whatever we come up with in the future needs to be a better value to those wikis so that they would want to deploy our new set of features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/flow-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of the Flow product&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;A previous attempt at refreshing Talk pages was a project called Flow.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;researching-community-gadgets&quot;&gt;Researching Community gadgets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One really wonderful thing about designing for Wikipedia is that if a problem is a big enough issue on Wikipedia, then a community member has probably leveraged the fact that this is an open source project and built what’s called a gadget to attempt to fix it. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Extension:Gadgets&quot;&gt;gadget&lt;/a&gt; is a homemade tool that any Wikipedia can enable. The only catch is that it’s not officially supported by the Wikimedia Foundation. This means that even if the tool is a game changer, the community member who created it has to maintain the code and make adjustments based on feedback or bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/community-driven-idea-funnel.png&quot; alt=&quot;Illustration of community driven idea funnel&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;This process represents one framework that we use for feature ideation. It would be great in the future to have a more supported version of this currently very fragmented and not always obvious framework (a girl can dream).&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having been working in the open source design community for over two decades, I kind of take for granted the uniqueness of this kind of innovation framework. I discussed this with Wikimedia Senior Design Manager Lucy Blackwell who said that “Wikipedia is unique in that it is truly community-driven, meaning the community are ‘active creators’ of the platform itself, their vested interest is their passion for Wikipedia and the many hours they have put in personally to developing it. In stark contrast, one finds in most other organizations that when gathering feedback from the people who use the platform, they end up being ‘passive participants’ in the feedback loop, often paid or rewarded to provide an opinion, for which the organization will decide whether to uphold or disregard.” It gives me great pride to work in an environment that operationalizes its values, whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The way that I view gadgets is that:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whatever the quality is of that gadget, the problem was big enough that someone felt compelled to fix it (so there’s a usability issue with what’s currently deployed to all users that I should probably look into).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If lots of other Wikipedia contributors have installed the gadget, then it probably has some good ideas that were accepted by the larger community, so I should learn from them, and, if appropriate, uplevel the ideas by productizing them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two gadgets that were brought to my attention by community members that impressed the Editing Team were the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey/reply-link&quot;&gt;Reply Link&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Jack_who_built_the_house/Convenient_Discussions&quot;&gt;Convenient Discussions&lt;/a&gt; (authored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey&quot;&gt;Enterprisey&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/User:Jack_who_built_the_house&quot;&gt;Jack who built the house&lt;/a&gt; respectively). Both addressed key issues such as replying and threading and handled them with elegant and intuitive interaction design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/reply-link-gadget-gif.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Relpy Link Gadget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Here is a gif of the Editing Team Product Manager, Peter Pelberg and I testing out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Enterprisey/reply-link&quot;&gt;reply link gadget&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-2-newcomers-and-emerging-communities&quot;&gt;Act 2: Newcomers and Emerging Communities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(2019-2020)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading the reports from both phases of the consultation, I realized that the voice of Junior Contributors was missing from the conversation (despite several attempts from communities to reach out to this audience). Hearing directly from them would provide a complete picture of the potential opportunities for the design. In fact, one of the major reasons that this project was being undertaken in the first place was to make it easier for new contributors to communicate on wiki.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;usability-testing-with-junior-contributors&quot;&gt;Usability Testing with Junior Contributors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying where to start to do this research was pretty challenging because the contributors to the Talk page consultation weren’t 100% brand new to the site. They probably had some level of experience on Wikipedia and other Wikimedia wikis, whether that was editing content or some other kind of interaction. I decided to try out a widely used testing service. What I like about services such as usertesting.com is that they often attract multilingual testers and, because of their popularity, I could pre-screen and filter the testers to meet profile requirements that matched the experience goals of Junior Contributors. I pulled together a very basic persona (based off of what I could intuit from the Talk page Consultation as well as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/New_Editor_Experiences&quot;&gt;other research&lt;/a&gt; on new editors) and wrote a few simple protocols for testing common workflows, such as replying to or starting a new conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior Contributors did, in fact, deal with many of the issues that I was dealing with. Specifically, testing showed that it was hard to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;start a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;reply to a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;follow a conversation,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thread discussions within a conversation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Here are a few choice quotes from the usability testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There was too much information going on in the top section. It was painful looking at all the options that I could click and also read through what is at the top.” Ct2-d4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I was not easily able to find it, although it was right in front of me.” ct3-d1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Everything was painful, I got lost a couple of times, the layout is very difficult to digest with lots of text and too much colours that don’t mean much unless you are familiar with the site” ct3-d2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“If I got to this point, I’d give up. Regardless of what I was doing because it’s overwhelming.” ct3-d2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, people who I tested the tool with repeatedly described how outdated the tools looked, felt, and worked. That’s probably because the tools haven’t significantly changed in 15 years, so it’s time to upgrade and provide contributors with the modern web affordances that they have come to rely on. One usability tester even said “I was really thinking I was going to see something like a Reddit page or some kind of chat page where there are some boxes and you just put in what you want to add.” Ct2-d5&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/thread-colon.gif&quot; alt=&quot;GIF of Relpy Link Gadget&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;In order to thread a conversation on Talk pages, a user needs to add a colon and then write their response.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emerging-communities-have-started-to-leave-wikipedia&quot;&gt;Emerging Communities have started to leave Wikipedia!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to individual Junior Contributors, another key stakeholder that the Talk page Consultation didn’t go into depth exploring was emerging communities. These are wikis who have moved these kinds of conversations mostly off wiki and into other widely used platforms, such as WhatsApp or Facebook. Sherry Snyder, Community Specialist at the Wikimedia Foundation explained “Different communities have different approaches, and some of them find it easier to communicate off wiki, using third-party services.” So, after talking with colleagues on our Product Team, our goal with this project is not to tell these communities what to do, but to offer an appetizing alternative should they return to on-wiki communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;act-3-synthesizing-feedback-and-designing-a-strategy&quot;&gt;Act 3: Synthesizing Feedback and designing a strategy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(present day)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all of these data points, we needed to develop a strategy for how to work with the online communities to design these new series of interventions. I took a step back from all of the pockets of feedback I received and &lt;a href=&quot;http://opendesignkit.org/methods/journey-maps/&quot;&gt;created&lt;/a&gt; a journey map for a few common workflows. The journey map was asking the questions: What’s the current experience for a Junior Contributor talking to a Senior Contributors? And, in turn, what does that experience look and feel like for Senior Contributors? I asked the questions intentionally this way because, unlike previous attempts at solving the problems of the page, I wanted to represent a shared experience. As Peter Pelberg, product manager for the project described, “A core promise people need to depend on talk pages to fulfill is connecting them with others. In this way, talk pages represent a unique place in the software where Junior and Senior Contributors meet. As such, we needed to consider their individual experiences within the context of the productive interactions this work is intended to promote.” Talk pages are places for conversations (in addition to also being places where people draft and evaluate Wikipedia content and much more), so I wanted to represent that there are opportunities for reinvigorating that asynchronous collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;center&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/journey-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image of journey map of different personas&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/center&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A journey map shows what the current experience feels like and identifies opportunities for improvements.&lt;br /&gt;
    &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Discussion_Page_Reply_Journey_Map.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Link to a larger (more legible) image&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point we understood the problem space and had a few solutions that we could start to experiment with, but we needed to figure out how and when we were going to do it. In terms of how, our team developed three principles that would guide all of our decisions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make it easy to do the right thing&lt;/strong&gt;: it shouldn’t be a challenge for someone to follow a social convention, such as signing their posts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevate existing functionality&lt;/strong&gt;: wherever possible, build upon the functionality that existing contributors have come to know and use.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fix what doesn’t function&lt;/strong&gt;: don’t elevate functionality for the sake of elevating. Make sure that it works, and if it doesn’t, fix it. Once that’s done, make sure that it’s super easy to discover and use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that philosophy in mind, our strategy is to fix the core interaction touch points that everyone struggles with, to make it easier for contributors of all skill levels to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand the context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discover new discussion tools to get started&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acquaint yourself with the editing environment: technically understand the UI, conceptually understand that this is a public post, have an expectation as to how and where it will be posted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Type and format your post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Post&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find your post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A key part of this strategy is to continue to learn from the work that the communities are doing on gadgets and to develop an understanding of how people are using and adapting Talk pages regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;where-to-start&quot;&gt;Where to start?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question. That’s a tall list to work from, where should we even begin? Even though we know that there are issues with discovery and context, we decided to start after that point in the conversation timeline. We are going to start off by making it easier for contributors to use the tools and then follow that up by making it easier for folks to discover them. The advantage of this approach is that it’s more iterative than designing something wholesale and deploying it. We can make small incremental tweaks and test those tweaks before building on them further. When I was researching approaches, I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://articles.uie.com/death_of_relaunch/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Jared Spool which describes many times when companies went big with a design change and it just failed. Because of this area’s history of failed attempts, we wanted to avoid that and so we are moving slowly, asking lots of questions and testing with the online communities early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first post in a series dedicated to the design of Talk pages on Wikimedia wikis. Please continue to read and share ideas, opinions or questions. You can learn more about the project on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Talk_pages_project&quot;&gt;Project Page&lt;/a&gt;. In my next post I will dive into some of the first features that we are working on and share what it’s been like for contributors testing out the prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to: Ed Sanders, David Lynch, Danny Horn, Sherry Snyder, Benoît Evellin, Prateek Saxena, Carolyn Li-Madeo, Peter Pelberg, Pau Giner and Lucy Blackwell&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Unless otherwise credited, all images in this post are licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC-BY-SA-4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Embarking on a design refresh of Wikipedia Talk pages — in three acts</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/people-talking-header.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/people-are-talking/people-talking-header.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">In search of the perfect search for Wikipedia</title><link href="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="In search of the perfect search for Wikipedia" /><published>2021-02-19T00:26:32+00:00</published><updated>2021-02-19T00:26:32+00:00</updated><id>https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/2021/02/19/search-on-wikipedia.html">&lt;p class=&quot;post__excerpt&quot;&gt;The Android app team improved one of their core features—searching for articles on Wikipedia. Along the way of making discovery more intelligent, personalized and efficient, we experienced a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schönbächler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent project, the Android app team decided to improve one of their core experiences: searching for articles on Wikipedia. Community feedback and previous usability tests revealed, that the app’s search functionality was perceived as inconsistent. Our goal was to make the discovery process for readers more intelligent, personalized and efficient to present the right result at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/272698/global-market-share-held-by-mobile-operating-systems-since-2009/&quot;&gt;market share of 72%&lt;/a&gt;, Android is by far the most used Mobile operating system worldwide. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mediawiki.org/wiki/Wikimedia_Apps/Team/Android&quot;&gt;Wikipedia Android app team&lt;/a&gt; builds features for more than five million active readers per month. And it‘s not a secret, that the majority of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nextbillionusers.google&quot;&gt;next billion users&lt;/a&gt; are likely joining the internet on an Android device. What does that mean for the Wikipedia Android app? Uncle Ben from Spiderman said it best: “With great power comes great responsibility“.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be able to make an educated decision about one of our app’s core features, we had to take a step back and understand how people are using the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-do-readers-navigate-to-articles&quot;&gt;How do readers navigate to articles?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team collected usage data and insights from readers who had explicitly opted in to sharing their anonymized usage data. We wanted to understand how readers currently access Wikipedia articles in the Android app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/pageviews-by-source.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie chart of page views by source&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We discovered that the pageviews were almost equally distributed into thirds. At &lt;strong&gt;33.7%&lt;/strong&gt; the largest portion of readers, visit articles via links from other Wikipedia articles. This data supports the reader behavior known internally as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki_rabbit_hole&quot;&gt;Wiki rabbit hole&lt;/a&gt;, where reader[s] travel by navigating from topic to topic while browsing Wikipedia. &lt;strong&gt;30.7%&lt;/strong&gt; of readers enter into an article via external links, these readers likely perform a search request via their default browser and are taken to the Wikipedia article in the app. Finally, &lt;strong&gt;28%&lt;/strong&gt; of all article visits (1.5 million readers a month) utilize the internal search bar for their queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-the-data-tell-us&quot;&gt;What did the data tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We knew now that &lt;strong&gt;28% of all page views derive from the internal app search&lt;/strong&gt;. However, we wanted more insight on how the different internal entry points for search are used. To accomplish this, we had to dig deeper into the data. Together with our analytics team we explored how readers commonly used the internal search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we examined how the search experience worked and looked like. There were two main entry points to perform a search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-first-entry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First entry point:&lt;/strong&gt;Search input field at the top in the Explore feed, the app’s home screen.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-second-entry.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second entry point:&lt;/strong&gt; Search button in the form of a magnifying glass icon at the top of each article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data revealed that approximately 60% of all readers access the search via the first entry point, a search input field in the Explore feed. Around 35% of readers were searching via the search button at the top of article (second entry point). Since the majority of our user base uses Wikipedia to read articles, we expected that most readers rely on the search button at the top of an article – so this was a surprising insight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-usage-distribution.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pie chart of page views by source&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we asked ourselves if the search button in the articles is not obvious enough, as our hypothesis was that people were navigating back to the home screen to make use of the first entry point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-did-the-readers-tell-us&quot;&gt;What did the readers tell us?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To gain further insights about how search is used, our engineering team created three variants for a usability test. Each variant had a different design and position for the main Wikipedia search in the article. Our goals were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find out about pros and cons of each variant, with a specific focus on discoverability and speed of access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How discoverable is the search functionality in each variant?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can the specific variants be improved?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-a.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant A:&lt;/strong&gt; Full size search input field at the top of the article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-b.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant B:&lt;/strong&gt; Search icon at the top of the article, which is the current user experience.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-variant-c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant C:&lt;/strong&gt; Search icon at the bottom of the article.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant A&lt;/strong&gt; was inspired by the analytics insight that two-thirds of all readers search via input field in the home screen. This version put the search input field at the top of the article, as it is on the home screen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant B&lt;/strong&gt; was the existing search experience in the app. To save vertical space, the image ratio and treatment was also slightly different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variant C&lt;/strong&gt; featured a search button in the bottom toolbar. The goal of this variant was to provide a more ergonomic search experience that should reduce “thumb travel” when reaching it on a smartphone. Find in page was moved to the overflow menu at the top right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went for an unmoderated, task-based test on &lt;a href=&quot;http://usertesting.com/&quot;&gt;usertesting.com&lt;/a&gt;. Participants were given a set of tasks to complete in a 15-20 minute time frame and perform the test remotely. Check out more details about the test &lt;a href=&quot;https://phabricator.wikimedia.org/T266883&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your guess on which of the variants performed best in the usability tests?&lt;/strong&gt; I bet if Luke Wroblewski, aka Mr &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LukeW/status/454637989503590400?s=20&quot;&gt;“Obvious Always Wins”&lt;/a&gt; had guessed, he’d have guessed right. &lt;strong&gt;Yes, it was Variant A.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, participants had no issues finding articles after installing the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similar to what we saw in analytics data, all participants directly used the search input on top of the Explore feed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our hypothesis, that participants were remembering their initial action once they were prompted to search for another article from the article page, turned out to be true. All participants naturally used the search input in the article.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From observing participants, we assume that readers are familiar with the look, feel and functionality of a search input from web browsers, such as the default web browser on Android: Chrome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to these reasons, we decided to move forward with the large search input field at the top of the article. The change guarantees great discoverability for searching Wikipedia and as a bonus, the find in article feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-make-search-more-intelligent&quot;&gt;How did we make search more intelligent?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way of optimizing the discovery process for articles, we realized that there was room for improvement in how we handled search queries with no results. One of the amazing things about Wikipedia is that it exists in more than 300 languages. Notably, a third of our readers access articles in multiple languages and effortlessly switch between different language versions of Wikipedia. When using Wikipedia on web, these are completely separate websites: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;en.wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;de.wikipedia.org&lt;/a&gt;, for example. One of the strengths of the Android app is that we can make these boundaries disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example below, you’ll notice that, even though multiple languages have been set in the app, the German word “Schabrackenschakal” (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black-backed_jackal&quot;&gt;a type of jackal&lt;/a&gt;) outputs zero results in the old version of the app when English Wikipedia is selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-second-language.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Searching articles that exist in a second language currently output 0 results.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, &lt;strong&gt;there is a German Wikipedia article&lt;/strong&gt; for &lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schabrackenschakal&quot;&gt;Schabrackenschakal&lt;/a&gt;. The result of the search query could be improved, as a person who’s using the app in multiple languages may not be aware of the language they’re searching in. We designed a solution that indicates results from other language versions of Wikipedia. This sounds like a straightforward solution, but is brand new to Wikipedia. For the first time, readers are able to search Wikipedia in multiple languages at once. Let’s check out how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-no-of-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Instead of 0 results, a compact list of results for other languages is presented. In this example, the result in German is highlighted as a link.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-other-language.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;After tapping the list item, readers are taken to the search of another Wikipedia language version.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-other-language-article.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;And finally, tapping the top search results then takes readers to this friendly guy!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why we don’t show results from other languages in the same list rather than having this extra tap. We intentionally designed it this way to educate readers about how to search the different language versions of Wikipedia. Wikipedias in different languages can have  different content and articles might not exist across languages. The extra tap raises awareness. Plus, we didn’t want to make the slightest sacrifice in regards to search performance, and searching multiple Wikipedia languages would mean significant search speed reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-we-personalize-search&quot;&gt;How did we personalize search?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its core, the app is a browser designed to explore the contents of Wikipedia in the best possible way. Saved articles, tabs and history are a reflection of a reader’s interest. We wanted to embrace this fact and create and a more personal discovery experience for readers. The new personalized search is another highlight and a brand new experience in the world of Wikipedia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate how useful this is, here’s an example: During summer 2020, there was a brief moment in Switzerland where cinemas were open. As one of a few Hollywood blockbusters this year, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tenet_(film)&quot;&gt;Tenet&lt;/a&gt; made its way to the big cinema halls. A good friend, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/azumbrunnen_&quot;&gt;Adrian Zumbrunnen&lt;/a&gt;, and I have been big fans of the film’s director, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan&lt;/a&gt; for years and closely follow his career. Adrian and I were in agreement that the movie was average for Nolan movie standards, but I remember looking him up on Wikipedia that night. We were interested in rewatching Nolan’s older movies and landed on &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan filmography Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the end of the year when I was looking for Nolan infos in the Wikipedia Android app again. This was the result of that search query:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-previous-experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The previous experience:&lt;/strong&gt; a search for “nolan” results in results that are not relevant to my interest.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re now surfacing relevant search results based on the user’s history. Articles from open tabs, reading lists or your browsing history are shown first. The right result is presented at the right time. Here’s the new search results list in action:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;columns&quot;&gt;
  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-new-personalized-experience.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The new experience:&lt;/strong&gt; a search for “nolan” takes articles from your open tabs, reading list and search history into account.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

  &lt;figure class=&quot;third-width&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/search-new-personalized-experience-article.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot of Search on Wikipedia Android&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Personalized search results allow readers to more efficiently find the right results. Let’s dig into Christopher Nolan’s art!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to prioritizing articles that readers have interacted with in the past, we added a source indication in the form of the icons next to the article thumbnails. To ensure that readers aren’t in their own &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Filter_bubble&quot;&gt;filter bubble&lt;/a&gt;, we show a maximum of three personalized results at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The search for the perfect search never ends. Design is an iterative process and we’re going to continue monitoring community feedback and data in the upcoming months. All the features above are now available in the official &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot;&gt;Wikipedia for Android app on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;. The app is ad-free and free of charge, forever. With the Wikipedia Android app, you can search and explore 40 million+ articles in 300+ languages, no matter where you are. Our team is working on other exciting features like this, stay tuned! Let us know what you think about the updates, what you’d like to see in the app and even more importantly, which Christopher Nolan &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;film&lt;/a&gt; is your favorite one and why via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/WikimediaDesign&quot;&gt;@WikimediaDesign&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Lucy Blackwell, Pau Giner, Carolyn Li-Madeo, Volker Eckl, Jess Klein, Matt Cleinman, Shay Nowick, Cooltey Feng, Sharvani Haran, Johan Jönsson, Rita Ho, Dmitry Brant, Jazmin Tanner, Anthony Borba &amp;amp; Prateek Saxena for their contributions to this article or the features.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;related-links&quot;&gt;Related links&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.wikipedia&quot;&gt;Wikipedia - Apps on Google Play&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Polar_Bear_-_Alaska.jpg&quot;&gt;File:Polar Bear - Alaska.jpg - Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/statistics/272698/global-market-share-held-by-mobile-operating-systems-since-2009/&quot;&gt;Mobile OS market share 2019 - Statista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://foundation.wikimedia.org/wiki/Privacy_policy&quot;&gt;Privacy policy - Wikimedia Foundation Governance Wiki&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Nolan_filmography&quot;&gt;Christopher Nolan filmography - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notion.so/wikimediadesign/In-search-of-the-perfect-search-for-Wikipedia-ca2a939963694c13a18e784b4abd7abf&quot;&gt;Black-backed jackal - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schabrackenschakal&quot;&gt;Schabrackenschakal - Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/LukeW/status/454637989503590400&quot;&gt;Luke Wroblewski on Twitter: ”Obvious always wins.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;post__authors&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scblr&quot;&gt;Robin Schönbächler&lt;/a&gt; is a Senior Designer at the Wikimedia Foundation
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Android app team improved one of their core features—searching for articles on Wikipedia. Along the way of making discovery more intelligent, personalized and efficient, we experienced a surprise.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/polar-search-cover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://design.wikimedia.org/blog/assets/uploads/search-of-perfect-search/polar-search-cover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>